It's very commonly said that the root of most human
unhappiness is the sense that one's life
has no meaning.
This is, I suppose, most frequently said in circles
interested in psychotherapy, because the feeling
of meaninglessness is often equated with the
existence of neurosis.
And so many activities into which one is
encouraged to enter philosophies one is encouraged to
believe, and religions one is encouraged to join are
commended on the basis of the fact that they give life a meaning.
I think it's very fascinating to think out what this
idea itself means or what it is
intended. When it's said that life has to have a purpose.
Well, now it's pretty obvious, I think,
that when we talk about life having or not having a meaning,
we're not using quite the ordinary sense of the word meaning
as the attribute of a sign.
We're not saying, are we, that we expect this natural
universe to behave as if it were a collection of words signifying
something other than themselves.
It isn't a point of view which would reduce our
lives in the world merely to the status of signs.
All that is mortal or all that is perishable
is but a symbol.
And so a symbol of what?
What do we want to feel? What would satisfy us
as being the meaning
behind this world?
It's so often, you know, that we don't follow our
ideas and our desires through. Most of
the things that we want very fervently are things
that we've only half glimpsed. Our ideals are
very often suggestions, hints,
and we don't know really exactly what we mean when we think about it.
But there is this obscure sense
in which we feel that life ought to
have significance and be a symbol in at
least that sense, if not just so arid a
symbol as a mere sign. Or it
also may mean that life is meaningful.
An individual feels that his life amounts to something
when he belongs and fits in with the execution
of some group enterprise.
He feels he belongs in a plan.
And this too seems to give people a sense of great satisfaction.
But we have to pursue that question further too. Why is it
that a plan. Why is it that fellowship
with other people gives the sense of meaning?
Does it come down, perhaps to another sense of meaning?
That life is felt to be meaningful when one is
fully satisfying one's biological urges,
including the sense of hunger,
the sense of love, the sense of
self expression in activity,
and so on. But then again, we have to push that inquiry
further. What do our biological
urges really point towards?
Are they just, however things always
projected towards A future is biology and its processes
nothing but going on towards going on towards going on.
Or there's a fourth and more theological sense of the meaning
of life. In all
theistic religions, at any rate, the meaning of life is God himself.
In other words, all this world means a person,
it means a heart, it means an intelligence.
And the relationship of love between God and man is the meaning of
the world. The sight of God is the glory of God,
and so on. But again, here there's something to be further pursued.
What is it that we want in
love with a person, and even a
person in the sense of the Lord God?
What is the content of it? What is it that we are really yearning
after?
Well, now, if we go back to the first point,
taking Goethe's words, that all that is transitory is
but a symbol, and that we want to feel that
all things have significance. It does seem to me
that there's a sense in which we often use the word significance,
where the word seems to be chosen quite naturally,
and yet at the same time, it's not quite the right word.
We say, for example, often of music, but we feel it to
be significant when just at the same time,
we don't mean that it expresses some particular
kind of concretely realizable
emotion. And certainly it's not imitating the noises of
nature.
Program Music, you know, would simply imitate
something else, and it deliberately sets out to express sadness
or joy or whatever, is not the kind
of thing. I mean, so often when one listens to the beautiful
arabesque character of the Baroque
composers Bach or Vivaldi,
it is felt to be significant not
because it means something other than itself,
but because it is so satisfying as it is.
And we use then this word significance so
often in those moments when our
impetuous seeking for fulfillment cools
down and we give ourselves a little space to watch things
as if they were worth watching, ordinary things.
And in those moments when our inner turmoil has really
quietened, we find significance
in things that we wouldn't expect to find significant at all.
I mean, this is, after all, the art of those photographers
who have such genius in turning the camera towards
such things as peeling paint on an old door,
or mud and sand and stones on a
dirt road, and showing us there that
if we look at it in a certain way, those things are significant.
But we can't say significant of what. So much as significant of themselves,
or perhaps significance, then, is the quality of a state of mind
in which we notice that we
are overlooking the significance of the world by our constant
quest for it later.
All this language is of course quite naturally vague and imprecise
because I think the wrong word is used and
yet not entirely the wrong word. Because as I said, it comes so naturally
to us that in those moments
the significance of the world seems
to be the world seems to be what is going on now.
And we don't look any further. The scheme of things seems to
justify itself at every moment of its unfoldment.
You see, the reason you want to be better is the reason why you aren't.
We aren't better because we want to be.
Because the road to hell is paved with good intentions.
Because all the do gooders in the world, whether they are doing
good for others or doing it for themselves, are troublemakers on
the basis of Kindly let me help you or you'll drown, said the monkey,
putting the fish safely up a tree.
We white Anglo Saxon Protestants, British, German,
American have been
on a rampage for the past hundred or more years to improve
the world.
We have given the benefits of our culture, our religion, our technology
to everybody, except perhaps the Australian Aborigines.
And we have insisted that they receive the benefits of our culture. Even our
political styles are our democracy. You better be
democratic or we'll shoot you.
And having conferred these blessings all over the place, we wonder
why everybody hates us.
See, because sometimes doing good to others and even
doing good to oneself is amazingly destructive
because it's full of conceit. How do you know what's good
for other people? How do you know what's good for you?
If you say you want to improve,
then you ought to know what's good for you, but obviously
you don't, because if you did you would be improved.
So we don't know. It's like the problem of geneticists
which they face today. I went to a meeting of geneticists not so
long ago where they gathered in a group of philosophers and theologians and said,
now look here, we need help.
We now are on the verge of figuring out how to breed
any kind of human character we would want to have.
We can give you saints, philosophers,
scientists, great politicians, anything you want.
Just tell us what kind of human beings ought we to breed?
So I said, how will those of
us who are genetically unregenerate make up
our minds what genetically generate people
might be?
Because I'm afraid very much that our selection
of virtues may not work.
It may be like for example, this new
kind of high yield grain which is made
and which is becoming ecologically destructive when
we interfere with the processes of nature and breed Efficient
plants and efficient animals. There's always some way in which we have to pay for
it. And I can well see that eugenically produced
human beings might be dreadful.
We could have a plague of virtuous people.
Do you realize that any animal considered in
itself is virtuous? It does its thing, but in crowds.
They're awful.
Like a crowd of ants or locusts on the rampage.
They're all perfectly good animals, but it's just too much.
I could imagine a perfectly pestiferous mass
of a million saints.
So I said to these people, look, there's the only thing you can do.
Just be sure that a vast
variety of human beings is maintained.
Don't please breed us down to a few excellent
types. Excellent for what? We never know how circumstances
are going to change and how
our need for different kinds of people
changes. At one time, we may need
very individualistic and aggressive people. At another time,
we may need very cooperative, team working people.
At another time, we may need people who are
full of interest in dexterous manipulation of the external
world. At another time, we may need people who explore into
their own psychology and are introspective.
There is no knowing. But the more varieties and the more
skills we have, obviously, the better.
So you see here again, the problem comes out in genetics.
We do not really know how to interfere with the way
the world is. The way the
world actually is is an enormously
complex, interrelated organism.
The same problem arises in medicine because the body is
a very complexly interrelated organism.
And if you look at the body in a superficial way, you may see there's
something wrong with it. Here's chickenpox.
And those spots that itch that come all out, all over the place.
Well, you might say, well, spots are there. Cut them off.
So you kill the bug. Well, then you find you've
got real problems because
you had to introduce some bugs to kill the bug. It's like bringing rabbits into
Australia, and that starts going
all over the place and getting out of hand. Well, then you think,
well, now, wait a minute. It wasn't the bugs in the blood. There are bugs
all over the place. What was wrong with this person that his
blood system suddenly became vulnerable to
those particular bugs? His resistance wasn't up. Therefore, what you
should have given him was not an antibiotic, but vitamins.
Okay, so we're going to build up his resistance. But resistance to what?
You may build up resistance to this and this and this class of bugs.
But then there's another one that loves that situation, comes right in.
See, we Always look at the human being medically
in bits and pieces. Because we have heart specialists,
lung specialists, bone specialists, nerve specialists and
so on. And they each see the human being from their
point of view. There are a few generalists, but they realize
the human body is so complicated that no one mind can understand it.
And furthermore, supposing we do succeed in healing
all these people of their diseases, what do
we then do about the population problem? I mean,
we've stopped cholera, the black bubonic plague.
We're getting the better of tuberculosis. We may fix cancer and heart disease.
Then what will people die of? Well, then, let's go
on living. There'll be enormous quantities of us.
Then we have to fix this birthing pills
for everybody. Then we find what are the
effects, the side effects of those pills. What are the psychological
effects upon men and women of not breeding children in the usual
way? We don't know.
And what seems a good thing today or yesterday,
like ddt, turns out tomorrow to have been a disaster.
What seemed in the moral and spiritual sphere too,
like great virtues in times past,
are easily seen today as hideous
evils. Let's take, for example, the Inquisition in its own
day. Among Catholics, the Holy Inquisition was
regarded as we today,
regardless the practice of psychiatry,
you, you see, you, you feel that in curing a person of cancer,
almost anything is justified. The most
complex operations, the most weird surgery,
people suspended for days and days on end, on the end of tubes
with X ray penetration burning,
or people undergoing shock treatment, people locked
in the colorless, monotonous corridors
of mental institutions. In all
good faith, they knew that witchcraft and heresy
were terrible things, awful plagues
imperiling people's souls forever and ever. So any
means were justified to cure people of
heresy. We don't change.
We're doing the same thing today,
but under different names. We can look
back at those people and see how evil that was, but we can't see
it in ourselves.
So therefore, beware of virtue.
Lao Tzu, the Chinese philosopher, said the highest
virtue is not virtue and therefore
really is virtue. But inferior virtue
cannot let go of being virtuous and therefore is not
virtue.
Translated in more of a periphrastic way.
The highest virtue is not conscious of itself as virtue,
and therefore really is virtue.
Lower virtue is so self conscious that it's not virtue.
In other words, when you breathe,
you don't congratulate yourself on being virtuous.
But breathing is a great virtue. It's living.
When you come out with beautiful eyes,
blue or brown or green, as the case may Be you
don't congratulate yourself for having grown one of the most fabulous
jewels on earth, just eyes.
And you don't account it a virtue to see,
to entertain the miracles of color and form. You say,
oh, that's just, but that's real virtue.
Virtue in the sense, the old sense of the word, a strength
is when we talk about the healing virtue of a plant,
that's real virtue.
But the other virtues are stuck on their ersats,
their imitation virtues.
And they usually create trouble because
more diabolical things are done in
the name of righteousness. And be assured that
everybody of whatever nationality or political frame of
mind or religion always goes
to war with a sense of complete
rightness. The other side is the devil.
Our opponents, whether in
China or Russia or Vietnam, have the
same feeling of righteousness about what they're doing as we have on our side
and a plague on both houses.
Because as Confucius said,
the goody goodies are the thieves of virtue.
Which is the form of our own proverb. The road to hell is
paved with good intentions inspired.
Consider this a quick reminder. God playing hide and seek. My mission
is to find other. So then, here's the
drama. My metaphysics, let me be perfectly
frank with you, are that there is the
central self. You can call it God, you can call it anything you like,
and it's all of us. It's playing all
the parts of all beings whatsoever,
everywhere and anywhere,
and it's playing the game of hide and seek with itself. It gets
lost, it gets involved in the farest out adventures,
but in the end it always wakes up and comes back to
itself. And when you are ready to wake
up, you're going to wake up, wake up. And if you're not ready, you're going
to stay pretending that you're just a little poor little me.
And since you're all here and engaged in this sort
of inquiry and listening to this sort of lecture, I assume that you're
all on the process of waking up.
Or else you're teasing yourselves with
some kind of flirtation with waking up,
which you're not serious about, but I assume
maybe you are not serious but sincere,
that you are ready to wake up. So then
when you're in the way of waking up and finding out who you really
are, you meet a character called a guru,
as the Hindus say this word, the teacher, the awakener.
And what is the function of a guru? He's the man who
looks at you in the eye and says,
oh, come on, I know
who you are. You know, you come to the guru and say, sir, I have
a problem, I'm unhappy and I want
to get one up on the universe or I want to become enlightened, I want
spiritual wisdom. Ah. The guru looks at you and says,
who are you? You know, Sri Ramana
Maharshi, that great Hindu sage of
modern times. People used to come to him and say, master, who was
I in my last incarnation? As if that mattered.
And he would say, who is asking the question?
He'd look at you and say, basically go right down to it.
You're looking at me, you're looking out and you're unaware of
what's behind your eyes. Go back in and
find out who you are, where the question comes from, why you
ask. And if you've looked at a photograph of
that man, I have a gorgeous photograph and you
look in those. I walk by it every time I go out of the front
door. Look at those eyes and the humor
lilting laugh that says, oh, come off it,
Shiva. I recognize you when
you come to my door and you say, I'm so
and so. I say, haha, what a funny way God has come on
today.
There are all sorts of tricks, of course, that gurus play.
They say,
well, we're going to put you through the mill.
And the reason they do that is simply that you
won't wake up until you
feel you've paid a price for it.
In other words, the sense of guilt that one has or the sense
of anxiety is simply the way one experiences
keeping the game of disguise going on.
Do you see that? Supposing you say I feel guilty,
Christianity makes you feel guilty for existing,
that somehow the very fact that you exist is an affront.
You are a fallen human being.
I remember as a child when we went to the services of the church on
Good Friday, they gave us each a colored postcard
with Jesus crucified on it. And it said
underneath this have I done for thee. What doest thou for me?
You know you felt awful. You nailed that man to the cross
because you eat steak. You have crucified Christ because
you kill the bull. After all, you depend on it.
Mithra. It's the same mystery.
And what are you going to do about that? This have I done for thee?
What dost thou for me? You feel awful that you just exist at all.
But that sense, that sense of guilt is
the veil across
the sanctuary. Don't you dare come in in
order to. You know, in all mysteries when you're going to be initiated,
there's somebody saying, don't you come
in, you got to fulfill this requirement, at this requirement,
of this requirement, of this requirement, then we'll let you in.
And so you go, you, you go through the mill
while. Why?
Because this is. You are saying to yourself,
I won't wake up until I feel I deserve it.
I won't wake up until I've made it difficult for me to wake up.
So I, I. I invent for myself an elaborate
system of delaying my waking up.
I put myself through this test and that test, and when I feel it's been
sufficiently arduous, then I may at last admit to myself
who I. And draw aside the veil
and realize that after all,
when all is said and done,
I am that I am, which is
the name of God.
And when it comes to it, that's really rather fun. They say
in Zen, when you attain satori, nothing is left you
at that moment but to have a good laugh.
But naturally, all masters,
Zen masters, yoga masters, every kind of master puts
up a barrier and
says to you,
simply plays your own game. You know, we say anybody who
goes to a psychiatrist ought to have his head examined.
Because you, when you go to a psychiatrist, you define yourself as
somebody who ought to have his head examined.
Same way the Zen masters say anybody who studies
Zen or comes to a Zen master ought to be given 30 blows with a
stick because he was stupid
enough to pose the question that he had a problem.
But you're the problem. You, you put yourself in
this situation.
So it's a question fundamentally, do you define yourself as
a victim of the world or as the world
sa.
You can't transform yourself. You can't
make yourself sane. You can't make yourself loving.
You can't make yourself unselfish.
And yet it's absolutely necessary that we be that
way. It's absolutely necessary
if we are going to hand over the
direction of nature to nature, which is
what it comes to. It's absolutely necessary
that we let go of ourselves. And it can't be done,
not by anything that we call doing it. Acting willing
or even just accepting things. You can't do it.
Why? Because you don't really exist
as that kind of a separate ego or personality.
It's just an idea based on a phony feeling.
So when it comes down to it,
it's shocking news for us,
for the human race, for our pride.
You're only making a mess by trying to put things
straight. You're trying to straighten out
a wiggly world, and no wonder you're in trouble.
So you can't do Anything. So you can't
transform yourself. And what can you do?
What happens then? If you actually realize you've come to a dead end
and the human race has come to a dead end, in my opinion,
what then? Commit suicide?
Or is there something else? What happens
when you just wait? There's nothing you can do.
You watch and
all you see is what goes on, that that is happening of
itself. You are breathing,
the wind is blowing, the trees are waving.
Your blood is circulating, your nerves are tingling.
It's all going on with itself.
Would you know that's you, that's the real you,
the you that goes on of itself.
It's not the symbol,
it's not the person, it's you
that's happening. As when you breathe. Yes,
you can get the feeling that I am breathing by shoving your breath.
But your breath goes on day in and day out
without you doing anything about it or even thinking of it. The same way
your brain is functioning without your forcing it.
So when you come to a dead end, and we are individually and
socially now in 1971,
at a dead end,
this is the moment of which it is said man's extremity
is God's opportunity because
we have to stop. And when we stop,
we find a world that is happening rather than
being done, being shoved.
And that happening, as distinct from
doing, is our fundamental self. And our fundamental
self is not something just inside the skin.
It's everything around us with which we
connect. When you look out of
your eyes at nature happening
out there, you're looking at you.
I'm not going to say what we should do from then on,
but simply that before we
think of doing anything in this critical situation,
we realize the completely illusory nature
of the beings that we think we are and
get back again to the beings that we
really are, which includes
all this outside
world no longer left outside.
I was explaining the
problem of how we thoughts
protect us from truth and what to do about
it. Showing various ways
in which the symbolizing process, which we
call thinking, the use of signs,
words, symbols, numbers to represent
what's going on in the external world or the world of nature.
It leads us into a curious confusion that
we confuse the symbolic process
with the actual world.
And the temptation to do this arises from the extraordinary
relative success that we have had in controlling
the world of nature with the power of thought.
But I don't know if it's ever struck you that we really don't
know whether we have successfully controlled it or not.
It could be argued a very strong case could be made that
the entire intellectual venture of civilization has
been a ghastly mistake.
And that we are now on a collision course.
And that all the vaunted benefits of intelligence,
technology and all that is
simply going to draw the human race to an extremely
swift conclusion. Of course, that might not be a bad
thing. I've sometimes speculated
on the idea that all stars
have been created out of planets.
You. You can't. You can't even imagine such a state of affairs
because you know it's
relative.
You have one row of caratids supporting a floor.
Very soon your children are the next row of carriages supporting
another floor. So that it gets higher and
higher and. But we don't really know where we began.
And we're always in the same place,
always hoping, always thinking that the
next time will be it. And this,
of course, is an eternal illusion. It's much better,
actually. One would be much happier to think that
there is. The future is simply deteriorating.
I can explain that very simply.
Human beings are largely
engaged in wasting enormous amounts of
psychic energy. In attempting to do things that are quite impossible.
You know, as the proverb says, you can't lift yourself up by your
own bootstraps. But recently I've heard a lot of references
in just general reading and listening where people say, we've got to
lift ourselves up by our own boots, bootstraps. And you can't.
And you can struggle and tug and pull till you're blue in the face
and nothing happens except that you exhausted yourself.
And the more we try,
you see, to put everything to rights,
the more we make fantastic misses and it
gets worse. And maybe that's the way it's got to be.
Maybe I shouldn't say anything at all.
Don't take me too seriously. I'm pitching a
case for the fact that the civilization has been a
mistake. That it would be
much better to leave everything alone.
That the wild animals
are wiser than we in that
they putting it in our crude and
not very exact language. They just follow their instincts.
Now, we who look before and after and predict and
are always concerned whether this generation is going to be better or worse
than the one that came before. We are tormented.
And we just don't realize,
because of this tremendous preoccupation with
time, we don't realize how beautiful we
are. Give me a
falcrum and I will move the earth. But there isn't one.
It's like, you know, betting on the future of the human race.
If I were really smart, I would lay a bet. The human
race will destroy itself. But the trouble is, there's nowhere
to place the bet.
And so, since I can't place the bed anywhere I'm involved
in the world must,
of course, try to see that it doesn't blow itself
to pieces.
Part of you which is supposed to improve you is exactly
the same as that part of you which needs to be improved.
In other words, there isn't any real distinction between bad me
and good I, between the higher self,
which is spiritual, and the lower self, which is animal.
It's all of a piece. You are this organism, this integrated,
fascinating energy pattern.
All sensible people, therefore, begin in life
with two fundamental presuppos positions.
You are not going to improve the world, and you are not going
to improve yourself.
You are just what you are Sa.
Give me some of that. Give me some of that.
When you are perfectly free to feel stuck or
not stuck, then you're unstuck.
Because actually nothing can stick
on the real mind. And you will
find this out if you watch the flow of your thoughts.
There is an expression in Chinese which
means the flow of thoughts, or what we call in
literary criticism, stream of consciousness.
And they put the character for thought three times,
nyan, nyan, nyan.
And so you will notice that thought
follows thought follows thought when you are just ruminating.
And those thoughts arise and
go like waves on the water all the time,
they come and go, and when
they go, they are as if they had never been here.
So actually, this shows your mind doesn't stick,
really. You can get the illusion of it sticking by,
for example, cycling the same succession of thoughts over
and over again. And that gives a sense of permanence
in the same way as when you revolve a cigarette butt in the dark.
You get the illusion of there being a solid circle, although there is
only the single point of fire.
And it is from this connecting of thoughts
that we get the sensation that behind our thoughts
there is a thinker who controls them and
experiences them. Although the
notion that there is a thinker is just one member in
the stream of thoughts. For example,
if you get a certain kind of rhythm that goes diggity diggy diggity diggy boop,
diggy diggy diggity diggity boop.
The boop is part of the rhythm,
but it can be used as a cue.
So you get in relation to diggy diggy diggy diggy boop.
You get thought, thought, thought, thought, thinker, thought, thought, thought, thought, thought, thinker.
And if this happens regularly enough and long enough, you get the illusion
of There being someone who thinks apart
from the stream of thoughts which come and go, the stream of experiences.
And we use such absurd phrases not only as thinking our thoughts,
but feeling our feelings, seeing, see sights and hearing sounds.
But you must understand, it is perfectly obvious that seeing a sight is seeing,
hearing a sound is hearing, feeling a feeling is
feeling. So in the same way thinking a
thought is thinking, but you get split minded,
you see, and so you get I and me and the
I who ought to or must control me as
sensation of some real entity that
stands aside from thoughts and chooses
among them, controls them, regulates them,
and so on. Actually,
this is a way to have one's thoughts not controlled.
The more there is this duality of
the separate thinker standing aside from the thoughts,
the separate feeler watching or feeling the feelings,
the more the stream of feelings is coaxed
into self protective activity,
into getting more and more like a stuck record, the purposes
of which are to protect and to aggrandize
and enlarge the status of the supposed thinker.
When Joshu, who was a Tang dynasty Zen master,
was asked, he had made some reference to the enlightened
mind being like a mind of a child.
And he said, well, what is the mind of a child? And he
said, a ball in a mountain stream.
Why, thought follows thought instantaneously
without interruption.
So the saying, walk or sit
as you will, but whatever you do, don't wobble.
Now, we can see this very clearly from confusions. We can get into
inactivity.
I have just said we can see this very clearly from confusions.
We get into inactivity.
What kind of a statement is that?
When I raise the question, what kind of a statement was it that I just
made? I'm beginning to talk about talking.
And one can do that provided you don't try to
do it while you're making the original statement.
If I want to say something about what I've just said,
then I must do it later, mustn't I? But not at the same time.
I cannot say, you are a fool, and at the same time
say, I am giving you an insult. In so many words I
cannot say, or in mathematics I cannot
write down a certain equation and as I am writing it down,
simultaneously state what kind of an equation this is.
Unless, of course, I invent an exceedingly complex language
which talks about itself as it goes along,
but in the ordinary way, people get completely mixed up by that.
In the middle of being about to say to somebody anything,
you start to think about whether this is the right thing to say
and you start wobbling. You get,
in other words, too much feedback.
And too much feedback makes any mechanism go crazy.
So in the same way, when you are very, very aware
of a difference between the deeds and the doer.
And the doer, while doing the deeds, is always sort of commenting on them,
the doer never really gets with it.
In other words, you are about to strike a nail,
and you wonder as you are about to hit it,
is this the right place to put it?
And so you probably hit your thumbnail
instead of the nail because you
don't go right through with hitting that nail.
This is not saying. Let me mark this again. It is not
saying that there should be no criticism
of thought. But if you
criticize thought, one thinking as if there were
a critic, thinker standing aside from the stream of thought,
then you get all balled up. And that is exactly
what happens in the process of attachment,
or what are called in Buddhist klesha,
which mean disturbing confusions of the
mind. And you see, this kind of confusion
is something which. To which the human organism is peculiarly liable.
Because the human organism has language,
has. You see, thinking is silent language.
And I mean language in the most inclusive sense of the word.
Not only words, but also images and numbers,
notation. Just because then we
can talk about anything. We can talk about talking,
we can talk about thinking, we can talk about ourselves.
As if we could stand aside and say, said I To myself,
Said I. All we are actually doing is
making a second thought or thought stream
which comments on the one that went before.
And then pretending that the second stream is a
different stream than the first.
That's because there are built into our minds all kinds of phony
images about memory. We think, for example,
of memory by analogy with engraving.
In order to remember something, we write it down.
And so we have a flat and stable piece of paper, and we
make marks on it with a pencil. And they stay there.
So we begin to think. Is mental memory something of the same kind?
Is there something stable upon which the
passage of thoughts makes an impression?
We say, he impressed me very much.
This was a lasting impression on my mind,
as if we were tablets. Indeed, the philosopher locked
use the expression tabula rasa, or clean slate,
to describe the mind of a child. This is a mind which
has not yet collected any memories, as if there were
some sort of surface which
accumulated these things and preserved
them. And that's me. But you see,
this superstition is related to
a much more ancient superstition that the world
consists of two elements, one of
which is stuff. And the other of which is form.
This is a myth based on a model of
the world which is fundamentally ceramic.
God,
what there is is you. And that should
be absolutely obvious, but it is not obvious at all.
That should be the simplest thing in the world.
That you, the I, is what has
always been going on and always will go on forever
and ever.
But we have been bamboozled by
religionists, by politicians,
by fathers and mothers, by all sorts of people
to tell us you're not it.
And we believed it.
So do you see now why if I put it to you
in this very negative way,
you can't do anything to change yourselves, to become better,
to become happier, to become more serene,
to become mystics or anything. If I say you
can't do a damn thing,
can you understand this negative statement in a positive way?
What I'm really saying is that you don't need to,
because if you see yourselves in the correct way,
you are all as much extraordinary phenomena
of nature as,
say, trees, clouds, the patterns
in running water, the shape of fire, the arrangement of
the stars, the form of a galaxy. You are all just like
that.
There's nothing wrong with you at all.
Except that I have to add this little flip.
You, you, you have in you. You do think there's something wrong.
See, then there's no question you do.
We all object to ourselves in various ways. And I'm
going to add, there's nothing wrong with that either,
because that's part of the flow. That's part of what is going on. That's part
of what we do.
So I don't. You see, what I'm actually going
to do is I'm going to deliver you from a sense of guilt because
I'm going to teach you that you needn't feel
guilty because you feel guilty.
Of course you feel guilty.
It's like someone put a match on you and you feel hot.
So they taught you as a child to feel guilty and you feel guilty.
You say, well, if someone comes along and says, well, you shouldn't,
that's not the point.
I'm going to say not that you shouldn't,
but that you do and don't worry about it.
And if you want to say further, but I can't help worrying about it,
I'm going to say to you, okay, worry about it.
This is the principle called in Japanese judo,
meaning the gentle way. Go along with it, go along with it,
go along with it.
So, therefore, this is the beginning of meditation.
You don't know what you're supposed to do.
What can you do? Well, if you don't know what you're supposed to do,
you watch.
You simply watch what's going on.
Like say somebody plays music,
you listen and you just follow those sounds
and eventually you understand the point of the music.
The point cannot be explained in words because music is
not words.
But after a while, in listening to any music,
you will understand the point of it and
that point will be the music itself.
I have often puzzled and puzzled about
what it must be like to go to sleep
and never wake up. To be
simply not there forever and ever
after all, one has some intimation of
this by the interval that separates going
to sleep from waking. When we don't have
any dreams but go to sleep and
then suddenly we're there again and in the interim
there was nothing. And if
there was never any end to that interval,
if the waking up didn't happen,
that's such a curious thought.
And yet, you know, I believe that although that's
rather gloomy kind of consideration,
I found that's one of the most creative thoughts I
ever thought in my life. And I keep going back to it.
You know, it's in line with a lot of the very fundamental
questions that children ask when they
say, mummy, who would I have been if you had
married someone else?
These are the kind of questions that make
us puzzle profoundly about our existence.
And one of the reasons why I think thinking about not
being about total non existence is
so creative is that in comparison
with that thought, the fact that we
are seems kind of queer,
incredibly odd.
But you know, in the Western world I suppose
we have two dominant ideas about
what happens to us when we die. There's the
old fashioned idea that after
we die we go to another world.
I say old fashioned, not to say it's out of date. We don't know what
the answer to this is,
but that's the traditional answer of the Western world.
When you die, you go to another life. Maybe heaven,
maybe purgatory, maybe hell, who knows?
I think nowadays though, the more general idea, the more plausible
idea to many people, is that when we die we
just cease to be. That's all there is to it.
But we're inclined, I think, to have in our minds a picture
of this which indeed is depressed of being
shut up in the dark for always and always and always to
be kind of buried alive in a blackness where we are
blind, deaf and dumb, but somehow still conscious.
But in the Eastern world there
are different ideas of this.
The major Eastern idea is what is generally known as
reincarnation of going through
life after life after life in an endless series.
Now, of course, when any idea
like that is explained, the first thing that we ask is,
is it true?
Is there a process of rebirth?
But you know, as this idea is held by
deeply thoughtful Hindus and Buddhists,
it isn't a belief in something which we can't prove. It's really
quite a self evident notion. Think of it in
this way. Supposing I make two statements.
Statement one, after I die,
I shall be reborn again as
a baby, but I shall forget my former life.
Statement two, after I die,
a baby will be born.
Now, I believe that those two statements are saying exactly the same
thing. And we know that the second one is
true. Babies are always being born. Conscious beings of all kinds
are constantly coming into existence after others
die. But why would I think
that the two statements are really the same statement?
Because after all, if you
die and your memory comes to an end end and you forget who you
were, being reborn again is exactly the equivalent of
somebody else being born. Because we have no consciousness
of our continuity unless we have memory. If the memory goes,
then we might just as well be somebody else.
But it seems to me that the fascinating thing about this
is that although a particular set of memories
vanishes, death is not the end
of consciousness. In other words,
we are deluded by a kind of fantasy.
If we think of death as endless
darkness,
endless nothingness is not only
inconceivable, but it's logically absolutely
meaningless. Because we aren't able to have any idea
or much less sensation of nothing unless it can be
compared with a sensation of something.
These two things go together.
And therefore I think what is meant is that
the vacuum created by the disappearance of a being, by the
disappearance of his memory system is simply
filled by another being.
Who is I. Just as you feel your eye.
The funny thing though, about being I, about feeling
that one is sort of a center of the universe, is that you
can only experience this I sensation in the singular.
You can't experience being two or three eyes all at the same
time.
Now then, it seems to me that this idea has
three very important consequences.
One is that the
disappearance of our memory in death is not
really something to be regretted.
Of course, everybody wishes to hold
forever to the memories and to the people and the situations
that he particularly loves. But surely
if we think this room, is that what, what we actually want?
Do we really want to have those we love,
however greatly we love them for always and always and always and always.
Isn't it inconceivable that even in a very distant future
we wouldn't get tired of it.
And this, indeed, is the secret of the thing.
This is why the demon of impermanence is beneath.
Because it is forgetting about things that renews their
wonder. Just think when you opened your eyes on
the world for the first time as a child.
How brilliant colors were, what a jewel the sun was,
what marvels the stars. How incredibly alive
the trees were. That's all because they were new to your eyes.
Or in the same way you know how it is. You've been reading a mystery
story, and you're looking around the house. You want something
to read. You pick up an old mystery store. If you read it
years and years ago. And you've forgotten all about the plot, it still excites you.
But if you remember the plot, it doesn't excite you.
And so, by the dispensation of forgetting,
the world is constantly renewed.
And we are able to see it again and again.
And to love again and again. To have people to whom we
are deeply attached and deeply fond.
Always with renewed intensity. And without
the contrast of having seen them
before. Before, before, before. For always and always and always.
Another consequence of this is
a very curious realization.
Remember that question. Who would I be if
my mother had married someone else?
Who, if I were you? We often
said one might so easily have been you.
I might so easily have been born in China and India. Why do
I feel that the world is centered in this place,
Distinct from some other place? You jolly well know the world is centered where you
are. And this
gives one a very strange feeling of
the idea that other people jolly well exist in the same sense you
do. Everybody's name is I.
That's what you call yourself.
So there will always be eyes in the world.
Every eye is, in a way, the same eye we
all might be anyone else. And there is
no escape. It goes on and on, on,
on. So long as there is consciousness anywhere, that is
I. You then, in a way look out through all eyes.
And that, perhaps, is the secret of the great virtue
of compassion.