The very fact that you are here at all to
listen to this sort of thing indicates,
as all philosophy indicates, that there is some unrest,
that to be a human being is in some way problematic,
that there is such a thing as a life problem,
and different people have different ways of expressing it.
But there is the reality of what is called in Buddhism,
dukkha, a very comprehensive word,
generally translated suffering, but which
might more accurately be called chronic frustration.
And I, first of all, want to try and identify what this human
problem is. And we start out from
the fact that most of us have a puzzle
with ourselves, not so much with other
people, but oneself.
Lots of people say that they do various things, like go to the
movies or get absorbed in work or read novels
in order to forget themselves. It's very commonly
said, I want to get away from myself.
And when we are left alone with ourselves in silence and there
is no distraction, civilized people, whether they
belong to the Eastern cultures or the Western cultures, tend to
feel uncomfortable. This is especially true of Americans,
who like to live in an environment of constant noise and
to keep their minds busy.
What is so much the matter with oneself that you can't stand it?
Well, first of all, we don't know what it is.
Yourself is the most difficult thing to get a look at,
because in just the same way that you cannot bite your own teeth,
that you cannot look straight into your eyes without the aid of a mirror,
that you are not apparently directly aware of your brain
for all this reason, yourself is too close to you for you to look at.
And it always remains an unknown, a kind of a blind spot in the middle
of everything. What color is
your head to your eyes?
Most people have a vague impression that behind the eyes there is a
blank. It isn't black, it certainly isn't
white, and you can turn around for all you're worth and never see it.
What is behind the eyes? We don't
know, but we have ideas
about it. And the dominant
idea which most people have is that there is something called
I. When you use the word I,
to what sensation do you refer?
In what way do you experience I as something existing?
Well, I've made a great deal of inquiries into this and
looking at it from the way most people talk,
they think of I myself as
a center of awareness and
of action, about halfway
between the ears and a little way behind the eyes.
Most people don't identify I myself with their
whole body. Because we say
in popular speech, I have a body, we are
not liable to say, I am a body.
We don't Feel that certain things that go on in
our bodies are things for which I, ego, am responsible.
We don't say I beat my heart.
We don't say I grow my hair. Because we
experience the beating of the heart and the growing of the hair as something
that happens to us.
We feel our bodies are vehicles, like cars which
were given to us by our parents and into which,
at some point in our development, the ego
was deposited.
Pop, when did you begin
to be you? All sorts of theories about that.
But generally speaking, I think of myself
as the source of voluntary action and
of conscious attention. And therefore
outside myself as I, both inside the body and definitely
outside the skin. Everything else is experienced as not I,
as other, as being very largely beyond
control and as in a way alien
to me. In the words of the poet Haussmann,
I, a stranger and afraid in a world I never made.
And here lies the root of problems,
because it appears that
I isn't really very permanent.
At least it's messed up with or mixed up with a body that grows
old and gets achy and inconvenient
and finally dissolves. Then what's going to happen to me?
Maybe I'm not afraid of actual death.
Especially if I believe that death is simply extinction,
total unconsciousness. There's nothing to be afraid of in that.
But it's the process of dying that's so inconvenient.
One is so hard to get rid of.
And so why, I mean, why am I trapped in this
situation? I didn't ask to
come here.
We say in popular speech, I came into this world.
We experience this world as other than ourselves, in the
sense that we say, you confront reality out there.
You must face facts out there. And facts
are always, of course, hard facts. Nobody ever talks about soft facts,
but there are lots of them.
So this sensation of. We could call it generally of alienation
from the universe.
Now, of course, it isn't true that you came into this world.
You came out of it as
leaves come out of a tree, as a baby comes out of the
womb. You're a symptom of the world
in the same way that when a tree produces
apples, you call it an apple tree.
And a world that produces people is a
world that peoples just as an apple tree, apples.
In fact, our whole situation of feeling that we are
strangers in the earth is a hallucination and
a rather dangerous hallucination because it
moves us to act upon the external world, both of people and
of things, in a hostile spirit.
So that we talk about the conquest of nature.
And this General feeling of resentment of being
involved. In a world where there are such
things as death, disease,
accidents, strife,
war, we feel put upon.
So the
various forms of Asian philosophy address
themselves directly to this problem,
but they are not like philosophy in the west,
and they are not like religion in the West.
If religion is something like Judaism or Christianity,
then Buddhism is not a religion.
If philosophy is something like the speculations
of Kant or Hegel or
even modern philosophers such
as Ayer and Reichenbach,
then Eastern thought is not philosophy.
The nearest thing to Eastern philosophy in the west is
psychotherapy, because the objective
of psychotherapy is to change the way in
which people feel. It is,
in other words, a technique for changing one's
state of consciousness. And so in exactly
that way, these systems that I'm going to talk to you about,
Hinduism, Buddhism and Daoism are primarily
methods for changing one state of consciousness.
If, for example, a person is crazy and feels that
he is the center of an enormous plot to persecute him,
the object of the psychotherapist is to disabuse him
of this illusion and get rid of his state of fear.
So, in a rather similar way, let us suppose
that normal people are simply
sharing a collective insanity,
which, because it's normal, they think is the. Is the ordinary way to
be. It is perfectly clear,
I think, that the world is insane,
that we are on a collision course,
and that therefore there is something to be said for the idea
that the normal person's state of consciousness might do with a change,
especially if it's a hallucination, and especially
if the way we feel our own
existence is in flat contradiction to
the way our existence would be described by a scientist,
such as a biologist or an ecologist or a
physicist. You know, I think ecology
is a very important science having to do with the relationship between organisms
and their environments. Now, when an ecologist
or a biologist looks at a living organism,
the business of science is to describe what's happening.
And he describes the living organism.
He finds out a very funny thing. He cannot describe
the organism defined as
something bounded by an epidermis without
also describing its environment. See,
science describes behavior. What is going on?
The man behind the microscope has this advice for you. Instead of
asking what it is, just ask, what does it do?
So the behavior of an organism cannot be
described without also describing the behavior of the environment.
If I describe somebody in the act of walking and
I say nothing about the floor or the area, the room
or whatever in which he's walking, all I'm describing is a body
in empty Space dangling its legs.
Well, that's not walking. To describe walking,
I have to describe the other behaviors or
processes going on around the organism. Well, what does that
tell me when I find that out?
It tells me that what I am talking about is
not the organism alone, but something for which
we've got only the clumsy term organism, environment.
Because, you see, that's what you are.
Imagine. How could you feel the existence of yourself
unless at the same time you felt something other?
How could you espy any kind of figure,
shape, form, unless at the same time you saw its background?
Supposing the outlines of my body were coterminous with your
whole field of vision. You wouldn't see me,
you'd see the microphone, the neck, tie or
pattern on the shirt. That would be the thing you were looking at.
Because you can only recognize anything if it goes along with the background,
which is telling us that figure and ground are
inseparable. They're different.
Yes. You have to get
the crucial idea of things being different but
inseparable.
As, for example, the two poles of a magnet are
inseparable. You can't have a one pole magnet,
but they're different. The two sides of a coin
are different, but inseparable.
And so there is a word that I've coined called go with.
There are certain things that go with each other,
and the organism goes with the environment.
And incidentally, the environment goes with the organism.
That's harder for us to see, but I shall explain it in due course.
A go withness is a transaction.
For example, when we buy and sell, that is a transaction.
Now, obviously you can't buy unless somebody is selling,
and you can't sell unless someone is buying. The operations
are different. Buying is different from selling, but they're inseparable.
And that suggests a certain kind of conspiracy between them.
They're explicitly different operations,
buying and selling, but they're implicitly one.
You and everything you call other are explicitly
different. But since you always find
these two aspects of experience together, there's a. There's a kind of
something fishy about it that
isn't noticed, that's been overlooked,
and that is that they're implicitly one.
But you see, in the ordinary course of events, as I've explained, we are not
aware of this. And we think that everything,
not self, or in other words, other,
is not merely different from us, but separate.
Therefore have this sense of not really belonging in this universe,
of finding nature a problem. And that's compounded by the
current superstitions of the modern world.
The mythology of 19th century science, which is everybody's common sense
today, that the world itself is stupid.
That it's a huge system of electronic
energy buzzing mindlessly,
in which we exist by virtue of some statistical flukes.
You know that if a million monkeys sat with a million typewriters for a million
years, in some course,
someday they would type out the Encyclopedia Britannica.
They'd eventually have to get around to it by just chance.
So there's the feeling among many people that what we are at this moment is
just such an event.
And that therefore, if we are going to maintain the human order,
our values, our reason, our civilization,
we've got to fight the world to maintain it.
Because the world is stupid. So in the
philosophy of science in the 19th century, you hear
people talking about energy lying
behind matter as blind energy. Freud defines
psychic energy as the unconscious. And furthermore calls it libido,
which means blind lust. It's stupid. The unconscious
is stupid. It wants pleasure and has
no sense of reality. And therefore Freud
would oppose the pleasure principle to the reality principle.
And therefore, civilization is always thought of as
being against pleasure. Because if you let people enjoy themselves too
much, they'll fall apart. Because the pleasure principle,
the pleasure urge, is stupid by definition.
So you see, then we have the sensation of living in
an alien world.
All this is further complicated by other factors which I must now go on
to explain.
The feeling of insularity, of being I,
alone and separate, has something
to do with the way in which we pay attention
to life.
And with the way in which we think about it. And these two things go
together. The task of any school teacher
with little children is to increase,
isn't it, their attention?
Spanish little children are
allegedly. Although this isn't always true, little children are supposed
not to pay attention to anything, particularly for very long.
They run from one thing to another. They look out of the window, they pick
their noses, they moon around. And so the teacher
has to wrap the desk and say, pay attention. And all
the little children know exactly what's expected of them,
that is, to wrap their legs tightly around the legs of the chair
and stare at the teacher with a slight frown.
That is, paying attention has nothing to do with paying
attention. It is simply an
act. But it. What it
does suggest is that we feel that paying attention or concentration
involves a certain strain.
You can't transform yourself. You can't
make yourself sane. You can't make yourself loving. You can't
make yourself unselfish.
And yet it's absolutely necessary that we be that way.
It's absolutely necessary if
we are going to hand over the direction
of nature to nature. Which is what it comes to.
Absolutely necessary that we let go of ourselves.
And it can't be done. Not by
anything that we call doing it. Acting willing, or even just
accepting things. You can't do it.
Why,
it's astonishing. All this is only 20 or
30 minutes from the heart of San Francisco.
Not a human habitation in sight anywhere.
I've been living out here for some months to
write and to absorb an atmosphere that
is different from the city. To try
and find out what is the essential difference.
Between the world of nature and the world of man.
Because there's an obvious difference,
like the difference of artistic styles. No one,
for example, would confuse a painting by Leonardo
with a painting by Picasso. And in the same way, there seems to
be a complete difference of style.
Between the things that human beings
do and the things that nature does.
Even though human beings are themselves part of nature.
On the one hand, nature is
wiggly. Everything wiggles. The outlines
of the hills, the shapes of the
trees, the way the
wind brushes the grass. It all wiggles.
And for some reason or other. We find wiggly things very
difficult to keep track of. And we say, well,
let's get things straightened out. Let's get this ironed out.
Let's get it all squared away.
And then somehow we think we understand things.
When we have translated them
into terms of straight lines and squares.
Maybe that's why they call rather rigid people squares.
But it doesn't fit nature.
You know, wherever human beings have been around
and done their thing, you find
rectangles. We live in boxes.
Our streets are laid out in a grid pattern.
Why, they even dropped a grid pattern on top of San Francisco.
With all those hills so that cars
run away. Because it
seems that the human being really has a very simple
kind of mind.
And all this wiggliness is too complicated.
I don't think it really is complicated. Because, after all,
it's very simple to move,
say, to raise something. Or to open and
close your hand. It's perfectly easy because we
don't have to think about it. Things become complicated
only when we think about them. And that's because
we are trying to translate them into a form of life.
Which is very much simpler and cruder. Than the
forms of life we're talking about. A triangle
is very much simpler and cruder than a mountain.
Even though you may represent a mountain with a
triangle. Human beings are
just as wiggly as nature and are brave.
Brains are an incredible mess of wiggles.
And that's the part of ourselves that we understand least of all.
I'm afraid the problem is partly due to Mr. Euclid, who invented geometry
because he didn't really measure the earth. He measured and gave
us ideas about the very simple forms in his own mind.
And perhaps we should come to the conclusion that he really had a rather weak
speaking intellect. Because sometimes
when I'm in the middle of all this,
I feel as if I were in the middle
of an amazing brain.
In other words, the brain is a network of interconnected
neurons. And each one of those neurons is a fairly simple
affair. Because it either fires or it doesn't
fire. It gives you the message on or off, yes or
no.
But what we call things, the plants,
birds, trees Are
far more complicated than a neuron. And there
are billions of them, and they are all
living together in a network. Just as there is an
interdependence of flowers and bees.
Where there are no flowers, there are no bees. And where there are no bees,
there are no flowers. They're really one organism.
And so, in the same way, everything in nature depends
on everything else. So it's interconnected.
And so the many, many patterns of interconnections.
Lock it all together into a unity. Which is, however,
much too complicated for us to think. Think about. Except in very, very simple,
crude ways.
But I am part of all this. I am,
as it were, one of the cells in this tremendous brain. Which I can't
understand because the part cannot
comprehend the whole. And yet.
And yet, at the same time, I don't feel like
so many people seem to feel that I'm
a foreigner or a stranger in this world.
Its aesthetic forms somehow appeal to
me more than most of the aesthetic
forms which men produce.
I feel in it as if in
the same way, when you see a flower in a field, it's really
the whole field that is flowering. Because the flower couldn't
exist in that particular place. Without the special surroundings of the
field that it has. You only find flowers in
surroundings which will support them. So in
the same way, you only find human beings on a planet of
this kind. With an atmosphere of this kind, with temperature of this kind
supplied by a convenient neighboring star.
And so, just as the flower is a flowering
of the field, I feel myself as a personing,
a manning peopling of the whole universe.
In other words, I seem like everything else to
be a center,
a sort of vortex at which the whole energy of
the universe realizes itself, comes alive.
A sort of aperture through which the whole universe is conscious of
itself. In Other
words, I go with it as a center to a circumference.
You know, the astrologers, in theory at least, may not have been
so far wrong when in trying to draw
a picture of a human mind or soul, they drew
a very crude map of the whole universe centered on
the time and place of the birth of that particular person.
It's not a bad idea, but I don't think
the astrologers know how to read their maps because the maps are too
crude. But the essential point is
obviously that each one of us,
not only human beings, but every leaf, every weed,
exists in the way it does only because everything else around it
does. In other words, there's a relationship between the
center and the circumference, which is rather
like the relationship between the poles of a magnet.
Without the center, no circumference. Without the circumference,
no center. And although we
say of poles that they're the poles
apart, that is to say, extremely different,
there's something between them. Just as the north and south poles of a magnet
are united by the magnet, so the individual
and the universe are inseparable.
But the curious thing is that while that's rather easy to
see in theory, very few people are aware of
it in a. In an important,
strong way like one is aware of blue in blue sky
or of the heat in fire.
It's more of an idea than it is of a realization.
And so it strikes me more
and more that our failure
to feel at home in
this astonishing brain in which we live is
the result of
a basic initial
mistake in our thinking about the world,
and is in turn the cause of
what is beginning to look like the failure of our technology,
of the fact that everything we're doing to try to improve
the world was a success in the short run,
made amazing initial improvements. But in the long run,
we seem to be destroying
the planet by our very efforts to control it and improve
it. And it strikes me
that that is because we are really too simple minded to
understand what we're doing. When we interfere with.
With the natural world strongly and on a vast scale,
we don't really interfere with it because that would suggest that we
were something different from it, something outside.
But I think what we're doing
is we are understanding it in
terms of languages,
numbers, in terms
of a logic which
is too simple for the job, too crude for the job to
begin with.
We understand everything in terms of words or numbers,
and they're stretched out in rows, in lines,
and our eyes have to scan those lines in order to understand them.
But when I scan this view, I don't do
it line by line by line.
I see the whole thing at once.
I take it in with, as it
were, a wide angle lens.
But when I try to understand the world through literature
and through mathematics, I have to scan
lines. You know, that's why it takes us so long to get educated in school,
because our eyes have to scan and
organize miles and miles of print and
that takes us 20 years or more to get through it.
But life happens,
changes go on too rapidly for that.
Because you see in the world everything is happening all together, everywhere at once.
And meanwhile we with our myopic little minds are
working it out step by step because we are greatly assisted
by the rapidity of the computer.
But even so, the computer is still looking at
things in rows. As the magnetic tape goes through and is scanned by the computer,
it's still all going along in a single track.
And I suppose then our difficulty is that we have lamentably
one track minds in an
infinitely many track universe.
And we may have to come to the alarming conclusion
that the universe is smarter than we are.
I've just come back from Los Angeles.
I was down there to meet with a group of rather
important people, people in the movie industry,
scientists and so on,
who were considering calling a
congress of the best minds in the world to meet
in Los Angeles in the near future to
be a kind of planetary alarm conference.
They wanted scientists and statesmen,
religious leaders, and to
do something to impress upon
the world through all the media that we
are in very serious danger of
destroying the biosphere, that is to say the whole
envelope of living creatures which covers this planet through pollution,
overpopulation, nuclear fallout,
poisoning of our food and very lack of food.
And we met to discuss the problem of organizing this conference.
And here were all these brilliant people and
it came over us that we really didn't know what we ought to say.
I mean, you can scream and create a state of panic, but that won't do
any good. And when
it came down to it, we didn't know what we ought
to say because we really don't know what to do.
Some things that we might do, for example to increase the food
supply with high yield crops may be ecological
mistakes. And so
the consensus of almost everybody at the meeting was that in some
way or other the human race has to learn how to leave
the world alone and let what is called the natural homeostasis,
that is the self balancing process of nature, take care of the
mess. Now, how are we going to do that.
This is Japanese ceremonial
tea. It's good on a cold day.
See, our problem is we don't really know how to stop. We've got something
stuck, started, and we see it's going in a wrong direction. And I
think the difficulty is to borrow an old Chinese saying
that when the wrong man uses the right means, the right means work
in the wrong way. In other words, there's something wrong with the way we
think. And while that is there, everything we do will
be a mess. Now, what is it that's wrong?
Now, as far as I can see, the basic mistake is
that we've invented this wonderful system of language
and calculation and
that it is at once too simple
to deal with the complexity of the world.
And also, we are liable to confuse that system
of symbols with the world itself, just as we confuse,
say, money with wealth. A lot of people are in business to
make money instead of wealth. When they make the money, they don't know what to
do with it.
And so, in the same way we confuse happiness
with status. And we confuse ourselves
as living organisms which are one with this whole universe.
Universe with something we call our personality.
Now, what is our personality? Our personality
is what we call our image, our image of ourselves.
And also our thought about ourselves, our idea of
ourselves. This is the person,
in other words, what people meet and understand.
And what I understand as Alan Watts is a big
act, which is not really me.
Because in the image of Alan Watts, there are not
all my unconscious processes, both psychological and physical.
The construction of my brain is not contained in the concept
Alan Watts. And the concept Alan Watts does not contain
the inseparable relationships which I have with all the rest of the universe.
And therefore, that concept is is a fraud.
And when it's mistaken for the real me, there's a confusion.
Because if somebody says to me, alan Watts,
do something about it. The concept Alan Watts can't do
anything. In other words, because it's only a
concept, you can't make it lift
a weight. Just as three is a concept. Three, the number.
You can't make just plain three do anything. So also,
you can't wrap up parcels with the equator. It's a useful imaginary line,
but it can't do anything. But we all
feel that this concept of ourselves, which we call our personality or
our ego, can do something because we think it
really exists. And I'll tell you why we think it exists.
What happens when you. If I were to say to you, now look
hard at the television screen, really look at it.
What do you do as distinct from just watching it in the ordinary way.
When you say, now I really got to see that, what do you do?
Notice that you tighten muscles all around here? That you frown
a little, you clench your teeth, perhaps. Now,
what has that got to do with seeing anything clearly?
Absolutely nothing to do with it. Same thing when you Listen carefully.
Now, listen carefully. Catch everything that's said, will you? Start tightening up
around your ears. That has nothing to do with hearing clearly.
Now, from the moment we were little children, when teachers in class screamed
at us, pay attention. We go tight in various ways.
Either to see or hear more clearly, to concentrate
or to will something which is supposed to be difficult to do.
And that constitutes a habitual tension over the whole body that's
there almost all the time. And that feeling of unnecessary
tension is, as it were, the material sensation upon
which we fasten this concept of I. We hang
it on to that feeling. The concept is
not us. The feeling of tension is completely
phony. It has nothing to do with success in seeing, hearing or acting.
And so we get the marriage of an illusion with a falsehood.
And that we call ourselves. And no wonder we feel cut
off from everything, alienated, frightened of life and death.
So what has to happen is we have to come back
to a sane view
of our own life. Which is
the way we really are. An organism functioning
in terms of the whole environment, with the whole environment.
Instead of this funny little separate personality. But how are we going to
do that? People say, oh, you can't change human nature overnight.
You're asking us to give up the ego. And that's
the most difficult of all things to do. Actually,
it isn't, because the ego doesn't exist.
But of course, if you try to give up your ego with your ego,
then it'll take you to the end of time.
Because this is the point. You can't transform
yourself. You can't make yourself sane.
You can't make yourself loving. You can't make yourself unselfish.
And yet it's absolutely that necessary that we be that way.
It's absolutely necessary.
If we are going to hand over the
direction of nature to nature, which is what it comes to.
It's absolutely necessary that we let go of
ourselves. And it can't be done.
Not by anything that we call doing it.
Acting, willing, or even just accepting things. You can't
do it. Why? Because you don't really exist
as that kind of a separate ego or personality. It's just an idea
based on a phony feeling. So when
it comes down to It. It's shocking news for
us, for the human race, for our
pride. You're only making a mess by
trying to put things straight. You're trying to
straighten out a wiggly world, and no wonder you're in trouble.
So you can't do anything. So you can't transform yourself.
And what can you do? What happens then if you actually
realize you've come to a dead end, what then?
What happens when you just wait? There's no nothing you can do.
You watch and all you see
is what goes on that is happening of itself.
You are breathing. The wind is blowing,
the trees are waving. Your blood is circulating,
your nerves are tingling. It's all going on with itself.
But you know that's you. That's the real you,
the you that goes on of itself.
It's not the symbol,
it's not the person. It's you that's
happening as when you breathe. Yes, you can get the feeling that
I am breathing by shoving your breath. But your breath goes
on day in and day out without you
doing anything about it or even thinking of it. The same way your brain is
functioning without your forehead. It.
So when you come to a dead end, and we are individually
and socially now in 1971,
at a dead end,
this is the moment of which it is said man's extremity is God's opportunity
because we have to stop, which includes
all this outside
world no longer left outside.
Sa I
have a friend, a girl, who's very intelligent and articulate,
and she was born blind. And she
hasn't the faintest idea what darkness is.
The word means as little to her as the word light.
So if you went to sleep,
you're not aware of darkness when you're asleep.
And so if you went into sleep,
into unconsciousness for always and always and always,
it wouldn't be at all like going into the dark. It wouldn't be
at all like being buried alive.
It would be as if, as a matter of fact, you had never, never existed
at all.
Not only you, but everything else as well.
You would be in that state as if you had never been.
And there, of course, there would be no problems. There would
be no one to regret the loss of anything.
You couldn't even call it a tragedy because there would be no one to experience
it as a tragedy. It would be simple,
nothing at all,
forever and for never.
Because not only would you have no future,
you would also have no past and no present.
Now, you would think that that was a point where we'd say, well, let's talk
about something else.
But I'm not content with that.
I demur because this makes
me think of two other things. This state
of nothingness makes me think first of all,
the. The only thing I. I get anywhere in my experience that's close to
nothingness is the way my head looks to my eyes.
Because I seem to feel that there is a world out
there as it were confronting my eyes.
And then behind my eyes there isn't
a black spot, there isn't even a hazy
spot. There's nothing at all.
I'm not aware of my head, as it were, as a black
hole in the middle of all this luminous visual experience.
It doesn't even have very clear edges because the field of vision is
an oval. And if I run my fingers along
my field of vision, it's like this. And this is
the point where my fingers just disappear from sight. Vague edged.
But then behind the this oval of vision there
is nothing at all. Just from the
sense of sight. Of course, if I use my fingers and touch,
I can feel something behind my eyes. But if
I use the sense of sight alone, there's just nothing there at all.
Now nevertheless,
out of that blankness I see.
Well, that's the first thing it makes me think of. Now the next thing it
makes me think of is this. If when I'm dead
I am as if I never had been,
then that's the way I was before I was
born. Because just as if I try to go back
behind my eyes and find what is there, I can't to a blank.
If I try to remember back and back and back and back,
I've got my earliest memories. And then behind
them, nothing. Total blank.
But just as I know there's something behind my eyes by using my fingers on
my head, so I know through other sources of information
that before I was born there was something going on. There were my
father and my mother, mother and their fathers and mothers,
and the whole material environment of the earth and
its life out of which they came. And behind that the
solar system, and behind that the galaxy,
and behind that all the galaxies. And behind that
another blank space.
What seems to me to be lacking in our Western religious
observances is some sort of social ritual
which gives an opportunity for spiritual experience.
That is to say, for a transformation of the individual consciousness
so that in one way or another the individual is
able to realize his oneness with the
eternal energy behind this universe,
which some people call God and others prefer not to name
or to conceive. So what I'm
proposing Instead of the ordinary kind of religious service, is,
as I said, a contemplative ritual.
The idea is not to have everybody shaken up and
whooping around, but to bring
about a state of profound peace.
So therefore, I should say something in a preliminary way about meditation,
or contemplation, as I prefer to call it.
Meditation is the act of allowing one's
thoughts to cease, stopping the agitation of thinking.
Thinking is talking to yourself. Now, if I
talk all the time, I don't hear what anyone else has to say.
Consequently, if I talk to myself all the time,
I don't have anything to think about except thoughts.
There is no interval between
thoughts during which I can come into touch
with reality. That is to say, the world which thoughts represent
as words represent events or as money
represents wealth. And so if I'm never silent in
my head, I'm living in a world of total abstraction,
divorced from reality altogether.
Reality itself is neither mental nor spiritual,
nor any concept that we can have of it. Reality is simply.
Now, therefore, to meditate. You might think that we attempt to suppress
thought. We do not do that because
you cannot meditate.
Let me put that in a more emphatic way.
You cannot meditate.
You, your ego image can only chatter,
because when it stops, it isn't there.
When you are not thinking, you have no ego, because your
ego is a concept. The thinker
behind the thoughts, the feeler behind the feelings, and the thinker
behind the thoughts is only a thought, an idea of some reference
point to which all our experiences happen.
And that, of course, cuts us off from what we experience. It makes a
great gap or gulf between the knower
and the known. And that
creates the spirit of alienation to the world from which we suffer.
Conflict, hate,
domineering, spirit arise from that basic division.
So when you come to an end of thought and you don't
know how to meditate, you don't know what to do with your mind. Nobody can
tell you. Then thinking comes to an end naturally. You can
begin meditation or meditation
happens. And that is happening is the
watching simply of what is,
of all the information to you conveyed by your exterior
and interior senses, and of the thoughts that
keep chattering on about it all. You don't try to stop
those thoughts. You just let them run as if they were birds twittering outside.
And they will eventually get tired of themselves and stop.
But don't worry about whether they do or don't. Just simply
watch whatever it is that you are feeling,
thinking, experiencing, and that's it. Watch it.
And don't go out of your way to put any names on it.
That's really what meditation is. And you see, you're not expecting
any result. You are in meditation, in an eternal
present. You are not doing it to improve
yourself. You found you can't do that. Your ego can't possibly
improve you because it's what's in need of improvement.
Your ego can't let go of itself because it is
a complex called clinging to oneself. That's what it is by definition.
So it's just something that evaporates when
it is understood that it is unable to achieve a
transformation of consciousness, mystical experience,
the vivid sense of union of individual
and cosmos.
So one of the easiest ways to enter into the state of
meditation is therefore listening to what
is using the sense of sound.
When you listen to sound,
you listen to it. Just the random sounds, you know, that are
going on in the room, in the street,
as if you were listening to music without
trying to identify its source, name it,
or put any label on it at all. Just enjoy
whatever sound may be going on.
Just listen. Now, we can go on
from that, listening to making
sound ourselves and also listening to it. And instead of
making sound, we learn the knack of letting it happen through us.
So then we get to what is in India called
the use of mantra words,
sounds chanted not for their meaning, but for their
sound. And thus everything that
will occur in the following celebration
will not be in the English language. It is
not intended to be understood in a discursive and intellectual sense.
You are asked only to dig the sound.
And I use the word dig advisedly because it means something
a little more than appreciate. It means enter into,
penetrate, get right to the bottom of. Because when you
are listening to sound and when you are letting sound hum through
you, this is one of the most obvious manifestations of the
energy of the universe. And I suggest
that churches get rid of their pews, where everybody is herded in like
cattle to look at the backs of each other's necks,
and that they spread their floor with rugs and cushions,
and that they have something in which people can approach
an ineffable, that means beyond words,
spiritual experience,
and not be told and forced
into a particular pattern of thinking of
mentation. So you see, for that reason,
I have only given the slightest suggestion of how
one uses these mantra or the silence for
meditation. You all have your own way of doing things like that.
Do it your own way. All this
is, is a vehicle, a support for
contemplation. Listen,
close your eyes, and go entirely into
a world of sound.
If I should say anything to you during this silence,
just listen to the sound of my voice and
don't worry about the meaning of the words.
Your brain will take care of that by itself.
The air which is playing with your ears is
also playing with your lungs.
If you let your lungs breathe as they wish to
without helping them,
watch what they do.
When they feel like breathing out,
let it go out, but don't assist.
When it feels like coming in,
let it come in, but don't pull.
Are you breathing or is it breathing?
You remember
there is no special state you are supposed to be in.
Simply let yourself be aware of whatever state you
are in. Don't name it,
just feel.
Now only is important.
Now, would you gently allow a
sound to arise in your imagination in
the ear of the mind? A sound that is pleasing to
you and
which you would feel natural humming and
letting your breath sort of fall out easily
and naturally hum the sound
out loud.