It's astonishing. All this is only 20 or
30 minutes from the heart of San Francisco.
Not a human habitation in sight anywhere.
I've been living out here for some months to
write and to absorb an atmosphere that is
different from the city. To try and find out what
is the essential difference. Between the world of
nature and the world of man.
Because there's an obvious difference, like the difference of
artistic styles. No one, for example, would confuse
a painting by Leonardo with a painting by Picasso.
Or museum by Bach with music by Shostakovich.
And in the same way, there seems to be a complete difference of
style. Between the
things that human beings do and the things
that nature does. Even though human beings are
themselves part of nature.
On the one hand, nature is
wiggly. Everything wiggles.
The outlines of the hills,
the shapes of the trees.
The way the wind brushes the grass,
the clouds, tracks of
streams. It all wiggles.
And for some reason or other, we find wiggly things
very difficult to keep track of.
And, you know, we say to people, keep still so that I can see you.
Keep still for the camera.
And we say, well, let's get things straightened out.
Let's get this ironed out. Let's get it all squared away.
And then somehow we think we understand things.
When we have translated them into
terms of straight lines and squares.
Maybe that's why they call a rather rigid people squares.
But it doesn't fit nature.
You know, wherever human beings have been around
and done their thing, you find
rectangles. We live in boxes.
Our streets, especially across states like
Kansas and Nebraska. Are laid out in a grid pattern. Why,
they even dropped a grid pattern on top of San Francisco with
all those hills so that cars run away.
Because it seems that the human beings
really has a very simple kind of mind.
And all this wiggliness is too complicated.
I don't think it really is complicated because, after all,
it's very simple to move, say,
to raise something. Or to open and close your hand.
It's perfectly easy because we don't have to think about it.
Things become complicated only when we think about them.
And that's because we're trying to translate them into a
form of life. Which is very much simpler and cruder than
the forms of life we're talking about.
A triangle is very much simpler and cruder than a
mountain. Even though you may represent a mountain,
a triangle.
Human beings are just as wiggly as
nature. And our brains are an incredible
mess of wiggles. And that's the part of ourselves that we
understand least of all.
I'm afraid the problem is partly due to Mr. Euclid, who invented
geometry because he didn't really measure the earth.
He measured and gave us ideas about the very simple forms
in his own mind. And perhaps we should come to the conclusion
that he really had a rather weakening intellect.
Because sometimes when I'm in the middle of all this,
I feel as if I were in the middle
of an amazing brain.
In other words, the brain is a network of interconnected neurons.
And each one of those neurons is a fairly simple affair.
Because it either fires or it doesn't fire.
It gives you the message on or off, yes or no.
But what we call things, the plants,
birds, trees, are far more complicated
than a neuron. And there are billions of them,
and they are all living together in a network.
Just as there is an interdependence of flowers and bees.
Where there are no flowers, there are no bees. And where there are no bees,
there are no flowers. They're really one organism.
And so, in the same way, everything in nature depends
on everything else. So it's interconnected.
And so the many, many patterns of interconnections lock
it all together into a unity, which is, however, much too complicated
for us to think about, except in very, very simple, crude ways.
But I am part of all this.
I am, as it were, one of the cells in this tremendous brain,
which I can't understand because the
part cannot comprehend the whole.
And yet, at the same time, I don't feel like
so many people seem to feel that I'm
a foreigner or a stranger in this world.
Its aesthetic forms somehow appeal to me
more than most of the aesthetic forms
which men produce.
I feel in it as if in
the same way, when you see a flower in a field, it's really the
whole field that is flowering. Because the flower couldn't
exist in that particular place without the special surroundings of
the field that it has. You only find flowers
in surroundings which will support them. So in
the same way you only find human beings on a planet
of this kind, with an atmosphere of this kind, with temperature of this kind
supplied by a convenient neighboring star.
And so, just as the flower is a
flowering of the field, I feel myself as a
personing, a manning peopling the whole universe.
In other words, I seem like everything else to
be a center,
a sort of vortex at which the whole
energy of the universe realizes itself, comes alive,
a sort of aperture through which the whole universe
is conscious of itself, self.
In other words, I go with it as a center to
a circumference.
You know, the Astrologers, in theory at least,
may not have been so far wrong when in trying to
draw a picture of a human mind or soul,
they drew a very crude map of the whole universe centered
on the time and place of
the birth of that particular person. It's not a bad idea.
But I don't think the astrologers know how to read their maps
because the maps are too crude.
But the essential point is obviously that each one
of us, not only human beings, but every leaf,
every weed,
exists in the way it does only because everything else around it
does. And in other words, there's a relationship between the
center and the circumference, which is rather
like the relationship between the poles of a magnet.
Without the center, no circumference. Without the circumference,
no center. And although
we say of poles that they're the
poles apart, that is to say, extremely different,
there's something between them. Just as the north and south
poles of a magnet are united by the magnet,
so the individual in the universe are
inseparable.
But the curious thing is that while that's rather
easy to see in theory, very few people are
aware of it in a. In an important,
strong way like one is aware of blue in blue sky
or of the heat in fire.
It's more of an idea than it is of a realization.
And so it strikes me more
and more that our failure
to feel at home in
this astonishing brain in which we live is
the result of
a basic
initial mistake in our thinking about the world and
is in turn the cause of.
Of what is beginning to look like the failure of our technology,
of the fact that everything we're doing to try to improve the
world was a success in the short run,
made amazing initial improvements. But in the long run,
we seem to be destroying the
planet by our very efforts to control it and improve it.
And it strikes me that that is because we are really too
simple minded to understand what
we're doing. When we interfere with the natural
world strongly and on a vast scale,
we don't really interfere with it because that would suggest that we
were something different from it, something outside.
But I think what we're doing
is we are understanding it in
terms of languages,
numbers, in terms of a logic
which is too simple for the job, too crude for the job to
begin with.
We understand everything in terms of words or numbers,
and they're stretched out in rows, in lines,
and our eyes have to scan those lines in order to understand
them. But when I scan this view,
I don't do it line by line. By line,
I see the whole thing at once.
I take it in with, as it were,
a wide angle lens.
But when I try to understand the world through literature and
through mathematics, I have to scan lines.
You know, that's why it takes us so long to get educated in school,
because our eyes have to scan and
organize miles and miles of print.
And that takes us 20 years or more to get
through it. But life
happens. Changes go on
too rapidly for that. Because, you see, in the
world, everything is happening all together, everywhere at once.
And meanwhile, we with our myopic little minds are working
it out step by step because we are greatly assisted by the rapidity
of the computer.
But even so, the computer is still looking at
things in rows. As the magnetic tape goes through and is scanned by the
computer, it's still all going along in a single track.
And I suppose then our difficulty is that we have lamentably
one track minds in an
infinitely many tracked universe.
And we may have to come to the alarming conclusion that
the universe is smarter than we are.
But, you know, that's you. That's the real you,
the you that goes on of itself.
It's not the symbol,
it's not the person. It's you
that's happening as when you breathe. Yes, you can get the
feeling that I am breathing by shoving your breath. But your breath
goes on day in and day out without your doing
anything about it or even thinking of it. The same way your brain is functioning
without your forcing it. So when you come to a
dead end, and we are individually and socially
now in 1971,
at a dead end, this is
the moment at which it is said man's extremity is God's opportunity
because we have to stop. And when we stop,
we find a world that is happening rather
than being done, being shoved.
And that happening, as distinct
from doing, is our fundamental self. And our fundamental self
is not something just inside the skin.
It's everything around us with which we connect.
When you look out of your eyes at nature happening
out there, you're looking at you.
I'm not going to say what we should do from then on,
but simply that before we think of
doing anything in this critical situation,
we realize the completely illusory nature of the
beings that we think we are and get
back again to the beings that we really are,
which includes all
this outside world
no longer left outside.
SA I've
just come back from Los Angeles. I was
down there to meet with a group of rather important people,
people in the movie industry, scientists and so on.
Who were considering calling
a congress of the best minds in the world
to meet in Los Angeles in the near future to
be a kind of planetary alarm conference.
They wanted scientists and statesmen,
religious leaders,
and to do something to
impress upon the world through all the media that
we are in very serious danger of
destroying the biosphere, that is to say the whole envelope
of living creatures which covers this planet through pollution,
overpopulation, nuclear fallout,
poisoning of our food and very lack of food.
And we met to discuss the problem of organizing this conference.
And here were all these brilliant people and
it came over us that we really didn't know what we ought to say.
I mean, you can scream and create a state of panic, but that won't do
any good. And when
it came down to it, we didn't know what
we ought to say because we really don't know what to do.
Some things that we might do, for example, to increase the food supply
with high yield crops, may be ecological mistakes.
And so the consensus of almost everybody at the meeting was
that in some way or other the human race has
to learn how to leave the world alone and let what is called
the natural homeostasis, that is the self balancing process
of nature, take care of the mess.
Now how are we going to do that?
This is Japanese ceremonial tea.
It's good on a cold day.
See, our problem is we don't really know how to stop. We've got something
started and we see it's going in a wrong direction.
And I think the difficulty is to borrow an old
Chinese saying, that when the wrong man uses
the right means, the right means work in the wrong way.
In other words, there's something wrong with the way we think.
And while that is there, everything we do will be a mess.
Now what is it that's wrong?
Now, as far as I can see, the basic mistake is
that we've invented this wonderful system of language and
calculation and
that it is at once too simple
to deal with the complexity of the world.
And also we are liable to confuse that system of
symbols with the world itself. Just as we confuse, say, money with
wealth. A lot of people are in business to make money
instead of wealth. When they make the money, they don't know what to do with
it.
And so in the same way we confuse
happiness with status and we confuse
ourselves as living organisms which are one with this whole universe,
with something we call our personality.
Now what is our personality?
Our personality is what we call our image,
our image of ourselves and also our thought about ourselves,
our idea of ourselves. This is the person,
in other words, what people meet and understand.
And what I understand as Alan Watts is a big act,
which is not really me.
Because in the image of Alan Watts, there are not all
my unconscious processes, both psychological and physical.
The construction of my brain is not contained in the concept
Alan Watts. And the concept Alan Watts does
not contain the inseparable relationships which I
have with all the rest of the universe. And therefore, that concept is
a fraud. And when it's mistaken for the
real me, there's a confusion. Because if
somebody says to me, alan Watts, do something about the concept,
Alan Watts can't do anything, in other
words, because it's only a concept,
you can't make it lift a weight. Just as
three is a concept, three, the number. You can't make just plain
three do anything. So also you can't wrap up parcels with
the equator. It's a useful imaginary line, but it can't do anything.
But we all feel that this concept of ourselves, which we call our personality
or our ego, can do something because we think it
really exists. And I'll tell you why we think it exists.
What happens when you. If I were to say to you, now, look hard at
the television screen, really look at it.
What do you do as distinct from just watching it in the ordinary way?
When you say, now I really got to see that. What do you do?
Notice that you tighten muscles all around here,
that you frown a little, you clench your teeth,
perhaps. Now, what has that got to do with seeing anything clearly?
Absolutely nothing to do with it. Same thing when you listen carefully.
Now, listen, catch everything that's said when you start
tightening up around your ears. That has nothing to do with hearing.
Clearer now, from the moment we were little children,
when teachers in class screamed at us, pay attention. We go
tight in various ways, either to
see or hear more clearly, to concentrate or
to will something which is supposed to be difficult to do and
that constitutes a habitual tension over the whole body that's
there almost all the time. And that feeling of unnecessary
tension is, as it were, the material sensation
upon which we fasten this concept of I,
we hang it on to that feeling. The concept
is not us. The feeling of tension is completely
phony. It has nothing to do with success in seeing, hearing or
acting. And so we get the marriage of an illusion
with a falsehood and that we call ourselves.
And no wonder we feel cut off from everything, alienated, frightened of
life and death.
So what has to happen is we have to come
back to a sane
view of our own life, which is
the way we really are an organism functioning
in terms of the whole environment, with the whole environment,
instead of this funny little separate personality. But how are we
going to do that? People say, oh, you can't change human
nature overnight. You're asking us to give up the ego.
And that's the most difficult of all things to do.
Actually, it isn't, because the ego doesn't exist.
But of course, if you try to give up your ego with your ego,
then it will take you to the end of time.
Because this is the point. You can't transform yourself.
You can't make yourself sane. You can't make yourself loving.
You can't make yourself unselfish.
And yet it's absolutely necessary that we be
that way. It's absolutely necessary.
If we are going to hand over the
direction of nature to nature, which is what it
comes to, it's absolutely necessary that
we let go of ourselves. And it can't be done.
Not by anything that we call doing it.
Acting willing, or even just accepting things.
You can't do it. Why?
Because you don't really exist as that kind of a separate
ego or personality. It's just an idea based on a phony feeling.
So when it comes down to it,
it's shocking news for us, for the
human race, for our pride.
You're only making a mess by trying to put things
straight. You're trying to straighten out a wiggly world,
and no wonder you're in trouble.
So you can't do anything. So you can't transform yourself.
And what can you do? What happens then if you actually
realize you've come to a dead end and the human
race has come to a dead end? In my opinion.
What then? Commit suicide?
Or is there something else? What happens
when you just wait? There's nothing you can do.
You watch and
all you see is what goes on that is happening of itself.
You are breathing, the wind is blowing,
the trees are waving. Your blood is circulating,
your nerves are tingling. It's all going on itself.
The whole theory of political control
by imposition of the rule of law from
above. Which is, alas, the Christian theory
of the universe. This is the way God is operating.
God is personally aware with his full,
total consciousness of every atom of existence.
Think of having to be occupied with the vagaries of
every human mind. Poor God,
the victim of his own power game.
And Lao Tzu is saying that in the art of ruling,
you do not use force.
You never press the issue.
He likens the functioning of the dao to water.
And he says now, water is always
taking the line of least resistance.
It doesn't strive, it always seeks
the low level which men abhor because they always want to be on top.
But what can you do with water? You can't cut it, you can't
injure it, you can't compress it.
So he's saying, in other words, if you want to govern the nation,
you must behave like water.
He has a conception of the dao, which is,
as it were, the exact opposite of all conceptions of God.
He says this the great dao flows everywhere,
both to the left and to the right. It loves and nourishes
all things, but does not lord it over them. And when
merits are accomplished, it lays no claim to them.
It says, the swishing wind does not last out morning.
The pelting rain does not go on all day. If heaven and earth cannot
keep these things up, how much less can have? So he has
an idea of the emperor as a.
An anonymous sort of person who would be, in other words,
to a political community in
the same way as today. The sanitary engineer
is never.
Would you imagine the sanitary engineer going through
town in a great car with a police escort and flags in all
directions. Nobody even knows who the sanitary engineer
is. And yet he's a very important official.
Without him, there would be health problems and all sorts of difficulties.
But because he's in charge of the sewers, everybody would
say, well, that's not very glamorous.
And Lao Tzu is saying that the. The chief official of the state
should have the same attitude as the man in charge of the sewers,
that the less he parades himself, the more
effective he can be. The less that's known about it better.
So he says, the energies of the emperor should be directed to
keeping the minds of the people unpreoccupied and their bellies
well filled. In other words,
let's not have news about politics. Let the
newspapers be full of interesting things,
not political things. But our newspapers, which are all about politics,
are full of catastrophes.
You open the newspaper and what do you read? What is news? Bad? Bad news
is news. But the saying, you know, no news
is good news. All news is bad news.
They don't say the great things that are going on very
rarely. So Lao Tzu advocates no news
at all. No discussion of politics.
He says, my ideal state would be a small
one in which you could hear the chickens in the neighboring state.
And the There would be no apparent government.
It's a kind of anarchy. But of course,
anarchy depends upon everybody being responsible.
Therefore, if you are going to have a control of
an enormous amount of information,
it has to be delegated and you have to trust them all
to work together. A highly organized system
where a lot of detail is going on has to be a system of mutual
trust. There is no way of bossing it if you
want to have it at all. You have to have it by letting go
and saying to all the units in it, come on, let's play together.
But the moment you come on uptight about them and say,
now I want an accounting from each
one of you, each one of them feels a little
mean about it and will conceal
information. And you, if you're going to keep charge of the whole thing
in that style of behavior, are going to have your hands full,
two full, you won't be able
to watch it all.
So therefore every organic complexity
works by the delegation of authority.
Every organic unity is a system of love,
that is to say of mutual trust, which says,
thank God I've got you around.
I often think about this. Somebody does something that's marvelous
and I think, what a relief that you could do that. And I
didn't have to.
All that effort that you put into doing this is so beautiful.
And I just relieved me of the necessity.
See, that's the way that the life principle really works.
In complete opposition to any idea of life
Lordship of all the credit belongs to
me. You as an ego, supposing you've
done, you've achieved something great.
And you say, no, it wasn't my ego that did,
was all these myriad little molecules and cells,
each one of whom contributed to this extraordinary thing
that I did. See, you can go in that
way towards infinite diversity and say of everything
that you did, no, it wasn't me, it was my people.
It was all these little fellows who were.
Each one of them did it to the degree that you
go towards the infinitude of the little ones.
To that extent you have a true sense
of unity.
Whereas if you don't give any credit to the little ones and you say,
well, I just push them around on you don't realize
how things are put together. This is the true inner
meaning of the principle of non duality. That the truest
unity is the same thing as the most detailed multiplicity.
You don't know what you mean by unity unless you understand multiplicity.
The one throws out the other idea. They balance each other like the
back and the front. So in exactly the same way, the more
you go for highly articulate multiplicity,
the more you get unity.
The whole idea of the giving in to the other,
trusting it to do it.
So this is the real secret underlying the democratic
principle, the notion of what
a republic is as distinct from
a monolithic monarchy,
where the people cease to trust themselves
and say to an authority,
please, you take care of us. Instead,
it works exactly the opposite direction.
And that direction is the opposite direction of the way
in which all living organisms flow
and manifest themselves.
If you believe that God is a monarch,
an absolute, omniscient and omnipotent authority,
shall we say a sort of cosmic ego,
then to claim to be that is to introduce democracy
into the kingdom of heaven to
us up divine authority and to speak in
its name without proper authorization.
And they asked Jesus, by what authority do you speak of heaven
or of men? And he was tricky
about answering that one.
He said, by what authority did John the Baptist speak?
And they were nervous about answering that one.
So the Gospel of Jesus, which of course was hushed up
from its inception, was that,
wake up everybody, and find out who you are
asking that again. In The Gospel of St. John, they,
pointing to his disciples, may be one, even as you,
Father, and I are one. And when
he was accused of blasphemy, the Jews
took up stones to stone him, you know, and he said, many good
works have I shown you from the Father, and from which of these do you
stone me?
And they said, for a good work we don't stone you, but for blasphemy,
because you, being a man, make yourself God.
Now listen to the reply. He said, is it not written in
your law? I have said ye are gods.
And if that is what the scripture says, it can't be denied.
So why do you tell me I blaspheme because I say I am a
son of God?
No answer because
I said I am a son of God. It doesn't say that in your King
James translation. It says, I am the son of God.
And you'll see the the italicized and you will think that that is for emphasis
if you don't realize that passages in italics in the King James Bible
are interpolations by the translators in
Greek, leaving out the definite article is equivalent of having the
indefinite article we ask to see you
is a son of God, not O E us to
Theo. So son of in
Hebrew and in Arabic means of the
nature of. When we call someone a son of a bitch,
we mean bitchy. And so if you call someone a
son of God, you mean divine of
the nature of God. As the Nicene Creed subsequently
defined it, he is of one substance with the Father.
But what happened was that this being blasphemy for
the Jews, it became blasphemy for the
Christians, for anyone else than Jesus to say it.
They said, okay, baby, it was so with you, but there
it stops. No more of this business.
And as a result of that,
Jesus was made irrelevant by pedestalization,
by being kicked upstairs,
in spite of the fact that he said, greater works than
these that I do. Shall you do. Oh, no,
upstairs with you, baby. Because we just
can't have that sort of thing going on in a monarchical universe. We are not
going to have democracy in the kingdom of heaven.
So this is why the Gospel is impossible.
Because we are supposed to follow the example of Christ,
where he says, for example, be not anxious for the morrow.
Do not worry about what you shall eat, what you shall drink, and what you
shall wear. God will take care of you. Doesn't he take
care of the birds? Don't the flowers grow? They're wonderful. They're crazy.
They're great. What are you worrying about? I've never heard a
sermon preached on that. Never.
Because it's totally subversive. The economy would crash.
So they say, oh yes, that's all very well, but he
was the boss's son,
see? He had that colossal advantage.
Take up your cross and follow him. Hey, but wait
a minute. I don't know. I'm going to be resurrected three days later.
I can't do all those miracles. He had an unfair
advantage.
So how can you ask us to follow the example of Christ?
But supposing he didn't have an unfair advantage?
Supposing that what was true about
Jesus as a son of God is true of us Only.
Only a few of us know it.
And we are pretty careful to be quiet about it,
lest the same thing happened to us as happened to Jesus.
And indeed it often does.
Now, why talk about this? Is it
interesting? Is it important for
the human being to realize that
in some sense of the Word, whatever it means, he is God, or one
with God. Well, the importance of it is this,
that to know that you are God is
another way of saying that you feel completely
with this universe. You feel
profoundly rooted in it and connected with it.
You feel, in other words, that the whole energy which expresses itself in the
galaxies is intimate.
It is not something to which you are a stranger,
but it is that with which you, whatever that is, are intimately
bound up. That in your seeing, your hearing, your talking,
your thinking you're moving,
you express that which it is which moves the sun and other stars.
And if you don't know that if you don't feel that,
well naturally you feel alien. You feel a
stranger in the world. And if you feel a stranger, you feel hostile
and therefore you start to bulldoze things about to beat it
up and to try and make the world submit to your
will. And you become a real troublemaker.
So I feel also one reason why you become hostile
is that feeling that you were just brought into this place, that your father
and mother went up to some monkey business that they probably shouldn't have
done, or it was bad rubber goods. And as a result of this, here you
are and you didn't ask to be here. Well, you always feel you can turn
around and blame them. You can blame somebody,
you can blame the government, you can blame the rascals, you can blame the,
blame the cheaters. Always supposing you yourself aren't a
rascal, which is a long odds.
You always can blame someone, say I
didn't ask for it, take it away.
And yet, and yet, and yet very few people are
all too ready to take it away.
And if you don't, if you don't say take
it away, what are you going to do?
You've really got to assume responsibility for it.
You've got to say yes to what happens.
It's my karma. And that doesn't mean merely.
There are many misinterpretations of the doctrine of karma.
It's usually in popularly understood is that what happens to you,
either fortunate or unfortunate, is the result of good or bad
deeds in a previous life. Well, that's popular superstition.
The real meaning of karma, the word in Sanskrit means simply
doing. And if I say of an event,
it is your karma, it is saying, it is your doing.
So the Exposition, a book which would expound karma
would be not so much a who done it as a you done it.
But that seems fantastic.
Allow ourselves the
idea that life is not
serious because somehow
you feel if you aren't engaged
in something serious, you're a loafer,
you're not contributing to the social welfare.
And so in this way the artist has
a peculiar role in this
society. Very, very interesting because
the artist is a very deceptive
fellow. He appears
to be the supreme luxury, the irrelevant fellow.
You can afford an artist, you can afford to buy paintings if
you have surplus money, that's a luxury.
So you can support an artist and we call it fine arts,
the completely useless person who
makes paintings which are sort of big labels or posters that you stick
on your utilitarian walls to decorate them.
But on the other hand, the artist
is the man who shows
you the future long before everybody else sees it.
The artist is the eye opener, just because
the artist is distinct in role from
the preacher and the philosopher.
So the. The role of the artist is very fascinating because
he appears to be the. The clown, the jester,
the absolutely unimportant and irrelevant person.
And yet it's actually through the artist that we learn how to live.
Not through the preacher, not through the philosopher,
not through the professor.
It is the artist teaches us, whether he does it visually in
painting or on sculpture, tactually over, above all in
music.
You should read, if you can get hold of it, an interview with
George Harrison, one of the Beatles, in a
recent issue of the East Village Other,
where he explains the deep philosophy
of music that they understand and
follow. How the
very nature of sound reveals
the meaning of the world and why, because of this, he regards
himself as a Hindu. In Hinduism,
the fundamental source of life is called vak.
Vak in Sanskrit means the word to speak,
but not so much the word that communicates as the sound,
the utterance, the flow of tone.
So you have in India the use of mantra,
the use of chanted words,
as one of the very basic forms of yoga,
understanding the mystery of the world.
The Hindus use the word om,
which would be spelled out A, U, m because
the letter A, ah is in the back of the throat.
You push it through the vowel to a lips.
So the word om comprehends the whole range of sound.
It's called the pranava.
All sounds are basically the sound of but
varied. The word that not only signifies
but also is what there is.
Everything is own, Sweet ohm.
The whole universe is of his own and
it has no meaning except it is the
very pulse of life.
Some of you have read a book of mine called the Choir's Cosmology,
in which I referred to once a very curious
experience I have with Hindu music.
I happen to have acquired from Timothy Leary some of
this extraordinary Mexican mushroom. And I
was feeling awful. I come
back from a trip to the east tired and I had a sore
throat and it was just lousy.
So I took this thing and I
found myself listening to this Hindu music. I didn't know what it was
and I thought when I listened to this, what kind
of idiocy is going on?
I thought, you see, my friend with whom I was spending
the day was a pretty wild kind of fellow, and I
thought he'd put on a tape recording of his and his friend's antics.
It was like children Making faces.
I thought, this is just something absolutely absurd going on.
So I said, roger, hey, let me see the album.
I got the case here. It says, classical Music of
India, edited by Anand Danielu,
who is the most scholarly,
respectable pundit the subject of Hindu music.
I said, somebody's pulling my leg.
No, not at all. Here was this
just babbling sound. Not only do the dit da
business, but they also could use their voices
like oboes. You know how that you'll
put a clothespin on your nose and do an oboe stump. And it sounded like
this. And it was just this whole kind of business of children were
just going out of their heads.
Well, I listened to this and I suddenly realized that
that's what life's all about.
And, you know, it was the most fantastic, sudden recognition
that everything in this world is
gloriously meaningless.
That's what's happening. We're all taught by
our mothers and fathers, put a value
on it when it goes a
certain way. The rhythm of life goes in
a certain way. When we say, oh, watch out, watch out,
watch out, watch out. Because that may be the end. What will the end be?
Spunk.
What's wrong with that?
Things that stop have to stop.
Things that go on have to go off. And things that go off have to
go on. But you see, we get
involved by putting a value on it. All right?
Now, I could say that's bad, you shouldn't do it. But at the same time,
getting involved and putting values on, it's all part of the game too.
Getting hung up, getting hooked. So you don't get
unhooked by saying to yourself, I shouldn't be attached,
I shouldn't do this, I shouldn't do that. All you do is you see
that getting hooked on it is simply another form of
it. More nonsense,
more jazz, more the deeper jazz.
When you. When you see a firm,
it has first of all the main branch. Then it
has sub branches. And out of these sub branches
come sub sub branches, and out of the sub sub
branches come sub sub, sub branches. And so you get a firm.
So now you could number each of these levels on which things are happening.
You say, well, this is a number one level. This is a number 42 level.
This is a number 65 level.
And you judge events and say, it's good,
it's bad, it's proper, it's improper. But what you don't recognize is
that you say something is improper because you thought it was a 63
level, whereas really it was 112.
And you didn't know, you didn't realize the level the thing was on.
So actually, in the whole play of
human life, with all its joys and sorrows, its tragedies, its evils, it's good
is just something like a fern.
It has tumors on it. That means just simply another clan is making its life
there. The clan of bugs of some kind are living
there too. They're doing their stuff. They're living off the fern.
The fern's living off something else. We're all leaning on each other in one way
or another.
I saw this whole thing as this fantastic play.
The reason why Zen is so peculiar is
that it has to begin with no
doctrines that can be stated in words,
nothing that it requires anybody to believe.
It has no system of
formulated philosophy.
In fact, it doesn't really have anything to say at all.
What is remarkable about them is
that it endeavors to convey its message,
the realization which constitutes awakening in Buddhism
without the intermediary of words and ideas.
There are four statements which sum up the
character of Zen Buddhism, and they are as follows.
A direct transmission of awakening
outside the scriptures. No dependence
on words and letters.
Direct pointing and
finally seeing into one's own nature
and becoming a Buddha, which is to say,
an awakened one.
I particularly want to concentrate on what is meant for the moment by
direct pointing, because. Because this is the technique in
which Zen excels. Zen feels
that all that human beings are seeking,
all that they really fundamentally desire,
whether it be complete contentment
of the heart or understanding
why this universe exists and what our place in it is,
all this understanding is
not something obscure and far off, but something
completely obvious and lying open for us
to anybody who cares to look at it. In this immediate
moment which we are living now,
it is as if to say the
whole secret of life, everything that you could
possibly desire is yours at this
moment. And if you cannot lay hold on it
now, you'll never be able to.
The difficulty is that it's very hard to convince people of this
by talking about it, because all talk, all systems of
ideas, are in relation to reality itself,
somewhat like a menu in relation to a dinner.
And those who try to get comfort,
to get wisdom out of books, or by believing
in various systems of ideas and philosophies,
such people are really devouring
the menu instead of eating the dinner.
Now, how then is 1,
2 divert people's attention from
the menu to the dinner itself?
There's only one way, and that is to point directly at the dinner,
to stop talking about it, to stop writing about it, and to point
at it directly.
We're all very convinced indeed that
we exist as a kind of self
or ego,
and our selfishness is one
of our major problems. It would.
Wouldn't it be rather fascinating
to find that when we look for ourselves, we are not really as
if where we expected to find ourselves, in the
center of all our experience, we found
only a hole, an empty space.
And then the problem of myself,
my happiness, my peace of mind, would have
disappeared.
There is no one whom one has to pacify,
whom one has to make happy.
You're not actually there.
But of course, one can't discover that just by hearing about
it. You have to look and see.
That's why one of the fundamental questions in all Oriental
philosophy is the simple question, who are you?
Look and try to find out who it is that is trying
to find out who it is that is trying to find out.
This is after all a
parable of what everybody is doing, who is engaged in what
we in the west call self seeking.
And this is really a stupid as somebody
sitting down solemnly in a chair and gnashing and gnashing
away, trying to bite his own teeth.
When the Buddha was in the
Gridra Kuta mountain, he turned a flower
in his fingers and held it before his listeners.
Everyone was silent.
Only Mahakashyapa smiled at this revelation,
although he tried to control the lines of his face.
The Buddha said, I have the eye of
the true teaching, the heart of Nirvana,
of awakening, the true aspect of
the formless, the ineffable stride of
the doctrine. It is not expressed
by words, but especially transmitted beyond
teaching. This teaching I now
give to Mahakashaba. And this is the same
sort of answer that Tosan
gave when he was asked, what is reality? He just said,
this flax weighs three pounds. An ordinary
statement, just as holding up the flower is
an ordinary action.
If I talk all the time and never listen to what
others have to say, I shall lose touch with my
fellow men. In the same way,
if I think all the time,
which is in a way talking to myself inwardly,
I shall lose touch with the reality with which words are
about which they're intended to symbolize.
It is the fundamental insight of Zen that by an excess
of thinking, men have lost touch with the real world in which they
live. The solution to this problem is
to be silent in one's mind and to look again at the
real world, not thinking, but seeing it directly.
This can't be talked about. If I want you to
listen to music, any advice to do so will drown out the
music. The directest way is to play the music
itself.
You cannot put what it is into words.
And this, indeed, is a central point of
Zen and of Buddhist understanding in general,
that reality is
beyond words.
And that one must not confuse the
world of things as we think about them
and talk about them and name them with
the world as it actually is.
Because in the world of ideas and words and conceptions
and inherited social notions,
every one of us is perfectly convinced that he is a self, an ego.
But when we step out of that world of conventional
ideas into the clear daylight of reality,
and with wide open eyes look for ourselves,
what do we find?