That what I want, basically what I really want is what you
want and I don't know what you want surprise
me.
But that's my, that's the kinship between I and thou.
So when I ask, I go right down to the question,
should we start it with what do I want?
The answer is I don't know.
When Bodhidharma was asked who are you? Which is another form of the same question,
he said, I don't know. Planting flowers to which the butterflies come,
Bodhidharma says, I know not,
I don't know what happened.
When you really don't know, you see, there's a.
There's a beginning stage of not knowing and there's an ending stage of not knowing.
In the beginning stage you don't know what you want because you haven't thought about
it or you've only thought superficially.
Then when you, somebody forces you to think about it and go through and say,
yeah, I think I'd like this, I think I like that, I think I'd like
the other as the middle stage. Then you get beyond that,
say, is that what I really want? In the end you say,
no, I don't think that's it. I might
be satisfied with it for a while and I wouldn't turn my nose up at
it, but it's not really what I want. Why don't you really know what you
want?
Two reasons that you don't really know what you want.
Number one, you have it.
Number two,
you don't know yourself because you never can.
The Godhead is never an object of its own knowledge.
Just as a knife doesn't cut itself, fire doesn't burn itself,
light doesn't illumine itself. It's always
an endless mystery to itself. I don't know.
And this I don't know uttered in the infinite
interior of the spirit,
this I don't know is
the same thing as I love.
I let go. I don't try to force or control.
It's the same thing as humility.
And so the Upanishads say,
if you think that you understand Brahman,
you do not understand and you have yet
to be instructed. Further, if you know that
you do not understand, then you truly understand.
For the Brahman is unknown to those
who know it and known to those who know it not.
And the principle is that
anytime you, as it were,
voluntarily let up control, in other words,
cease to cling to yourself, you have an
access of power because
you're wasting energy all the time in self defense,
trying to manage things, trying to force things to conform to your will.
The moment you stop doing that, that wasted energy is available.
Therefore you are in that sense having that energy available.
You are one with the divine principle. You have the energy.
When you're trying, however, to act as if you were God,
that is to say, you don't trust anybody and you're the dictator and you have
to keep everybody in line, you lose the divine energy because what
you're doing is simply defending yourself.
So then the principle is the more you give it away,
the more it comes back. Now you say, I don't have the courage to give
it away. I'm afraid.
And you can only overcome that by realizing you
better give it away because there's no way holding onto it.
The meaning of the fact, you see that everything is dissolving constantly,
that we're all falling apart, we're all in a process of constant
death, and that the worldly hope men set their
hearts upon turns ashes, or it plots, prospers, and like snow upon the
desert's dusty face lighting a little hour or two is gone. You know, all that
Omar Kayan jazz,
you know, the cloud cat towers, the gorgeous palaces, the great globe
itself I all which it inherits shall dissolve and like this insubstantial
pageant faded, leave not a rack behind. All falling apart.
Everything is. That's the. The great assistance to you
see that. That fact that everything is in decay is your
helper that is allowing you
that you don't have to let go because
there's nothing to hold on to.
It's achieved for you, in other words, by the process of nature.
So once you see that you just don't have a prayer,
it's all washed up and that you will
vanish and leave not a rack behind.
And you really get with that.
Suddenly you find you have the power,
this enormous access of energy.
But it's not power that came to you because you
grabbed it came in entirely the opposite way.
And power that comes to you in that opposite way
is power with which you can
be trusted.
That what I want, basically what I really want is
what you want. And I don't know what you surprised
me,
but that's my. That's the kinship between I and thou.
So when I ask, I go right down to the question,
should we start it with what do I want?
The answer is, I don't know.
When Bodhidharma was asked, who are you? Which is another form of
the same question, he said, I don't know.
Planting flowers to which the butterflies come,
Bodhidharma says I know not I
don't know what I want. When you don't know what you want,
you've reached the state of desirelessness when
you really don't know. You see, there's a. There's a
beginning stage of not knowing and there's an ending stage of not knowing.
In the beginning stage you don't know what you want because you haven't thought about
it or you've only thought superficially.
Then when you somebody forces you to think about it and go through and say,
yeah, I think I like this, I think I like that, I think I'd like
the other as the middle stage. Then you get beyond that,
say, is that what I really want? In the end you say,
no, I don't think that's it. I might
be satisfied with it for a while and I wouldn't turn my nose up at
it, but it's not really what I want. Why don't you really know what
you want?
Two reasons that you don't really know what
you want. Number one, you have it.
Number two,
you don't know yourself because you never can.
The Godhead is never an object of its own knowledge.
Just as a knife doesn't cut itself, fire doesn't burn itself,
light doesn't illumine itself. It's always
an endless mystery to itself. I don't know.
And this I don't know uttered in the infinite
interior of the Spirit.
This I don't know is
the same thing as I love. I let go,
I don't try to force or control.
It's the same thing as humility.
And so the Upanishad said,
if you think that you understand Brahman,
you do not understand and you have yet
to be instructed. Further, if you know that
you do not understand, then you truly understand.
For the Brahman is unknown to those who know it
and known to those who know it not.
And the principle is that
anytime you, as it were,
voluntarily let up control, in other words, cease to cling to
yourself. You have an access of power because
you're wasting energy all the time in self defense trying
to manage things, trying to force things to conform to your will. The moment you
stop doing that, that wasted energy is available.
Therefore you are in that sense having that energy available.
You are one with the divine principle, you have the energy.
When you're trying, however, to act as if you were God.
That is to say, you don't trust anybody and you're the dictator and you have
to keep everybody in line. You lose the divine energy because
what you're doing is simply defending yourself.
So then the principle is, the more you give it away,
the more it comes back. Now you say, I don't have the courage to give
it away. I'm afraid.
And you can only overcome that by realizing you
better give it away because there's no way holding on to it.
The meaning of the fact, you see that everything is dissolving constantly.
That we're all falling apart. We're all in a process of constant death.
And that the worldly hope men set their hearts apart pond turns
ashes or it prospers and likes snow upon the desert's dusty face lighting
a little hour or two is gone. You know, all that Omar Khayyam jazz,
you know, the cloud cat towers, the gorgeous palaces, the great
globe itself I all which it inherits shall dissolve and like
this insubstantial pageant faded leave not a rack behind.
All falling apart. Everything is.
That's the. The great assistance to you see that
that fact that everything is in decay is your helper that
is allowing you that you don't have to let
go because there's nothing
to hold on to. It's achieved
for you, in other words, by the process of nature.
So once you see that you just don't have a prayer and
it's all washed up and that you will vanish
and leave not a rack behind.
And you really get with that.
Suddenly you find you have the power, this enormous
access of energy. But it's not power
that came to you because you grabbed. It came in
entirely the opposite way. And power that comes to you in
that opposite way is power with
which you can be trusted.
Well, now,
the easiest way to get into the meditative state
is to begin by listening.
If you simply close your eyes and
allow yourself to hear all the sounds that are going
on around you.
Just listen to the general hum and
buzz of the world as if you were
listening to music.
Don't try to identify the sounds you're hearing.
Don't put names on them.
Simply allow them to play
with your eardrums and
let them go. In other words, you could
put it. Let your ears hear whatever they want to
hear. Don't judge
the sounds. There are no, as it
were, proper sounds or improper sounds. And it doesn't matter
if somebody coughs or sneezes or drops
something. It's all just sound.
And if I am talking to you right now and
you're doing this, I want you to listen to
the sound of my voice just as if it were noise.
Don't try to make any sense out of what I'm saying,
because your brain will take care of that automatically.
You don't have to try to understand anything, just listen to
the sound.
As you pursue that experiment, you will very naturally
find that you can't help naming
sounds, identifying them, that you will go on
thinking, that is to say, talking to yourself inside your
head automatically.
But it's important that you don't try to repress those thoughts
by forcing them out of your mind,
because that will have precisely the same effect as
if you were trying to smooth rough water with a flat iron.
You're just going to disturb it all the more. What you do is this.
As you hear sounds coming up in your head,
thoughts, you simply listen to them
as part of the general noise going on, just as you
would be listening to the sound of my voice, or just as you
would be listening to cars going by, or to birds
chattering outside the window. So look at your
own thoughts as just noises,
and soon you will find that the
so called outside world and the so called inside
world come together. They are a happening.
Your thoughts are a happening, just like
the sounds going on outside. And everything is simply
a happening and all you're doing is watching it.
Now, in this process, another thing that is happening
that is very important is that you're breathing.
And as you start meditation,
you allow your breath to run just
as it wills. In other words, don't do
at first any breathing exercise, but just
watch your breath, breathing the way it wants to breathe.
And notice a curious thing about this.
You say in the ordinary way I breathe,
because you feel that breathing is, is something that you are
doing voluntarily, just in the same
way as you might be walking or talking.
But you will also notice that when you are not thinking about
breathing, your breathing goes on just the same.
So the curious thing about breath is that it can be
looked at both as a voluntary and an involuntary
action. You can feel, on the one hand I
am doing it, and on the other hand it is happening to
me. And that is why breathing is
a most important part of meditation, because it is
going to show you, as you become aware of your breath,
that the hard and fast division that we make
between what we do on the one hand and what happens
to us on the other is arbitrary.
So that as you watch your breathing, you will become aware
that both the voluntary and
the involuntary aspects of your experience are
all one happening.
Now, that may at first seem a little scary because you
may think, well, am I just the puppet,
a happening? The mere passive witness of something that's going on
completely beyond my control, or on the other
hand, am I really
doing everything that's going along? Well, if I were, I should
be God. And that would be very embarrassing because I would be
in charge of everything. That would be terribly responsible position.
The truth of the matter, as you will see it,
is that both things are true.
You can see it, that everything is happening to you.
And on the other hand, you're doing everything. For example,
it's your eyes that are turning the sun into light.
It's the nerve ends in your skin that are turning
electric vibrations in the air into heat and temperature.
It's your eardrums that are turning vibrations in
the air into sound. And in that way you are creating
the world. But when
we are not talking about it, when we are not philosophizing about
it, then there is just this happening,
this.
And we won't give it a name.
Now then, when you breathe for a while,
just letting it happen and
not forcing it in any way, you will discover a curious thing,
that without making any effort, you can breathe
more and more deeply.
In other words, supposing you simply are breathing out.
And breathing out is important because it's the breath of relaxation,
as when we say, and heave a
sigh of relief. So when you
are breathing out, you get the
sensation that your breath is falling out,
dropping, dropping, dropping out, with the same
sort of feeling you have, as if you were settling down into an
extremely comfortable bed. And you
just get as heavy as possible and let yourself
go. And you let your breath go out in just that
way. And when it's thoroughly,
comfortably out and it feels like coming back again,
you don't pull it back in. You let it fall
back in, letting your lungs expand,
expand, expand, until they feel very comfortably
full. And you wait a moment and let it
stay there. And then once again, you let it
fall out. And so in this
way you will discover that your breath gets quite
naturally easier and easier and slower and
slower and more and more powerful.
So that with these various
aids, listening to sound,
listening to your own interior feelings and thoughts,
just as if they were something going on, not something you are
doing, but just happenings. And watching your breath as
a happening that is neither voluntary nor involuntary.
You are simply a aware of these basic sensations.
Then you begin to be in the state of meditation.
But don't hurry anything. Don't worry about the
future. Don't worry about what progress you're making.
Just be entirely content to be aware
of what is. Don't be terribly
selective. Particular say I should think of this and not of that.
Just watch. Whatever is happening,
the Earth is not a big rock
infested with living organisms,
any more than your skeleton, his bones
infested with cells.
The Earth is geological, yes.
But this geological entity
grows people.
And our existence on the Earth is a symptom of
the solar system and its balances.
As much as the solar system, in turn is a symptom
of our galaxy. And our galaxy in its turn, is a symptom
of the whole company of galaxies.
Goodness only knows what that's in.
But you see, when, as a scientist, you describe
the behavior of a living
organism,
you try to say what a person does. It's the only
way in which you can describe what a person is, describe what they do.
Then you find out that in making this description, you cannot
confine yourself to what happens inside the skin.
In other words, you can't talk about a person walking unless
you start describing the floor. Because when
I walk, I don't just dangle my legs in empty space.
I move in relationship to a room.
And so in order to describe what I'm doing when I'm walking,
I have to describe the room. I have to describe the territory.
So in describing my talking at the moment,
I can't describe this just as a thing in itself because I'm talking to
you. And so what I'm doing at the moment
is not completely described unless your being here is described
also. So if that is necessary,
if, in other words, in order to describe my behavior, I have to describe your
behavior and the behavior of the environment, it means that we've really
got one system of behavior that
what I am involves
what you are. I don't know who I
am unless I know who you are. And you don't know
who you are unless you know who I am. It was a wise rabbi
once said, if I am I because you
are you, and you are you because I am I, then I am
not I and you are not you. In other words, we are not separate.
We define each other. We're all backs and fronts to each other.
We and our environment and all of us and
each other are interdependent systems. We know
who we are in terms of other people we all
love together. And we
are, I think, quite urgent, in need of
coming to feel that we are the
eternal universe. Each one of us sa a
certain amount of doing nothing and stopping rushing around would
cool everything.
But also it must be remembered that passivity is the root of action.
Where do you suppose you're going to get energy from just by being energetic.
No, you can't get energy that way. That is
exhausting yourself. To have energy you
must sleep. But also much
more important than sleep is passivity
of mind, mental silence.
You can't, as I tried to explain, be passive
as an exercise that's good for you. You can only
get to that point by realizing there's nothing else you can do.
So for God's sake, don't cultivate passivity as a form
of progress. That's like playing, because it's good for
your work. Also,
you get soft, you're not on the
key. Vi you develop flabby muscles because
you never get involved in a fight.
So the. What the Daoist tries
to develop is a sensibility to the situation.
He tries to feel out intuitively
what kind of action is required under these circumstances,
because he feels that he can never discover it analytically
with his conscious attention alone.
Well, now to talk in modern Western terms about how this is
done. We must realize, of course, that we are equipped
inside our heads with an absolutely fantastic
thing called the brain.
With its millions and millions of neuron
cells. It is, as it were, the most amazing
computer ever devised.
The basic to the Taoist attitude to life is
that you have that within you. And you may, if you don't know anything about
brains, though, very much, call it intuition or something of that kind.
But you have within you the most amazing logical
analyzer that exists in the known
world. And the point is to
get it to work for you.
And instead of trying with conscious attention
alone, which can only think of about three things at a time without
using a pencil,
that is to say, keep three variables in mind at once.
Very few people can do four without using a pencil.
You can do four if you're a trained musician, where you've got. You're playing four
different lines of a fugue. Say you're keeping four variables
in mind at once. With an organist you can go
from four to six because you've got your two feet
and they're playing too. But that requires
a high amount of training to be able, with conscious attention,
to keep these many variables in mind.
But the world around us has infinitely many variables going
in it. And you can reason out something with
your conscious verbal thinking.
Say you want to make a contract in business and you figure
out how to make it, whether it will be a good contract, whether it will
work, etc. Etc. And you think of all these things and write
them down and you make the contract and you think that's fine. But one of
the variables that you couldn't possibly include in the contract was that
your partner would slip on a banana skin and break his neck.
All sorts of things. I mean, the contract might make
provisions in it if your lawyer was thoughtful for what was to
be done under the case of the disability of any of the parties there too.
Etc. But eventually there are so many possibilities
that can occur that you cannot think of them all.
So then the question arises,
is it within the power of the human brain to
comprehend because of its immense complexity in
a kind of un or subconscious way,
what the surface consciousness can never grasp?
And the. The Taoist would say, certainly it can,
that you've got to learn to use your brain by
allowing it to go to work on your problems
without interfering with it, and then it will deliver you
a decision. And this is why when
you get to. When you get to the real study of Taoist
and Zen Buddhist practice,
you get to the point where you learn to act without making decisions.
Or rather, to use a more exact word, without choosing.
Krishnamurti talks a great deal about being choicelessly
aware. And he says
freedom is precisely the state of not having to choose.
The only way to handle danger is to face it.
If you start getting frightened of it,
then you make it worse because you project onto it
all kinds of bogeys and threats which don't exist in it at all. Whenever you
meet a ghost, don't run away because
the ghost will capture the substance of your
fear and materialize itself out of your own substance
and will kill you eventually because it will take over all
your own vitality. So then,
whenever confronted with a ghost, walk straight into it and
it will disappear. We gotta survive.
You must survive. That's the great thing
we're all working under and pounding it out day after day in
anxiety. Because this is a description of anxiety.
Anxiety is the fear that one of a pair of opposites
might cancel the other forever.
And if by any chance, by any means, you find out that that is not
so, you have an entirely new attitude to
what human beings are doing,
which may be very creative, but which also may be
very dangerous. You see
through the game. You are only
just kidding that you're just poor little me. See, the function of
a guru, that is to say a spiritual teacher in India,
is to look, give you a funny look in the eye because
you come to him and say, Mr. Guru, I have problems,
I suffer and it's a mess and I can't control my mind and I'm
miserable and depressed and so on. And he gives you a funny
look, and you feel
a bit nervous about the way he looks at you because he thinks,
you know, he's reading your thoughts. And this man is a great magician.
He can read everything that's in you. He knows right down into your unconscious.
And you know all the dreadful things you've thought and all the awful desires
you have. And you are rather embarrassed that this man looks right through you and
sees them all. But that's not what he's looking at.
He's giving you a funny look for quite another reason altogether,
because he sees in you the
Brahma, the Godhead,
just claiming it's poor little me. That's why he gives you
a funny look and why he seems to see right through
you, as if to say,
shiva, old boy, don't kid me, I know who you are.
But you're coming on beautifully in this act that
you're somebody else altogether. And I
congratulate you. You're doing a wonderful job playing
this part which you call the person, my person.
So it's all very well. Anybody can have ecstasy.
Anybody, as a matter of fact, can become aware
that he is one with the eternal ground of the universe.
But since that what's what you are anyway, I going to ask,
so what? When a hero
goes on an adventure and he leaves his people and is
going to a strange land, he can go away and just hide himself
around the corner in an obscure house and then appear a year later
and say, I've been on a heroic journey and tell all sorts of tales and
they say prove it, because they expect him
to bring back something, something which nobody has seen before.
Then they believe you've been on a journey.
So in the same way. Exactly. Anybody who goes on a spiritual
journey must bring something back.
Because if you just say, oh man, it was a gas,
anyone can say that.
Now. This is why in the doctrines of Buddhism there
is a differentiation between two kinds of enlightened Buddha beings.
They are both forms of Buddha, which is to say, the word Buddha
means somebody who has awakened, who has discovered the secret
behind all this. In other words, all this thing we call life with
its frantic concerns, is a big act which
you, in your unconscious death are deliberately
setting up.
So you can do one of two things. When you discover this, you can become
what's called a Pratyaka Buddha, that means a private Buddha
who doesn't tell anything.
Or you can become a Bodhisattva,
practical Buddha goes off into his ecstasy and
never is seen again. Bodhisattva is come
one who comes back and appears in the everyday world and
plays the game of the everyday world by the rules of the everyday
world. But he brings with him Upaya. He brings with
him some way of showing that he's been on the journey,
that he's come back. And he's going to let you in on the
secret too. If you, if, if,
if you will play it cool and also come
back to join in
the everyday life of everyday people.
The first thing then is to discover what indeed you
do love, if anything. And you will find there is something
and then go into the nature of that.
Now it said that selfish people love themselves
is something which you thought was other than yourself,
even if it be very ordinary things such as ice cream or
booze. In the
conventional sense, booze is not you,
nor is ice cream. It certainly it turns into you in a manner of speaking,
when you consume it, but then you don't have it anymore,
and so you look around for more in order to love it once again.
But so long as you love it, you see, it's never you.
When you love people, even however selfishly you love them because
of the pleasant sensations they give to you, still it is
somebody else that you love. And as you inquire
into this, as you follow honestly your own selfishness,
many interesting transformations begin to come about in you.
One of the most interesting transformations of being directly
and honestly selfish in the same way that, for example, cats are,
is that you stop deceiving people.
If what you define as you is
inseparable from everything which you define as not you,
just as front is inseparable from back,
then you realize that deep down between self and other,
there is some sort of conspiracy.
If these things always occur in combination and
look very different from each other and feel quite different,
nevertheless, the feeling of difference between them allows
each one to exist.
And so underneath the opposition or the polarity between
self and other, or between any other pair of opposites you can think of,
there is something in common, as there is, for example, between figure and
background. You can't see a figure without
a background. You can't have an organism without an environment.
Equally, you can't have a background without a figure or an environment,
without organisms in it, or without things in it.
You can't have space which is unoccupied by any
solid. You can cannot have solids not occupying
some space. This is absolutely elementary
and yet we don't realize it because,
for example, the average person thinks that space is nothing,
but it's just a sort of not thereness in which there
are things and
we are slightly afraid that not thereness,
that nothingness, that darkness, that the negative polls
of all these oppositions will win,
that they will eventually swallow up every kind of
being and every kind of thereness. But when
you catch on to the game, you realize that that won't happen.
Because what is called not existing is quite
incapable of being there without the contrast of something
called existing.
It's like the crest and the trough of a wave.
You can't have a wave that is all trough and no crest,
just as you can't have a wave which is all crest and no trough.
Such a thing has never been manifested in the physical universe.
They go together.
And that is the secret.
There really is no other secret than that.
That is the secret in
giving away the control. You got it.
You got the kind of control you wanted.
That's to say where you had a loving relationship
to the world, but you
didn't have to make up your mind what it should do.
You let it decide.
Now do you see? That's how your bodies work.
You don't have to make up your mind what your nerve
cells are going to do. You've delegated all
that authority.
If the President of the United States has to lay awake at nights thinking
what every official under his command is going to do, he can't be president.
He's got to make an act of trust in all those subordinates
to be responsible and carry on their things in just the same way as you
make an act of trust to all your subordinate organs
to carry on their functions without you having to tell them what to do.
And this is the secret of what we will call organic power
as distinct from political power.
Lao Tzu puts it in this way. The great Dao flows
everywhere, both to the left and to the right. It loves
and nourishes all things, but does not lord it over them.
And when merits are accomplished, it lays no claim to them.
The more therefore you relinquish power,
trust others, the more
powerful you become,
but in such a way that
instead of having to lie awake nights controlling everything,
you do it beautifully by trusting the job to everyone else.
They carry it on for you.
So you can go to sleep at night and trust your nervous system
to wake you up in the morning. You can even tell it,
I want to wake up at 6 o'clock and it'll wake you up just like
an alarm clock.
This seems a sort of paradox to say this, but the principle
of unity,
of coming to a sense of of oneness with
the whole of the rest of the universe is not to try to obtain
power over the rest of the universe. That will only
disturb it and antagonize it and make it
seem less one with you than ever. The way to become one with the universe
is to trust it as
another, as you would another,
and say, let's see what you're
going to do.
This seminar about birth, death and the unborn
is going to be a discussion of the Buddhist philosophy of
change. And I'm going to start out by going
into the very tricky and difficult question
of the Buddhist view of birth and death.
And the doctrine which is ordinarily understood as reincarnation
or rebirth.
It's a curious thing that
many Westerners who become interested in Hinduism or
Buddhism do so because of
this idea of reincarnation they
like,
gives a more satisfactory vision of
individual history and development than
the two possibilities that would normally be open to Westerners to believe
in. On the one hand,
you've got the choice of the Christian view,
which is that you live in this world once,
and in this four score years and ten, your eternal fate is
settled, or you've got the possibility of
the materialistic view, which is that you only live
once and when you're dead, you're dead. That's that you're a flash
of consciousness between two eternal darknesses.
Intelligent people in the Western world have never felt very happy about either
of these two prospects. And therefore there's
a certain attractiveness about the idea, which seems
to be the point of Buddhism and Hinduism, that you are
a soul on a pilgrimage. And that from
some extremely obscure origin, you began as some sort
of animalcule and worked your way up, step by step,
through all sorts of forms of life. And finally you
have the privilege of appearing in human form.
And once you've got there, you have an opportunity to
develop to the highest spiritual position.
You must remember that according to both Hindu and Buddhist doctrines,
the human form is a very privileged position.
For there are, according to both of them, because they share a common cosmology,
six domains of beings.
And if you visualize the
wheel of life with its six divisions,
at the highest top division, there is the realm
of the deva. Deva is a word
from which we get the word divine and equally the word devil.
A deva means, though originally a God, or more
correctly, an angel. Angel is a
better Western translation of deva than God.
Immediately opposite the deva world, at the bottom
of the circle, there is the Naraka world of
beings in torment. This is the dimension of the world, which is the
screaming mimis. Which is experience in the form of absolute
horror. The deva world is the experience
of being in the form of bliss.
And between these two poles there are all kinds of ranges.
There are, for example, the Ashuras next to the devas,
going clockwise around the wheel, and the Asuras,
they are a wrathful beings.
Ashura is the incarnation of divine anger.
Then next to the Asura, going around, are the animals,
all animals whatsoever. Then again, we get to the Naraka at the
bottom, the place of the Purgatory, we'll call it.
Then coming up again, there's the world of the Preta,
who are frustrated beings.
And they're represented iconographically as having
very large bellies and very tiny mouths, that is to
say, an immense appetite with very
little means of satisfying it. They are a sort of spiritual
bottleneck. And then coming
up between the pretas and the devas is the world
of the humans. And this is understood to represent
a sort of middle position.
You can be liberated from the human state because
the devas are too happy to be liberated,
the Asuras too furious, the animals too dumb,
the Narakas too tormented and the pretas too frustrated.
You need not take this as a literal account
of various kinds of being in the universe. You can take them
simply as a depiction of various states of the human mind,
of the moods you can go through.
They're all really in your own head, as we shall see later on,
about many other things. But these
are the six worlds of Hindu and Buddhist cosmology,
and the notion is that one reincarnates again
and again through the six worlds. This is the popular idea.
In other words, if you live this human life
in a bad way and you become angry,
if you devote your life to fury, you'll be reincarnated as
an Ashura. If you devote your life to
merely living for back and belly, you'll be reincarnated
as an animal. If you are horribly cruel
to people, you'll be reincarnated as a Naraka,
and so on all around. But on the other hand, if you do good
things in the because of your
karma, you will be reincarnated in the Deva world,
or in better and better situations in the human world.
That's the popular understanding. And Westerners, many of
them, think, well, that's great, because this opens up vast vistas
of future development. We can go on in future lives
working out our destinies. And we can also love to think about.
About who we were before. When you fall in
love with somebody, did you meet before in some Past life
is this the working out of a karma that is between you?
And it's very interesting. But the funny thing is that Hindus and Buddhists
who do believe in rebirth do so not
because they like it, but because they feel they have to accept it
as a hard fact. And the whole task of the work of
sadhana, or a spiritual practice and discipline is
to get out of it. So it always
strikes me. It's very funny that Westerners
take this up because they find it comforting, but Easterners
are always trying to get away from being reborn.
It was so funny once Joseph Campbell told me a story that
he was sitting with a Vedanta swami,
one of these Vedanta Society swamis.
And the swami was saying, oh, dear me. He said, you know,
really, the idea of rebirth is so wonderful. Said I.
I really. I think this is
the. The most. The most comforting notion.
And Joe said to him, swami, don't be a damn
fool. What are you talking about? The idea
of rebirth being so comfortable.
Don't you realize that that's what you're supposed to get away from?
And the swami suddenly jumped, said, oh, yes, of course.
It was like I once had a talk with a swami, and he
was arguing, you see, that behind all the multiple forms of this
world, there was only one single
divine principle. And he was going on about
this. I said, swami, you can't talk like that. You know very well
that the Brahman, the ultimate reality, isn't one,
because one has an opposite, which is many, and Brahman has no opposite.
You should speak as Brahman as the non dual.
And again, you talk just like a Hindu.
They're funny, you see, because these swamis have accepted an enormous
amount of Western feeling, how the British
were responsible for that, for occupying India so long and perverting
its traditions.
Now it is so curious, all this, because in Buddhism there
still prevails an idea of rebirth very
strong among all Buddhist countries.
And yet Buddhism explicitly
denies that there is any individual reincarnating
soul. You see, in Buddhism there
is a doctrine which is called the three signs of being.
I should more correctly say the Sanskrit word is bhava,
vhava, and that means becoming rather than being.
Bhava is from the basic root,
I think, bh, which is connected with the.
With growth. So bhava,
becoming, the process of change has
three signs. One is called dukkha.
D u h K H A dukta in
Sanskrit means frustration,
sometimes translated suffering.
But I think frustration is a more general
word which is perhaps better. It's dukkha
is the opposite of sukkah. Sukkah means sweet.
Dukkha perhaps means sour. But in
this, in the way it's used, it means frustration as
a basic characteristic of living beings.
Because for some reason or other, life is always eventually
frustrating. You desire more than you can ever get.
You overreach the possibilities.
And so to every being, death comes as a collapse
and as something unfortunate.
The next sign of being is called anita A n
I t y a in Sanskrit, anitya, which means impermanence,
the opposite word being, nitya, eternal.
So anitya is everything is
in flux. And finally,
anatman, A n a T M a N,
anatman, which means that nothing has
its own soul.
Now that sounds to a Christian a
terrible idea, because we use the word
soulless, or we say to a person, you have no soul,
which means you have no finer feelings. You have no,
you're not a human being. Because Christian theology
did distinguish between humans and animals by saying that animals have no
soul. Idiots have no soul. They've lost their soul.
But you can see at once that there is a complete difference
of the meaning. This is a. To translate atman as
soul is ridiculous.
Anatman means basically
that nothing exists.
Well, there's another word in Sanskrit
you have to know, svaphava sva, that means
oneself or one's own, same as the Latin sus,
because the V becomes the U sva
bava bhava, becoming again, your own becoming,
or sometimes it's called your own nature or self nature.
So what it is saying is that you don't. That nothing has
any real swabhava,
because no individual thing
of any kind exists except in relation to all the
other things.
In other words, you are what you are
only because of your relationships to everything else.
And therefore the whole universe is a system of interdependence.
It's just as if, for example, you were to stand two sticks on the
ground and lean them against each other, and they will stand up
and form an inverted V because
they lean on each other.
And this is an old thing that they teach children in
Japan, that these sticks leaning against each other form
the Chinese character for man. And they
say, therefore, man cannot exist unless we support each other.
This is the basis, therefore, of brotherhood and of good
social relationships. But underneath that is
the far more profound idea that
the universe coheres
by everything depending on everything else.
And therefore nothing exists alone,
nothing exists in its own right. And that's what anatman
means. You do not have an indestructible
immortal soul, which is just plain you forever
and ever and ever, and is independent of there being anything else
at all.
Also, though, this does go along with the idea that there is not some kind
of gaseous spook, some kind of etheric double
astral body what have you, which outlasts the
existence of the physical body and migrates
to the next incarnation.
So it has always been a puzzle for Buddhist philosophers to explain
how they can at once believe in reincarnation and at the
same time deny the existence of an individual spooky,
which is independent of the physical frame.
And the most subtle discussions in all Buddhist literature range
around this puzzle. The most important
text of early Buddhism is a book called the Questions of
King Melinda. This is the Greek Menanda.
He is a king in the succession of Alexander the Great,
who ruled in Alexander's eastern empire and
had long conversations with a Buddhist sage by the name of Nagasena.
And Nagasena tries to explain to the king how
there can be rebirth without anyone who is being reborn.
And so this is the problem to which we address ourselves.
How can there be a continuing process
without anything carried along by
it? And you will recognize at once that the problem is
very largely semantic because
it involves our whole idea of continuity.
What, for example, do you mean by a wave?
When you see you throw a stone into the water, and from
the plop point where the stone goes in, a whole
lot of rings emerge and they are waves and they go out,
and you can, as it were, look at one of them and
follow it. And you say, I am watching a wave.
But what is a wave?
You know very well that the
water itself,
no, no volume of water, no specific volume of water,
is moving outwards from the place where you drop the pebble.
The water is staying quite still so far
as lateral motion is concerned, but the water is moving
up and down. And these up and down movements create
the illusion of a thing called a wave that goes along.
Similar to the illusion when you watch a barber's pole revolving.
It seems to be a procession of something that
keeps going up from the bottom of the pole to the top.
But actually it's just going around.
Now that that appearance of
something moving when there is actually the only thing
that is going outwards is motion.
And motion is about as abstract as you can think.
This is the whole root of the Indian
idea of Maya, of the world as Maya,
as a construct, as something which,
shall we say, exists only in your mind only.
We shall have to be very careful what
we mean by that. And I'm going to come to
that later on in the sermon.
So here. Here is. Here is the point.
You are delivered from rebirth.
This being the purpose of the spiritual disciplines of
Hinduism and Buddhism. As soon as you
are relieved of the illusion that something is going on,
continuity. This, after this, after this,
after this, all linking up together into a chain.
In the famous Zen text called the Platform Sutra,
attributed to Hui Nun, the sixth patriarch,
there is a passage which says, if we
allow our thoughts, past, present and future to
link up into a series, we put ourselves under restraint.
But on the other hand, if we just see that they are not
they, there is just this thought and then this thought and then this thought.
You are liberated.
This is an idea which is taken up by T.S. eliot in his poem the
Four Quartets, where you come to the passage
where he says that you're getting on a train and
you settle down in the compartment with your newspaper
and you're going on a journey. But the one
who arrives at the destination will not be the same person
who left the platform in the beginning,
because you who sit here now are
not the same as the people who came in at the door a little
while ago. Just in exactly the
same way as the flame of a candle appears
to be a constant flame, which we can identify as a
thing, but as a matter of fact, it is a stream of
hot energy,
which is whatever particles,
whatever gaseous the molecules are here are going
like this the whole time, flowing upwards and disappearing.
The flame is converting the candle wax into gas.
And in exactly the same way as we can see that the flame has
an identity. You say it is a flame. We have a noun
for it, where actually it is a process, it is flaming.
And so in just precisely that way, it. Every human
being is a process.
Just as the flame is the conversion of wax into gas,
so you and I are the conversion of
air and water and light and beef steak and milk
into and
which again converts into something else. You see, we are the
flowing vibration through which all this goes,
and not for one moment are we the same.
So then the meaning of the Buddhist doctrine
is that you who
live today are never going to die,
because the one that's going to die will not be the youth here now.
And likewise, the one that's here now was never born.
It goes like this. It is explained by Dogen,
who was the most fabulous Zen philosopher living around
1200 AD when he said the
spring does not become the summer
and the summer does not become autumn.
No one would say that spring becomes the summer.
There is spring and then there is Summer.
And he said, in the same way, when you burn wood,
there are ashes, but the wood does not become the ashes.
There is wood and then there is ashes.
Each is, as it were,
sufficient to itself. There are, as it were,
so steps. It's like vibrations,
wave crests. You see,
where the water
doesn't move, you see, water doesn't move laterally.
So in this sense, by analogy, the spring does not become the
summer, but by watching it,
you in your mind impose motion on
the up and down of the water. And so you say the
spring becomes the summer. So likewise you say the baby
becomes the adolescent, becomes the man,
becomes the crone, becomes the corpse.
And the Buddhists say, no. These states follow
in the same way as the apparent motion of a wave.
And so the,
the. The word to the wise is live
the moment you're in, there is
no other place to be. You will not
die, and you were never born.
If you realize, if you see through the illusion
now, this may sound as if one were creating a theory of the
universe, which is what you might
call atomistic,
discontinuous. It is saying the universe is nothing,
but what point instance?
And it all comes down to that. See, this is an
extension of the Western philosophy of nominalism.
Nominalism is opposed to realism. The nominalists
argue against the realists point of view, which is,
realists say there is such a thing as mankind.
Mankind is a reality, and every
individual human is a special instance of
a real universal substance
called man. The nominalists
argue this is abstraction and nonsense. There is no such thing as
mankind. There are only individual people.
And of course, this has become, in the 20th century, the ascendant point of
view. There is not really such a thing as the United States
of America. That is a political abstraction. There are
just the people who live here.
But if you take nominalism to its logical conclusion,
you get to the point where you don't exist at all.
A human being. Well, there is no such thing as a human being. It's an
abstraction. All there is is the molecules that are the cells
which infest your bones.