Sometimes in life, we face moments when it becomes undeniably
clear that something must end. It might be a
relationship, a dream that no longer inspires us, or a chapter
of our lives we've clung to for far too long.
And yet the act of letting go, of allowing it to truly end,
often feels like stepping into an abyss.
Why is that? Why do we hesitate, even when every fiber
of our being knows the truth? It's because
endings are painted as failures. In the story we tell ourselves,
we're taught to persevere, to hold on, to fix what's
broken at all costs. But perhaps the greatest
misstep is not in letting go. It's in clinging to something
that has already run its course. We fear endings
because they feel like losses. Yet in truth,
an ending is merely a transformation, a shift in the pattern of life
that a life that allows something new to emerge.
Imagine holding onto a flower that has withered.
Its petals fall away. Its fragrance fades. And yet you
grip it tightly, unwilling to let it go.
Why? Because the act of releasing it means acknowledging its passing.
But what if letting it go also meant opening your hand
for a seed? One that could bloom into something new?
To let it end is to acknowledge the rhythm of life,
the cycles of beginnings and endings that have always shaped our
existence. Without one, the other cannot
follow. Sometimes the hardest part
is not the end itself, but admitting that we've outgrown something.
It can feel like betraying a part of ourselves. But what
if holding on is the real betrayal? When we
cling to what no longer serves us, we deny ourselves
the opportunity to grow. Life, after all, is not
static. It's a continuous dance of change.
Endings are not failures. They are the moments when life whispers, this is
not the path anymore. Trust me, there is more ahead.
I remember hearing a story about a butterfly struggling
to emerge from its cocoon. A passerby,
seeing its struggle, decided to help. By gently opening
the cocoon, the butterfly emerged. But its
wings were underdeveloped and it could not fly.
What the helper didn't realize was that the struggle was necessary
for the butterfly to grow strong enough to take flight.
Endings often feel like that struggle.
They're uncomfortable, sometimes agonizing.
But they prepare us for what comes next.
Without them, we remain in a state of limbo,
unable to grow into the fullness of our potential.
When we resist an ending, we also resist the wisdom
it offers. Each ending comes with lessons. If we are
willing to listen, it might teach us about our resilience,
our values. Or the truth about what. What we want from
life. But to hear these lessons, we must first summon
the courage to let go. And courage doesn't
mean the absence of fear. It means acting in spite of means,
trusting that life knows what it's doing, even when we
cannot see the bigger picture. Endings are
sacred moments of transformation. And they ask us
for one thing. Faith. Faith in ourselves.
Faith in the process. And faith that letting go of what was opens the
door to what can be. Think of the trees in autumn,
shedding their leaves. They do not resist the
cycle. They let go, trusting that spring will bring new
growth. And so must we.
So when the time comes, don't be afraid to let it end.
Trust that in the letting go, you are not losing yourself. You are finding
the space to grow into the next version of who you are.
Remember, the end is not the final act.
It's the prelude to a new beginning.
When something ends, it's tempting to numb the pain or run from
it entirely. It's human nature,
after all, to avoid discomfort, to shield ourselves
from the sharp sting of loss. But what if pain isn't the
enemy we think it is? What if, instead of resisting it,
we allowed it to be what it is, a natural part of life's ebb
and flow, A teacher pointing us toward deeper understanding.
Pain, when something ends, is not there to punish us.
It's there to remind us that we care, that we were connected,
that something mattered enough to hurt when it was gone.
And yet, most of us treat pain like an intruder,
Something to be banished as quickly as possible.
We fill our days with distractions, hoping that if
we keep ourselves busy enough, the ache will
dissolve on its own. But pain doesn't
vanish when ignored. It lingers in the background, waiting to be
felt, acknowledged, and honored.
Have you ever noticed how much effort goes into avoiding pain?
We brace ourselves against it, pretend we're fine,
or convince ourselves that we're over it before we've even begun to
process what's happened. But pain, much like a
storm, has its own timetable. You can't rush
it away or force it to disappear. What you can do
is stand in its presence, let it rain down on you, and trust that
the storm will eventually pass.
There's a story of a young boy who planted a seed
in his garden. Eager for it to grow,
he would dig it up every few days to check its progress.
Unsurprisingly, the seed never had a chance to sprout.
In the same way, when we rush through pain or try to sidestep
it, we deny ourselves the opportunity to heal.
Pain is like fertile Soil for growth. And when we
sit with it, when we allow ourselves to feel its depth, something extraordinary
begins to happen. We grow stronger. We grow
wiser. We grow more compassionate,
not just toward ourselves, but toward others who are also navigating
their own storms. There's a strange
kind of beauty in allowing pain to take its course.
When we stop fighting it, we find that it's not as unbearable as
we feared. Pain, when welcomed rather than resisted,
has a way of softening us, opening us up.
It's through these cracks that light finds its way in that
transformation begins. It's often the moments of
deepest hurt that reveal our greatest strength.
But this isn't to say that pain is easy to bear.
It's not. It can feel like an unrelenting weight, a constant
reminder of what's been lost. And yet, pain is not permanent.
Like the tide, it rises and falls.
It ebbs and flows. It moves through us,
shaping us as it goes. Each wave of hurt
carries with it the potential for healing, for growth, for renewal.
Think of a wound. If ignored, it festers.
But if cared for, cleaned, bandaged, and given time,
it heals. The scar it leaves behind doesn't signify
weakness or failure. It tells a story of resilience.
And so it is with emotional pain. By allowing
it to surface, by tending to it with patience and care,
we give ourselves the chance to heal fully.
We honor the depth of our experience, and in doing so,
we honor ourselves. Pain is not the end
of the story. It's a part of the process, a necessary
step on the path toward healing and letting go.
So don't be afraid to let it hurt. Feel it fully,
not as a burden, but as a burden, but as a reminder that you are
alive, that you are growing, that you are growing, that you are
moving forward. In the willingness to embrace
pain, we find the freedom to heal and eventually
the strength to let it go.
Healing is a peculiar process, isn't it?
It doesn't follow a straight line or a logical timeline.
It's not something we can control or force into submission.
Healing is more like a dance, one that requires patience,
trust, and an openness to move with the rhythm of life.
And yet, how often do we treat healing like a task
to be completed, something to check off a list so we
can move on to the next thing. But healing
isn't about rushing to feel okay again. It's about allowing
ourselves the space to not be okay for a while. It's about
sitting with our wounds, listening to what they have to say, and letting
time do its quiet, mysterious work. Like a
tree regrowing its bark after being stripped bare,
healing happens slowly, layer by layer.
You can't rush it, nor should you try.
We live in a world that prizes quick fixes.
If something is broken, we want it repaired immediately.
If we're hurting, we want the pain to disappear overnight.
But the deepest healing doesn't come from avoidance or distraction.
It comes from acknowledgment, from creating space for all
the messy, complicated feelings that arise after something has
ended. Healing isn't neat or tidy. It's raw and real,
and it asks for our full presence. Think of a
wound on your skin. If you constantly pick at
it, trying to speed up the process, it only gets worse.
But if you let it breathe, if you care for it gently,
it eventually closes, leaving behind a scar as a
testament to your resilience. Emotional wounds
are no different. They need care and attention, not force.
Healing comes when we stop trying to control the process and instead
trust that it's unfolding exactly as it should.
There's a beautiful truth in the way nature heals itself.
When a forest burns, it seems like a disaster.
The child remains a stark, barren lifeless. But over
time, new growth begins to appear.
Tiny shoots push through the ashes. Seeds that lay dormant awaken,
and life returns in ways that are often richer and
more vibrant than before.
The forest doesn't rebuild itself overnight, but it does
rebuild in its own time. It finds
a way to thrive again.
And so it is with us. Healing is not about returning
to who we were before the pain. It's about becoming
someone new, someone shaped by the experience, but not defined by it.
It's about learning to carry our scars with grace, to let them remind
us not of what we lost, but of what we gained. Strength,
wisdom, and the ability to move forward with an open heart.
It's important to remember that healing is not linear.
Some days, you'll feel like you're making progress,
and other days you might feel like you're right back where you started.
But this, too, is part of the process. Healing is
a journey, not a destination.
It's a continual unfolding, a gradual letting
go of what no longer serves us so that we can make room
for what's next. We often think of healing as something we
must do alone. But it's worth remembering that
connection can be a powerful part of the process. Process.
Whether it's leaning on a friend, seeking guidance from
a mentor, or simply allowing yourself to be seen and heard,
healing happens in the presence of compassion,
both from others and from ourselves.
So let it heal. Let it take the time it needs.
Trust that the pain you feel now is not forever, that the cracks it
leaves behind will someday let in the light. Healing isn't
about erasing the hurt. It's about transforming it into something
beautiful. Because when we allow ourselves to
heal, we're not just mending what's broken. We're becoming whole
again in a way we never thought
possible. Letting go is often misunderstood.
People talk about it as if it's a simple, single act,
like opening your hand to release something you're holding.
But in truth, letting go is a process, not an event.
It's not about forgetting or pretending something didn't happen.
It's about releasing the grip of attachment. Not to the
experience itself, but to the story we tell ourselves about
it. You see, we're storytellers by nature.
We weave narratives about what happened, why it happened,
what it says about us. When something ends,
we often replay it in our minds over and over, trying to make sense of
it, trying to rewrite the past in a way that feels
less painful. But the past is unchangeable.
What we can change is our relationship to it.
Letting go doesn't mean erasing memories or denying
emotions. It means loosening our attachment to the
way things were. It's about recognizing that clinging
to what's gone only prolongs the suffering.
Imagine trying to swim while holding onto a heavy
rock. No matter how strong you are, the weight
will pull you down. The moment you let it go,
though, you find yourself free to float, to move, to breathe.
And yet, letting go isn't always easy. There's a
fear that if we release our hold, we'll lose something vital,
something that feels like it's part of who we are. But here's the
thing. What's meant for you will never require you to cling so tightly.
The connections, experiences, and opportunities
that truly belong in your life will stay, not because you're
holding on, but because they are meant to.
Letting go is also an act of trust. It's trusting
that life knows what it's doing, even when we don't. It's trusting that
endings are not punishments, but transitions. Think of the
leaves falling from a tree in autumn. The tree doesn't
fight to keep them. It lets them fall, knowing that
in time, new growth will come. The bare branches
are not a loss. They're a preparation for renewal.
There's freedom in letting go, a lightness that comes when we release what
no longer serves us. But to find that freedom,
we must face the discomfort of the in between, the space where we've
let go of the old but haven't yet stepped into the new.
It can feel unsettling, even empty. But it's in this
space that transformation happens. It's where we
rediscover who we are without the weight of the past holding us back.
And as we let go, we must also forgive not
just others, but ourselves.
Forgiveness doesn't mean condoning what happened. It means freeing yourself
from the burden of resentment. It's a gift you give yourself,
a way of cutting the cord that ties you to the pain.
Because holding on to anger or blame only binds you
tighter to what you're trying to release.
Letting go is ultimately an act of love.
Love for yourself, for your growth, for the life that's waiting for you. Beyond the
hurt, it's about creating space, not just for healing,
but for possibility. When we let go, we make
room for something new to enter. We open the door
to experiences, connections and opportunities we might
never have imagined while holding on to the past.
So let it go, not with force or resistance,
but with gentleness and grace. Trust that life has
a way of unfolding exactly as it should, even when
we can't see the bigger picture. And as you
release what no longer serves you, you. You'll find yourself
lighter, freer, and ready to step forward into the next
chapter, unburdened and open to all that is yet to come.
When something ends, it's natural to feel an ache,
a kind of emptiness that seems to echo louder than
anything else. But it's in this space, this gap
between what was and what is yet to come, that the seeds of growth
are planted. Pain has this remarkable way
of shaping us, of carving deeper wells within
us to hold more joy, more love, and more understanding.
Yet for this to happen, we must
allow ourselves to sit with the discomfort, to feel it fully
and let it guide us toward transformation.
You see, pain is not the enemy. It's a teacher,
one that we often try to ignore or run from.
But avoiding pain only prolongs its lesson.
When we resist it, we give it power over us.
When we allow ourselves to feel it, however, we reclaim that power.
Pain, in its raw and unfiltered state, is simply
energy. It moves through us not to punish, but to
awaken. It reminds us of what we care
about, what we've lost and what we've gained through the experience of
simply being alive. Think of a storm when
it comes. The winds howl, the rain pours, and it feels overwhelming.
But no storm lasts forever.
Eventually, the skies clear, and in their place, we often find
the air fresher the earth renewed. Our pain
works much the same way. It sweeps through us,
demanding our attention. But if we let it move, if we let it
flow, it passes, leaving us clearer, stronger,
and more aligned with our true selves.
Yet there's a vulnerability in letting yourself feel deeply.
Society tells us to be strong, to move on quickly, to distract
ourselves with busyness. But real strength
lies in allowing yourself to break open. It's in saying,
this hurts and staying with that hurt long enough to understand it.
In the breaking, something extraordinary happens. You begin to heal,
not by avoiding the pain, but by. But by moving
through it. Healing isn't about forgetting or
erasing the past. It's about integrating it,
about letting it become part of your story without letting it define you.
When we face our pain, we discover something unexpected,
a resilience we didn't know we had. And with that
resilience comes wisdom, the kind that
can only be earned by walking through the fire and emerging
on the other side. There's a kind
of beauty in pain, as strange as that might
sound. It strips away the superficial, the distractions
and the noise, leaving only what truly matters.
It forces us to confront ourselves, to ask the questions
we might otherwise avoid. Who am I without this?
What do I really need? What am I being called
to learn? These questions don't have easy answers,
but they open the door to a deeper understanding of ourselves
and the world around us. And while the
process of healing through pain can feel isolating, it's also one
of the most profoundly human experiences we share.
Everyone has felt loss, disappointment, or heartbreak in
some form. To feel pain is to be alive, to be connected
to the great tapestry of existence. And in
that connection, we find the strength to keep going and
let the pain move through you. Don't cling to it, but don't
rush it either. Give it space to teach you what it needs
to teach, and then let it flow. It's in this surrender
that we find freedom, not from the pain, but within
it. Because when we allow ourselves to hurt,
we also allow ourselves to heal, to grow and to
emerge anew. And so,
in the end, it's not the pain that defines us, but what we do with
it. Let it guide you, shape you, and remind you
of the strength that lies within. Let it teach you
that even in the darkest moments, you have the capacity to rise,
to realize, to heal, and to carry on.
There comes a moment when, after all the struggle, all the reflection
and all the healing, we are faced with the final, inevitable act.
Letting gas. It's a concept that can feel simple in
theory, but is often anything but in practice.
Letting go asks us to release the weight we've been carrying.
The pain, the attachments, and even the stories we've told ourselves
about who we are. It's not a sign of giving up or forgetting.
It's an act of courage, an act of trust.
It's stepping forward into the unknown without the baggage
of the past holding you back. The hardest
part of letting go is not the act itself, but the fear of what
comes after. We cling to what's familiar
even when it no longer serves us, because we're
afraid of the void that might take its place.
But this fear is an illusion. Letting go isn't about
creating emptiness. It's about creating space. Space for something
new, something unexpected, something better than what we can imagine
while we're holding on so tightly. Think of the autumn
leaves. They don't resist the wind when it comes
to sweep them from the branches. They let go,
trusting that the tree will survive, that it will flourish again in spring.
In the same way, letting go allows us to move with the natural rhythms
of life. It aligns us with the flow of existence
rather than keeping us stuck in resistance.
And what is it we hold on to? Really often,
it's not the person, the situation or the thing itself,
but the idea of what it meant to us,
the potential it carried, the identity it gave us,
the comfort it provided. But when we
hold on to something too long, we lose sight of who we are without it.
We let it define us, even as it begins to weigh us down.
Letting go, then, is an act of reclaiming ourselves.
It's not always immediate, and it's rarely
easy. Sometimes we have to let go, piece by
piece, moment by moment, until one day we realize the
grip has loosened and the burden is no longer ours
to carry. Other times, it's a sudden
release, like a dam breaking, flooding us with relief and
clarity all at once. Either way, the result is
the same. Freedom. Freedom from the expectations,
the hurt, the regret.
Freedom to be present, to move forward and
to embrace life as it is, rather than as we wish it had been.
This isn't to say that letting go is without pain.
There will be moments of longing, moments where the past beckons, like an
old friend. But these moments are reminders
of our humanity, not reasons to turn back.
They are opportunities to honour what was without
losing sight of what is and what could be.
Letting go is an act of love, not just for others, but for yourself.
It's recognizing that holding on to what no longer aligns with your
Growth is a form of self betrayal.
It's choosing to nurture your well being over clinging to
something that stunts it. It's saying I deserve to move
forward and allowing yourself the grace to do so.
And in letting go, we find that we are not left with nothing,
but with everything we need. The lessons we've learned, the strength
we've gained, the clarity we found, they remain with us,
shaping us into who we are meant to become. Letting go
doesn't mean losing it means making room for more.
So when the time comes, and you know it will,
let it go. Not because it's easy, not because
it's painless, but because it's necessary.
Because holding on will only keep you tethered to a past that no
longer exists. Let go and you'll find that
the act itself is not an end, but a beginning.
The beginning of a life lived fully, freely and unapologetically
in the present.
Some people will use a symbolism of the
relationship of God to the universe, wherein God
is, say, brilliant light,
only somehow veiled, hiding underneath all
these forms that you see as you look around you.
So far, so good. But the truth is funnier than that.
It is that you are looking right at the brilliant light
now that the experience you
are having, which you call ordinary everyday consciousness,
pretending you're not it, that experience is
exactly the same thing as it. There's no difference at
all.
And when you find that out, you laugh yourself silly.
That's the great discovery.
In other words, when you really start to see things and
you look at an old paper cup and
you go into the nature of what it is to see,
what vision is, or what smell is, or what touch is,
you realize that that vision of the paper cup
is the brilliant light of the cosmos.
Nothing could be brighter. 10,000 suns couldn't
be brighter. Only they
are hidden in the sense that all the points of the infinite
light are so tiny when you see them in the cup,
they don't blow your eyes out, but it is actually.
See, the source of all light is in the eye. If there
were no eyes in this world, the sun would not be light.
You evoke light out of the universe.
In the same way you, by virtue of having a soft skin,
evoke hardness out of wood.
Wood is only hard in relation to a soft skin.
It's your eardrum that evokes noise out of the air.
You, by being this organism, call into being
the whole universe of light and color and hardness and heaviness
and everything you see. But in
the mythology that we've sold Ourselves on. During the end of the 19th century,
when people discovered how big the universe was and that
we live on a little planet in a solar system on the edge of a
galaxy, which is a minor galaxy, everybody thought,
ah, we're really unimportant. After all,
God isn't there and doesn't love us and nature doesn't give a damn,
and we put ourselves down, see? But actually,
it's this little funny microbe, tiny thing
crawling on this little planet that's way out somewhere
who has the ingenuity by nature of this
magnificent organic structure to evoke the whole universe
out of what would otherwise be mere quanta.
There's jazz going on.
But you see, this little, little ingenious organism
is not merely some stranger in this.
This little organism on this little planet is
what the whole show is growing there and
so realizing its own presence.
Well, now, here's the problem.
If this is the state of affairs, which is so,
and if the. The consciousness state you are
in at this moment is the same thing as what we might call the divine
state, if you do anything to make it different, it shows
you don't understand that it's so.
So the moment you start practicing yoga or praying or
meditating or indulging in some sort of spiritual cultivation,
you are getting in your own way.
The Buddha said, we suffer because we
desire. If you can give up desire, you will suffer.
But he didn't say that as the last word. He said that as the opening
step of a dialogue. Because if he.
If you say that to someone, they're going to come back after a while and
say, yes, but I'm now desiring not to desire.
And so the Buddha will answer, well, at last you're beginning to understand the point,
because you can't give up desire.
Why would you try to do that? It's already desire.
So in the same way you say you ought to be unselfish or to
give up your ego. Let go, relax. Why do you want to do
that? Just because it's another way of beating the game, isn't it?
The moment you see, you hypothesize that you are different from the universe.
You want to get one up on it.
But if you try to get one up on the universe and you're in competition
with it, it means you don't understand. You are it.
You think there's a real difference between self and other. But self,
what you call yourself and what you call other are
mutually necessary to each other, like back and front.
They're really one. But just as A magnet polarizes itself in
north and south, south, but it's all one magnet. So experience polarizes
itself as self and other, but it's all one.
So if you try to make the North Pole, get the mastery of
it, or the South Pole, get the mastery of the North Pole, you show you
don't know what's going on. A guru or
teacher who wants to get this across to somebody because he knows it
himself, and when you know it, you know you like others to see it
too. So what he does is he gets you into
being ridiculous harder and more
assiduously than usual.
In other words, if you are in a contest with the universe,
he's going to stir up that contest until it becomes ridiculous.
And so he sets you such tasks as saying, now, of course,
in order to be a true person, you must give
up yourself, be unselfish.
So the Lord sits, steps down out of heaven and
says, first and great commandment is, thou shalt
love the Lord thy God. You must love me.
Well, that's a double bind. You can't love on
purpose. You can't be
sincere purposely. It's like trying not to think of a
green elephant while taking medicine.
But if a person really tries to do it, so you know, this is
where Christianity is rigged, you should be very sorry
for your sins. And though everybody knows they're not,
but they think they ought to be, and so they go around trying to be
penitent or trying to be humble,
and they know the more assiduously they practice it, the phonier and phonier
the whole thing gets. And so
in this way, it's what it's called the technique of
reductio ad absurdum. If you
think you have a problem, you see, and that you're an ego and that
you're in difficulty, the answer that the Zen master makes to you is,
show me your ego. I want to see. See this thing that has a problem.
When Bodhidharma, the legendary
founder of Zen, came to China, a disciple
came to him and said, I have no peace of mind. Please pacify
my mind. And Bodhidharma said, bring out your mind here before me, and I'll pacify
it. Well, he said, when I look for it, I can't find it. So Bodhidharma
said, there, it's pacified,
see, because when you look for your own mind, that is to say, your own
particularized center of being, which is separate from everything
else, you won't be able to find it. The only way you'll know
it isn't there is if you look for it hard enough to find out that
it isn't there. And so
everybody says, all right, know yourself, look within, find out
who you are. Because the harder you look, you won't be able to find it.
And in then you realize that it isn't there at all. There isn't a separate
you. Your mind is what there is
everything. But the only way to find that out
is to persist in the state of delusion as hard as possible.
That's one way. I don't say the only way, but it is one way.
And so almost all spiritual disciplines,
meditations, prayers, etc, etc,
our ways of persisting in folly,
doing resolutely and consistently what
you're doing already.
So if a person believes that the earth is flat, you can't
talk him out of that. He knows it's flat. Look out of the window and
see. It's obviously it looks flat. So the only way to
convince him that it isn't is to say, well, let's go and find the edge.
And in order to find the edge, you've got to be very careful not to
walk in circles. You'll never find it that way.
So we got to go consistently in a straight line due west along
the same line of latitude. And eventually, when we get back to
where we started from, you've convinced the guy that the
earth is round. But that's
the. That's the only way that'll tell. That will teach him.
Because people can't be talked out of illusions.
It is in this sense that a person becomes, in the truest sense
of the word, a self, an original,
authoritative source of life.
During the past few months I have been studying
an extraordinarily interesting paper written
by Joseph Campbell, whose name will be familiar to
many of you as the author of a
book on mythology called the Hero with a Thousand Faces.
Now this particular paper, the Symbol without Meaning, is an exploration
of an extraordinary phenomenon in the history of religions
which you might call the. Into the beginning,
the development and the dissolution of cosmologies
of great views of the world under religio
philosophical auspices, which are the,
as it were, the languages about the universe
devised by various cultures.
Now he distinguishes two great phases in man's
religious history which
he equates with two styles of culture
which predate our own technological
style of culture. And these are respectively,
the hunting cultures and the agrarian cultures.
He points out that the kind of religion which is characteristic of
a hunting culture is what now generally goes by the name of shamanism.
Although this particular word Is distinctive of
Mongolian styles Of so
called primitive religion. Nevertheless, the phenomenon known as shamanism.
Is found distributed all over the planet.
Shamanism is characterized
by the fact that it's a very
individualistic type of religiousness. That is to say,
the religious experience of the shaman. Is not something which
he gets from an authoritative priesthood.
It's not something handed down from generation to generation.
For which he goes to a human teacher.
The shamana is a solitary medicine
man. Man of power.
Invariably has to find his experience for himself.
Usually it is by going alone into the
dangers of the forests or jungles.
Or holding himself up for some days in
his own hut. And undergoing some
kind of ordeal. Not necessarily on the
physical level. So much as on the psychic level. Going through an adventure
in the psychic world. The world of spirits.
And when he comes through the ordeal,
he comes out an initiate of
power.
The reason why one must attach so much importance.
To the individual character of this experience. Is that it goes along with the
general style of a hunting culture. In which every
individual man contains the
whole culture. That is to say, it's not the kind of culture in which specialized
functions are needed. In which there is a division of labor.
The hunter spends much of his time on
his own. And he has to learn to take care of
himself in the forests.
Without any other human aid.
And although there are societies
and social groups. They are composed of men with
their women and children. Men who are equals because of
the type of life that they follow.
Now, an entirely different state of affairs arises. When we get
a settled agrarian culture here.
Because the style of life is more complex.
A division of labor is required.
And you begin to get not only a separation of human beings.
Into various castes and various functions.
But also the necessity of devising far
more complex, complex languages and institutions.
To provide communication between them.
And this always involves a very,
very powerful socialization. Of the individual.
Spending his time more and more in a settled place. And therefore having
greater intercourse with other people. He has to learn to think
in accordance with common patterns.
Whether these patterns be based on language.
Or on the type of work.
The geographical features of the area
which he inhabits. Or whatever they may be. Each individual
has to subordinate himself more and more.
To a socially implanted
view of life. Because only on these.
Under these conditions. Is communication between the individuals possible.
And so it comes about that the style of religiousness. Which one
associates with an agrarian. As distinct from a hunting culture.
Is a traditional and authoritative style
of religion. In which the individual derives
his experience From a tradition.
Usually embodied in a priesthood And
Campbell goes on to point out that
the first historical instances of
the appearance of the familiar circle symbol, which is called in
Sanskrit, the mandala,
is associated with the agrarian cultures.
No example of this kind of symbol is found archaeologically prior
to the development of
an agrarian community.
Now, I might say something about the mandala as a
world mythological symbol, Although anybody who studied the works of
CG Jung is very familiar with it. A mandala
is essentially a circle, usually divided
into four quarters or multiples of four, and has
in it, as it were, the general theme of the integration
of a community.
It is not unlike, for example, a stockaded village
or city, a ring of defense
around the center.
And Campbell shows that the
symbol represents the formation of the kind of society
we're talking about where the
human functions are divided. And we find in many of these ancient societies that the
functions are precisely divided into four for
groups. Just as in medieval European
society, we had the spiritual power, the priesthood,
the temporal power, the nobility,
the commons and the
serfs, so in ancient Indian society,
we had the Brahmana caste, the priesthood, the Kshatriya
caste, the rulers and soldiers,
the Vaishya caste, the commons or merchants,
and the Shudra caste, the laborers.
So these four castes represented, as it were,
represented by the four divisions of the mandala,
the common, integrated,
encircled community.
And the important point
that he makes about its religiousness is, as I said, that it was an
experience carried down
by tradition, an experience in
which a priestly caste was
the authority, and which had
to be a common experience, just because
the whole style of life in a community of this kind depended upon
communication. And we can communicate
with each other by virtue, not only of sharing a common language,
but also, more importantly, by sharing a common view of
the world. A common type of
sensuous experience is, of course, why those who
have the type of sensuous experiences which we call hallucinations
and illusions do not fit easily into a community.
But every so often, his paper goes on to show the
social cosmologies. Views of the world held in common by
societies tend to break up.
And actually, he starts the paper in
the 15th century, when, through the expansion
of the Western world, through not only exploration
of the surface of the globe, but greater knowledge of
astronomy, begins to break up the geocentric
view of the Ptolemaic universe,
the view of the world under which Christianity itself had come to birth.
And this he looks upon as a breaking
up of the mandala,
a breaking up of the
communal, agreed, stable picture of the world
by means of which men were able to communicate. With each other
and a breaking up, therefore, which involves a disruption
of all our means of communication and
a throwing of culture into
a fundamental confusion.
It is perhaps, if this be true,
just because of the breaking up
of the unified worldview and an
entry into the confused world of the relativistic world of modern
thought, that the Western peoples have become interested
in other and former attempts to deal with
life as it. As it must be lived when
the mandala, as it were, breaks up.
For after all, the idea of
going beyond the communal view of the world and
somehow managing to get along without it is not a new thing.
It's very interesting that in ancient Indian society,
and to some extent even still in modern Indian society,
that when a man has done his work in society
and is able to hand over his caste duties,
whether they be priestly or political or professional, to his
son or sons, that,
as I think you all know, he, as it were,
abandons the world and
gives up caste and becomes what is ordinarily called
a sannyasin. We speak
of that usually as holy man or hermit or
spiritual devotee of some kind. But what is of particular interest
in this connection is the. The abandonment
of caste is also called
entering into the state of Vanaprastha.
Vanaprastha in Sanskrit means a forest dweller.
And in this sense, the man who gives up caste
goes back, as it were, to the style
of life that predates the agrarian culture. He goes, as it
were, back to shamanism.
And this is true not only in Indian culture, but also
in Chinese. For whereas the Confucian
way of life represents the community weltenchaum,
that is what the mandala corresponds to,
the enclosed, nice little, tight little world in which we feel
we understand each other and understand our environment.
In China, the Daoist philosophy
is the philosophy
corresponding to the Indian search
for liberation or moksha, liberation, that is to say,
from the socially conditioned view of the world.
And there is evidence to show that the Taoist
solitary sage has some
sort of ancestral connection with the shaman.
Of course, we should not suppose that the entry
into the stage of Vanaprastha or the return to the forest by the Taoist
sage is, in the strict sense of the word, a regression,
going back to the shaman's religion, going back to
the life of the hunter, and at the same time going
beyond the place where we find ourselves in a society where the
worldview is a conditioned social pattern.
Now, in what sense and in just what way is this going
beyond? And likewise, how does it apply to our
own situation where we are not, as it were, going voluntarily beyond
a nice, clear,
authoritative and comfortable view of the world. But rather being forced
beyond it by the very pressure of events, by the uncertainty of our times.
And by the confusion and
instability of modern thought.
Which offers us no secure and
humanly comfortable picture of the universe.
Well, first of all, it must be obvious that one
of the things that is principally involved.
By a social system of communication.
Is that it is a form of what Korzybski has called time binding.
The whole possibility of thought and language involves a
codification of experience.
It involves a
form of thinking about
life. Which is basically,
after all, description. Now,
description is a
way of coding, putting into symbols the
events that go by us. And as
we begin to be able to put events into symbols.
We develop most peculiar powers of memory.
It becomes much easier to recollect and to formalize what
has happened to us. And along with this, naturally goes the ability
to project our recollection.
Into thoughts about the future course of events.
And this, apparently, is something which primitive,
very primitive types of human being. In which animals do
not do to any great extent. But the
price that is always paid for this ability to describe
and to prefigure what is going to happen to
us. Is that it has a very, very alarming effect upon our
emotions. Because we
are able, by being able to think about all sorts
of future possibilities. To experience the emotions
appropriate to those possibilities. As if they were present happenings.
In other words, the civilized man tends to be in a state
of chronic worry and fear and anxiety. Because he's always
confronted not with the simple actuality of what is happening before him.
But with the innumerable possibilities of what might happen.
And since, because of this, his emotional existence
tends to be in a chronic state of anxiety and tension,
he loses increasingly the
ability to relate to
the concrete world. As it manifests
itself to him. In the actual present in which he lives.
He becomes so tied up inside that, as it were, the channels of
his sensibility become blocked. He gets a
kind of neurological sclerosis. A kind
of inability to give himself
to be spontaneous, to be alive
with full, joyous abandon. Thus, the more
civilized we become, the more stuffy we get.
And therefore the various ways
of liberating oneself from society,
of entering what the Indians call vanaprastha,
the life of forest dweller going back to the forest.
When a person reaches a certain point in life. When he says, now, look here,
I've had enough of all this. I'm simply tired
of making life not in
the least bit worth living by Going through
the horrors as to what might happen,
of going through all this in the name of efficiency
and membership in the community. Let me for
a while get away from it all and find out what the scarlet stories for
myself, I'm tired of being told what I ought
to believe. I'm tired of being told how I ought to see, how I
ought to behave, how I ought to feel. Let me
find out for myself who I really am.
And so these institutions
of going back, as it were, to the shaman
state of religion, of getting away from the community interpretation
of how one ought to think and feel,
arise in very many great cultures of the past.
Now they arise, therefore, again today.
And it's perhaps impossible
and misleading to try and have what
I would call authoritative attitude about this phase of man's
spiritual exploration.
Sometimes, for example, when a person wants to find out who he really is,
he goes to a psychiatrist. And occasionally he
will find a kind of psychiatrist who does not have an authoritative
view of what human health is and who simply helps the individual
to find his own way. Other times,
unfortunately, we will find doctrinaire psychotherapists
who think they know what an integrated, healthy and normal human being is,
and who have a whole theoretic pattern of what is
believed to be the actual fact of what
I believe to be the actual facts of human nature, the actual design of
the psyche. And they attempt, consciously or subconsciously,
to wangle the patient into accepting this view.
Alternatively, we may get from the Orient accounts
books about authorities, about their ways of
liberation, which in many cases, however, have tended to harden
into an orthodoxy and to present a traditional spiritual
experience just as if they were the kind of spiritual experiences
which it is the function of that social officer, the priest,
to impart.
And thus when we get swamis
representing an orthodox interpretation of Indian
moksha or liberation, or when we get
even Zen masters representing perhaps an orthodox
Buddhist experience, or seeming to represent one,
we should be suspicious. Because these are the
kind of experiences which cannot be transmitted,
which, for their very nature, are something which one
finds out for oneself and which
looks, they could be explained, if they could be transmitted, would not
be the very thing which they are intended to be.
Because they are discoverers of
something authentic, of something genuine, of something which is firsthand
between oneself and one's universe.
And thus it's in the nature of things that they
can't be codified, they can't be made a factor in social
communication.
And so it is that it is, in a way, fortunate that
we here in the Western world do
not have too Many authoritative
masters and teachers to whom we feel we can now go
for enlightenment. More and more of us, I think, tend to feel that
we are all alone together, whistling in the dark, that we haven't a savior.
There is no statesman clever enough to understand
the frightful tangle of international affairs. Or really
to do anything very much about it. There is no psychologist
or physician or philosopher. Who really impresses
us as having the last word on everything. More and
more, each one of us are thrown on our own resources.
This seems to me to be a perfectly excellent state of affairs.
So that we become, in a symbolic sense, back in the forest.
Like the hunter of old. Who has nobody
around him to tell him how he ought to feel and how he ought to
use his senses. And must therefore make his own exploration
and find out for himself. But you
know, when you study the records of these self discoveries, the fascinating
thing is that there seems to be such
a common measure of agreement between all
those who find out for themselves.
And yet always the way in which he has to find out.
Is not through seeking agreement with others, not trying to
find what others have found, but only to
find what his own senses and his own direct experience
tell him. When he, as it were, goes into his
inner closet, goes into his own secret place
and asks for
a direct encounter with
the world. And no longer,
as it were, looks out of the corner of his eyes to see if everybody
else is doing the same thing and getting the same results.
It is in this sense that a person becomes, in the truest sense
of the word, a self. An original,
authoritative source of life. As distinct
from a person in its original sense,
a mask, a role that he is playing
in a society.