Isn't it true that swans are monogamous?
It's a very funny thing that when they begin to mate, they start fighting and
they don't know what it's all about. Then suddenly the fight turns into lovemaking.
Underneath duality, there's unity.
The Tweedledum and Tweedledee agreed to have a battle.
So, you see, here's that weaving principle.
The things hold together by over, under, under, over,
over, under, under, over, over, under, under.
And that creates a stuff, it creates a
fabric, it creates clothing, it creates shelter,
creates what we call matter,
matter and
also the same word. Maya. Illusion.
See the world as a
marvelous illusion. We have
tried scientifically to understand the world
and explain its mysteries by
analyzing the smallest, smallest particles
of things that exist,
inquiring down, down, down, what is this thing we call flesh
or call steel or stone? What is it
made of? Go down into the midst
of it, and that's given us a certain understanding.
But only half of the understanding,
equally important, is not what
is the tiniest part, but in what
context is the tiniest particle.
You see, in. In relation to what is
it? Just as the word bark, as I
showed you, has different meanings in different sentences.
So cells, molecules, atoms have
different properties in different contexts.
So what the scientist equally needs to study is
not simply what is anything when
very, very minutely analyzed, but where
is it? When is it that makes all
the difference?
Relativity isn't some kind of
slippery morass in
which all standards and all directions
get lost. Relativity is
really the soundest situation that there is.
See, it's the. It's the one supporting the other. It's this thing,
sharpness, teeth,
biting spines, crab shells,
all that kind of thing. You know, on the other side, it's the melting softness
of life.
See, they go together just like that.
If you see that, if you. If you get that principle,
you can feel yourself not
sort of just rattling around in the world as a kind of somebody
who's been stuck down there, but you can
feel yourself
going on in
absolutely exact relationship with everything around
you.
And this is very beautiful.
It isn't just that you are here looking
at what's out there like
you might be photographing it with your eyes.
It's that if that there wasn't there,
you wouldn't be here.
The outside thing that you see and the inside thing that
you are are poles
of the same magnet or
back and front of the same coin.
And without one, there isn't the other.
That means, of course, then, that we are living in
the midst of a world of
animals, vegetables, minerals,
atmospheres,
astronomical bodies. That's highly
intelligent. It's intelligence
concentrated, crystallized in our brains.
That's where it comes out. You see, in any
field, let's take any field of forces, we take
a sort of chemical solution, and at certain critical
points in this chemical solution, the crystals start to form.
And so in the same way the total intelligence of this whole
universe crystallizes in human brains,
also in other kinds of brains.
That's where it really comes out.
But it's total intelligence of the whole field that
does this. So we
go with the whole thing, interdependent with it.
We don't live in an environment which is just
rock, just air, just atmosphere
and so on. The environment's only like that when we
think about it analytically and
try to explain it. But when we think of it
isn't just rock and air. See,
but those things go together. When you see
the interconnectedness, when you see in the simplest way how flowers
go with bees and other insects, they don't
live without them, humans go
with cattle, they don't exist without them,
plants, et cetera, etc. Etc. Etc. When you see the intervals,
the significance of the relationships between these things,
it's only then when you see that, that you are
aware of the melody.
Go back to the illustration I gave of the person who can't hear melody,
who's tone deaf. He hears only a succession of sounds because he's not
aware of the intervals. Now, most people are brought up to be tone
deaf in respect to their own existence and the rest of the universe.
They don't see the relationships, they are not aware of the universe.
Once you spot that, you spot how everything
goes with the thing, that you are one end and that out there
is the other end, and they really go together,
then you may be said to be living a harmonious life.
When life gets busy, pause,
take a breath and reset your mind. Download mindset
and listen to your favorite inspirational speeches to unlock your full potential.
The very idea of the future has something spurious
in it to live for. The future
is an indefinite postponement of life.
The great political systems of the Western world,
whether they be capitalist or communist,
are based on the notion
that what we live for is the future. It's always a five
year plan for something to turn up that will be better
than what we have now later on. Our notions of
the great Society are based on a
futurist approach to life, wherein you
go through in your education a whole series of steps.
The word in Latin, gradus, means a step.
So we have first grade, second grade, third grade, gratus,
gratis, gratis. Finally become a graduate. But you're
still doing it. So that when you become
finally successful as the president of your
corporation, you have a funny feeling
of being cheated.
You climbed the stairway and you got to the top, and there's
nowhere else to go. And since you've never
been taught to live in the present, you don't know how to.
So an insurance salesman comes around and
says, listen, I've got the very thing for you.
Retirement program. Because when you're 65,
you'll drop out of the system. And then you'll
really be able to enjoy yourself despite your
prostate trouble, menopause, false teeth and
everything else.
So the art of living in the eternal now is not
taught in our educational system.
And it's not taught because it's thought of as being feckless,
irresponsible. It isn't irresponsible at all.
It's. It is everybody's duty, I could put it that way.
To enjoy themselves.
Because if you don't do that, you become a nuisance,
you become aggressive, you become a robber, you become a thief.
You become somebody who's trying to organize
the rest of the world. That is to say, a power maniac.
Simply because you haven't learned the very simple,
inexpensive art of living in the present moment.
It really doesn't take an awful lot of energy to
maintain a human life.
If you really consider what you need to eat,
what you need to wear, how much housing you have to have.
It comes down to something quite simple.
And the simpler, the more you have
the capacity to enjoy watching
a raindrop crawl down a window.
But if you watch a raindrop crawl down a window and you think, my,
look at that, everybody says you're crazy.
You're watching a raindrop fall down a widow. Can't you find something more important to
do? That means, can't you make more trouble than that?
So the mentality that doesn't recognize
the importance of watching a raindrop crawl down a window is
the one that is creating the trouble in the world today.
We say you are of no value. You're not even human unless
you're changing things, unless you're interfering, unless you're progressing.
We confuse growing with progressing. Unless something is happening
and great operation, a new project is going on and you're busy with
it. We say, well, you're, you, you're. You're lazy,
you're good for nothing because you are not working
for the future. But they say if you're working
for the future, you're quite mad.
So they don't work for the future.
And we say, well that's awful, that's irresponsible, you can't
do that. That's not maintaining the world properly.
What do you think? Maybe that is maintaining the world properly.
Maybe it's we who think that everything should be
progressing who are destroying the world.
Of course we are,
by our Protestant ethic, by our notion
keeping everything in charge. It's true, we have a
great initial success. We destroy
diseases, we keep people alive.
But on the end is the H bomb, get rid of
it all entirely. These non
political people are saying to us,
the trouble with you is you don't know what you want.
You have a future which
you're working for, but you're all wretch
and no vomit. You promised yourselves
the good thing is going to happen. Keep promising, promising,
promising, promising. Even your money is a promise.
It says on the dollar bill that the treasury of the United
States will promise to pay a dollar. What are
you going to get if you deliver this and say, come on now,
I want whatever it is in this dollar.
And they just can give you credit because
it's paper, it's all symbolism. So the whole
point is the future
is an illusion.
The basic ideas in Hindu cosmology that in the
course of time you go through the series of yugos
or the epochs, you begin
with a great state of affairs and it gradually deteriorates.
Is a way of saying to people, in the
course of time things only fall apart.
Therefore get out of time,
get off the wheel of samsara,
the rat race.
So this underlies my idea of what
I call the politics of diversion.
Divert Western man from history, from the
notion that he is in a historical process which is
leading to something always better and better and better, but which in fact only
leads to more and more destruction.
Divert people from time by
living a style of life which is timeless
and which is therefore more attractive than
life devoted to time.
People are hypnotized with money, which is
the symbol of wealth, as if it were something that was valuable in its own
right. People don't realize, in other words, that money
is bookkeeping, nothing but bookkeeping.
And therefore the whole idea of taxation, for example,
is a complete anachronism.
The thing that is stopping the flow of
the actual wealth of the world is this fixation on
money. What you need to do is
actually reverse taxation.
Instead of charging taxes, issue credit, but you
have to keep the credit balance to the gross national product
in some form of figuring. And then everybody can
circulate what they're making.
Otherwise, you're in this ridiculous situation where people are starving
in India and we are hoarding food supplies and
burning them and trying dumping them in the ocean, which is a
share insanity. But it's all based on a psychological block about
money. So this kind of
psychological block is what
an Indian philosophy would be called a Maya. It is an illusion.
And it's the same kind of illusion as that of the future.
The idea that the future is when we are really going to live.
And if that's the way you operate when you get there, you're never going to
be able to handle it because you still want a future ahead of you.
You're a perpetual donkey with a carrot suspended
from your collar on a rod like this, and you're pursuing it.
Now, why talk about this? Is it
interesting? Is it important for the
human being to realize that
in some sense of the word, whatever it means,
he is God, or one with God?
A lot of people understand,
but so what?
Well, the importance of it is this.
That to know that you are God is another
way of saying that you feel completely with
this universe. You feel profoundly
rooted in it and connected with it. You feel,
in other words, that the whole energy which expresses itself in the galaxies
is intimate. It is not
something to which you are a stranger, but it
is that with which you, whatever that is, are intimately
bound up. That in your seeing, your hearing,
your talking, your thinking you're moving, you express that
which it is, which moves the sun and other stars.
And if you don't know that, if you don't
feel that, well, naturally you feel alien.
You feel a stranger in the world.
And if you feel a stranger, you feel hostile.
And therefore you start to bulldoze things about to beat
it up and to try and make the world
submit to your will. And you become a real troublemaker.
So I feel also one reason why you become hostile
is that feeling that you were just brought into this place,
that your father and mother went up to some monkey business that they probably
shouldn't have done, or it was bad rubber goods. And as a result of this,
here you are and you didn't ask to be here. Well, you always feel you
can turn around and blame them. You can blame somebody,
you can blame the government, you can blame the rascals, you can blame the
cheaters. Always supposing you yourself aren't a
rascal, which is long odds.
You always can blame someone and say, I Didn't ask
for it, take it away.
And yet, and yet, and yet very few people
are all too ready to take it away.
And if you don't, if you
don't say take it away,
what are you going to do?
You've really got to assume responsibility for it.
You've got to say yes to
what happens.
A lot of people don't know how we got the Bible at all.
We Westerners got the Bible thanks to the Catholic
Church and they took over
the books of the Old Testament, which even by the time of Christ had not
been finally decided upon by the Jews. The Jews
did not close the canon of the Old Testament until the year 100
AD or thereabouts at the Synod of Jamnia.
And then they finally decided which were the canonical books of
the Hebrew Scriptures and embodied them in the Masoretic
text, the earliest copy of which dates from the
10th century, early in the 10th century AD.
The books to be included in the New Testament were not finally decided
upon until the year 382
AD again at the Synod of Rome under Pope Damasus.
So it was the Church, the Catholic Church, that promulgated the Bible
and said, we are giving you these scriptures on
our authority and by the authority of
the informal tradition that has existed among us from the
beginning, inspired by the Holy Spirit.
So you receive historically the Bible on the Church's
say so. And the Catholic Church insists
therefore, that the Church, collectively speaking
under the presumed guidance of the Holy Spirit,
has the authority to interpret the Bible.
And you can take that or leave it.
Hindus believe that the Vedas are divinely
revealed and inspired with just as much fervor as any Christian or any
Jew. Muslims believe that the Quran is
divinely inspired. And some Buddhists believe
that their sutras are also of divine,
or rather a Buddhic origin.
The Japanese believe that the ancient texts
of Shinto are likewise of divine origin.
And who is to be judge?
So if the Church says the Bible is true,
it finally comes down to you. Are you going to believe the church
or aren't you? So really,
I won't deny anybody's right to hold these opinions.
You may indeed believe that the Bible is literally true
and that it was actually dictated by God to
Moses and the prophets and the apostles.
That may be your opinion and you are at liberty to hold it. I don't
agree with you. I do believe,
on the other hand, that there is a sense in which the Bible is divinely
inspired.
But since inspiration
always comes through a human vehicle,
it is liable to be distorted by that vehicle,
in other words, I'm talking to you through a sound system.
And it's the only one now available.
Now, if there's something wrong with this sound system,
whatever truths I might utter to you will be distorted, my voice will be distorted,
and you might mistake the meaning of what I said.
Now, so therefore, everybody who receives divine inspiration,
and I'm using that in a very loose way,
but anybody who receives it will express it within
the limits of what language he knows.
And by language here, I don't only mean English,
Latin, Greek, Hebrew or Sanskrit.
I mean language in the sense of what sort of terms
are available to you. What kind of religion were you brought up with?
My opinion is the Jesus of Nazareth
was a human being, like Buddha,
like Sri Ramakrishna, like Ramana Maharshi,
etc, who early
in life had a colossal experience of what we call cosmic
consciousness. Now, you don't have to be any particular
kind of religion to get this experience. It can hit anyone
anytime, like falling in love in greater
or lesser degree, but it's found all over the world.
And when it hits you, you know it. Sometimes it comes
after long practice of meditations and spiritual discipline.
Sometimes it comes for no reason that anybody can determine.
We say it's the grace of God, that there comes this overwhelming
conviction that you have mistaken your identity,
that what you thought, what I thought was just old Alan
Watts, was only completely superficial.
So you can very well understand how people to
whom this happens feel genuinely
inspired because very often there goes
along with it an extremely warm feeling because
you see the divine in everybody else's
eyes. When Kabir,
a great Hindu Muslim mystic,
was a very old man, he used to look around at people
and say, to whom shall I preach?
Because he saw the beloved in all eyes.
The traditions of Asia,
Hindu, Buddhist, Taoist and so forth, are full of miraculous
stories. And we take them in our stride.
We don't think that there are any sign of anything in particular except
psychic power. And I'm really a little scared
of the growing interest in psychic power, because that's
what I call psycho technics.
And we've made such a mess of things with ordinary techniques that
heaven only knows what we might do if we got hold of psycho technics
and started raising people from the dead and prolonging life
insufferably in. The whole answer to the story of miracles
is simply imagine that you're God.
Now, what happened?
The apostles didn't quite get the point.
They were awed by the miracles of Jesus.
They worshiped him as people do Worship gurus.
And it's, you know, to what lengths that can go if you've been
around guru land. And so the Christian said,
okay, okay, Jesus of Nazareth was the son
of God, but let it stop right there. Nobody else.
So what happened was that Jesus was pedestalized.
He was put in a position that was safely upstairs
so that his troublesome experience of cosmic consciousness would
not come and cause other people to be a nuisance.
And those who have had this experience and expressed it during
those times when the Church had political power were almost invariably
persecuted. Guardiano Bruno was burnt
at the stake. John Scotus original was excommunicated.
Meister Eckhart's theses were condemned, and so
on and so on. A few mystics got away with it because
they used cautious language.
But you see what happens if you pedestalize Jesus.
You strangle the gospel at birth. And it has been the tradition
in both the Catholic Church and
in Protestantism to
pass off what I will call an
emasculated gospel.
Gospel means good news. And I cannot for
the life of me think what is the good news about. The gospel is ordinarily
handed down. Here is the revelation of God in Christ,
in Jesus. And we are supposed to follow his life
and example without having the unique
advantage of being the boss's son,
born of a virgin, knowing he is the son
of God, having the power of miracles,
knowing that basically it's impossible to kill him, that he's going to rise
again in the end. And we are asked to take up our cross and follow
him, when we don't know that about ourselves at all.
So what happens is this. We are delivered,
therefore, a gospel which is in fact an impossible religion.
It's impossible to follow the way of Christ.
Many a Christian has admitted it.
I am a miserable sinner. I fall far
short of the example of Christ. But do you realize
the more you say that, the better you are.
Because what happened was that Christianity institutionalized
guilt as a virtue. And therefore
you will always be aware of your shortcomings.
And so the more shortcomings you feel, the more. In other words,
you are aware of the vast abyss between Christ and yourself.
So you go to confession, and if you've
got a nice, dear understanding confessor,
you'll say, my child, you know you've sinned very grievously,
but you must realize that the love of God and of our Lord is infinite
and that naturally you are forgiven.
And you know you've committed a murder and robbed a bank and fornicated
around and so on. The Priest is perfectly patient and quiet.
Well, you feel awful to the love of God. I've wounded Jesus,
grieved the Holy Spirit and so on.
But you know in the back of your mind you're going to do it all
over again. You won't be able to help yourself.
You'll try, but there's
always a greater and greater sense of guilt.
This is the Christianity of most people.
Now there is a much more subtle Christianity of the theologians,
the mystics and the philosophers. But it's not what gets
preached from the pulpit. What would
the real gospel be? The real good news
is not simply that Jesus of Nazareth was the Son
of God,
but that he was a
powerful son of God who came
to open everybody's eyes to the fact that you are
too.
And this is perfectly plain. If you will
go to the tenth chapter of St. John,
verse 30, there is
the passage where Jesus says, I and the
Father are one. There are some people who are not
intimate disciples around, and they're horrified and they immediately pick
up stones to stone him.
He says, many good works I have shown you from the Father,
and for which of these do you stone me?
And they said, for a good work we stone you not, but for blasphemy,
because you, being a man, make yourself God. And he
replied, isn't it written in your law, I have said you are
gods?
He's quoting the 82nd Psalm.
Is it not written in your law, I have said you are gods.
If God called them those to whom he gave his word,
gods. And you can't deny the Scriptures.
How can you say I blaspheme because
I said I am a son of God?
Well, there's the whole thing in a nutshell.
Because if you read the King James Bible that descended with the angel,
you will see in italics in front of these words,
son of God. The Son of God. Because I said I am
the Son of God. And most people think that the italics are for emphasis.
They're not. The italics indicate words interpolated
by the translators. You will
not find that in the Greek. The Greek says a son of God.
So it seems to me here perfectly plain that
Jesus is. Got it in the back of his mind that this isn't
something peculiar to himself. So when
he says I am the way, no man
comes to the Father but by me. This I
am. This me is the divine
in us, which in Hebrew would
be called the ruach Adonai.
So the point is that the ruach is the
divine in the creature by
virtue of which we are sons of or of the nature
of God, manifestations of the divine. This discovery
is the gospel that is the good news.
But this has been perpetually repressed
throughout the history of Western religion,
because all Western religions have taken the
form of celestial monarchies.
Which is not the religion of Jesus,
which was the realization of divine sonship, but the religion
about Jesus which pedestalizes
him and which says only this man of all the
sons of woman was divine. And you had better recognize it
utterly exclusive,
convinced in advance of examining the doctrines of
any other religion that it is the top religion.
And so it becomes a freak religion,
just as it has made a freak of Jesus an unnatural man.
It claims uniqueness, not realizing
that what it does teach would be far more credible
if it were truly Catholic. That is to say,
restated again the truths which have
been known from time immemorial, which have appeared
in all the great cultures of the world.
If then we can see this, that Jesus
speaks not from the situation of
a historical deus ex
machina, a kind of weird extraordinary
event, but he is a voice which
joins with other voices that have said in every
place and time, wake up, man, wake up
and realize who you are.
No scolding, no rational demonstration
of the right way to behave is going to inspire people with love.
Something else must happen.
I feel then you see that it's enormously important that churches
stop being talking shops. They become
centers of contemplation. What is contemplation?
Contemplum. It's what you do in the temple. You don't
come to the temple to chatter, but to be
still and know that I am God.
And this is why, if the Christian
religion, if the gospel of Christ is to mean
anything at all, instead of just being one of the forgotten religions
along with Osiris and Mithra,
we must see Christ as the great mystic,
in the proper sense of the word mystic, not someone who
has all sorts of magical powers and understands spirits and
so on. A mystic, strictly speaking, is one who realizes
union with God by whatever name.
This seems to me the crux and message of the Gospel,
summed up in the prayer of Jesus, which St. John records as
he speaks over his disciples, praying that they may
be one. He even as you, Father, and I are one,
that they may be all one.
All realize this
divine sonship, or oneness,
basic identity with the eternal energy of
the universe and the love that moves the sun
and other stars.
You become aware vividly of the fact that
you as a an individual
imply by your existence everything else that
exists or
ever has existed or ever will exist.
You can't exist as the kind of person you are without all that.
Now that's the secret to the connection between you and the
cosmos. Just as a back doesn't exist without
a front in just that sort
of way, all of it doesn't exist without you,
and you don't exist without all of it.
Welcome to the Alan Watts Being in the Way podcast. I'm your host
Mark Watts, and today and in the coming weeks, we're going to
bring something special to you, which is some of my father's radio talks from
the 90s. Being in a half hour format, these radio
programs are a little shorter than what we've been doing in the past. And so
even though you may be spending a little bit less time with us, I hope
that you'll enjoy the program and seek out our other offerings@AlanWatts.org
where you'll find a variety of selections, including offerings from our new
streaming channel. You'll also find the podcast there and a variety of
other offerings, including biographic material about
my father and his rich legacy. Our podcast today
is out of The Trap, Part 2 this
morning I was discussing the
two great myths which underlie
Western man's sense of identity.
The Judeo Christian myth of
a universe founded upon the personal
decision of a cosmic king, whose image,
however gracious and loving it may be in certain aspects,
is historically founded on the great
monarchs of the ancient near east,
on people like Hammurabi and
Amenhotep iv, and in
their turn, David and Solomon.
Also be it said, on the image of Cyrus who
liberated the Hebrews from their captivity in
the Babylonian empire.
And the very word Cyrus, of course, is the Greek word for Lord.
Kyrie, Kyrios. So Kyrie eleison.
The question is, are we worshiping Cyrus or the Lord of
the universe?
Now I pointed out that this mythology became
intolerable to Western man because it was
a conception of the universe that was just too damn intelligent.
It was the whole thing was peeking on
you. And so it was very comfortable
to be able to exchange this mythology for a conception
of the universe as being purely mechanical, stupid and empty.
Only you paid for that. The price of knowing that you were futile,
that you too were a machine. But some people would rather a
dead universe than a living one, with standards of
righteousness that were a little bit oppressive.
But the point I wanted to make is that the
latter story about the world is just as much of a myth
as the former one. Although this conception
of the Newtonian universe, this mechanical trap, is,
is plausible Today this is merely a
matter of fashion. And so what we saw was
this. You can talk
the universe down by describing everything intelligent in
it as a special form of unintelligence. On the other hand,
you can talk it up by saying that all unintelligent
things are merely special forms of intelligence,
say rather low grade forms of intelligence, intelligence, but intelligent nonetheless.
And that is a more complementary view to things than the
other one. And I was suggesting that it's, on the whole
better policy to pay compliments to life than to give it insults.
As the proverb says, you don't catch flies except with
honey. And after
all, if things do manage to exist and
to go along, the view which
has the positive edge to it is likely to be
better than the one that has the negative edge.
Not because I'm trying to be some sort of Pollyanna person or silly optimist,
but simply because in
the interchange, or you might call it conflict,
game between the various pairs of opposites,
although the snake has the best lines,
the dove wins out in the end because
the dove does it just
a little bit more. You see what I mean? In, for example, in the system
of Hindu cosmology, the period of
manifestation is divided into four yugas, four epochs,
and they differ in length. The best one comes first,
that's the longest, and everything is just splendid. Then there comes
a second epoch that's not so good. It's got
a little. It's a bit off balance, and that lasts pretty long, but not as
long as the first one. Then there comes another epoch in which the powers
of good and evil are equally balanced and that lasts still
shorter. Finally comes the so called Kali Yuga,
which is the worst one, when evil is triumphant and the whole
world blows up at the end, and that's the shortest. So you see,
for exactly 2/3 of the time, if you figure it
all out, the positive forces are in operation,
but the negative ones have their innings because it goes off with such a big
bang at the end.
So this is the way the world ends, not with a whimper, but with a
bang, according to this cosmology.
And furthermore, a thing to console you is that time goes faster
in the Kali Yuga than in the other Yugas. And in
the end, you see, the destruction is personified as Shiva,
who just dances the dance of the Tandava
with all his 10 arms waving with knives and clubs and lightning and everything.
And the whole thing blows up. But the instant it blows up,
everybody wakes up, finds out who they are
and laughs. It's silly because What a terror and how easily overcome.
Now that, of course, again, I'm speaking mythological language.
And it is important to realize this because mythological
language is useful. You can
say things with it you can't say in other ways.
And often mythological ideas are more sophisticated
than what you might call abstract or even scientific ideas.
You see, if you think of the universe as founded on
Brahma or someone like that, even Jehovah,
you've got definitely an anthropomorphic idea of the Lord.
He's the, the old gentleman or he's the great dancer,
whichever image you want to use.
And you might say this is rather primitive. Yes, it is primitive,
but there, there isn't really a better image. If you
think of it as, say, to use Northrop's
inimitable phrase, the undifferentiated aesthetic continuum.
What you've got is a conception vaguely resembling tapioca or
some kind of goo. And that is really an inferior
conception to the human image.
Alas, you see, we don't know anything more evolved than the human image.
You may have had some of you conversations with angels
or with the, the ultimate itself. And when you do meet the ultimate itself itself,
as some of you have, you know that
you can't think about it, but it's certainly not
a minus quantity. It's certainly nothing like goo,
just plain undifferentiated goo.
So the, the advantage of mythological ideas
is that you know they're mythological and therefore you don't take them literally.
That's a very important thing to remember. So don't
worry about people who believe in God. The problem
about believing in God, incidentally, is that
believing is the wrong attitude. Believing is a
form of mistrust because it's saying,
I fervently wish that you exist,
and if you don't, I don't know what to do with myself. Now the,
the real attitude of faith is not believing,
but simply being open to whatever reality is.
And to say you don't know. That's why even in early Christianity,
you find out that they call the highest form of faith
unknowing agnosia in Greek, from which we
get, in its kind of deprived sense, the word
agnostic. But agnosia,
unknowing is the highest form of faith because ultimately, of course,
what is the, the, the final witch than which there is no
witcher, wouldn't completely know itself what it
was, because in order to know what something is,
you have to be able to classify it and you have to compare it with
something it isn't. And so the final Ground of the universe
is perfectly unclassifiable, therefore, strictly speaking,
outside the domain of logic and formal philosophy.
Now, having examined them, these two
mythological forms which underlie
the Western man's intense
feeling of alienation and separateness,
we have to go into another dimension of the question,
and that is the influence upon who we think we
are of our social institutions.
Now, what is a social institution?
We know that there are things like the
family, marriage,
the police, the courts,
the law, the church. And we know that
these are social institutions. But social
institutions are far more subtle than those things.
Time, for example, is a social institution because
it is a matter of convention, that is to say, of coming together to agree
to measure time in a certain way,
way. And we have international agreement about
that. Likewise, obviously, money is
a social institution. So are
weights and measures.
So are ideas of value.
What is the good life? Who is contributing to
society and who is working against it.
So, you see, we were discussing this morning, among other things,
excuse me, the idea of survival.
And that survival is a good thing and
to survive as long as possible is a very good thing. But that is
a form of social institution.
It is something we have come to agree about.
It isn't necessarily true in
the sense that, shall I say,
the French language is not a truer language
than the English.
But so long as people agree to speak a certain language,
they can communicate. And they've decided that communication is
a good thing. So any language that makes communication
possible is a good language.
And in a way, the more people who agree about it, the better.
But it is a matter of agreement, you see.
Same way the lines of latitude and longitude are conventions.
They are. They don't exist. You can't tie
up packages with the equator. But it's a
very useful idea. And so, in the same
way, the ways in which we have shaped the constellations that
we all agree that the stars called the Big Dipper look something
like a dipper. And though,
you know, there aren't any strings tying them together,
the constellation is not there as a constellation.
So, in a sense, we project our institutions
onto the world in rather the same way that psychiatric
patients project images onto a Rorschach blot.
And what interests the psychiatrist is what sort of images this person
produces that tells him something about the person. In the
same way our social institutions tell us something about people.
And furthermore, as I also explained this morning,
people are also members of the external world.
And therefore they tell us something about the external world.
Man is something nature is doing and
is not a stranger, as these two Great myths have
made us believe so.
It's the. The physical facts of the matter are not
that we are confronted with note that word confront
with a world that cares nothing for us and that
has nothing in common with our kind and style of intelligence.
It is rather the very opposite that
the fact that we are intelligent is symptomatic
of the intelligence of the world as a whole.
We live in a highly intelligent environment.
And intelligence, you see, is really a
kind of complex behavior.
When we see some very exquisite
pattern, we look at it and say,
my, isn't that wonderful? Isn't that intelligent
looking? I wonder who did it. Because we associate
all intelligence with a who.
And when you look at a plant, it's obviously intelligent.
Its shape, its rhythm,
all its wonderful tubes inside. Its complex relationship to
bees and birds and to the surrounding
atmosphere and light. This is a very intelligent
affair. Now, in. In just the same way
we are related to the external world as
plants are, in amazingly complicated
ways. And by and large, we don't notice them.
Because the aspect of our consciousness
with which we notice things is very limited.
It notices what it calls facts,
things and events and pinpoints
them. It pulls them out as significant.
You see, when you remember coming here and what you saw
and who was here, you only remember very tiny
bits of the whole scene.
You will not remember what very many people wore unless you
happen to be interested in clothes. You won't really
remember how they did their hair, what their styles were. Unless you are peculiarly
interested in hairstyles. You probably won't notice their
shoes at all and goodness
knows what else that nobody has ever thought to notice.
But when, under certain circumstances, our consciousness
becomes expanded, as in mystical vision,
you begin to become aware of things that you don't notice.
One of the most important things that. That we don't notice is space.
Most people regard space as nothing.
It's just a void in which we move around.
But actually, space is terribly important. It has properties.
We are all something happening in space.
In rather the same way that a whirlpool occurs in water.
Space has turns in.
Has ripples in it. It has places where it's denser than at other places.
And this is all becoming clear in physics.
But it's certainly not impinged upon the consciousness of the
average intelligent person.
So the space in which we live and move and have our being
is an intelligent continuum. It isn't just nothing at all.
There's one little lesson about this that I will.
That you must excuse me for repeating. If you've heard it before, but it's very
important, and it's a lesson in the value of
space. And it's showing you that space
and energy are the same thing. Let us
suppose that we have a universe in which there is only one ball,
and that's all there is. There isn't anything else.
Nobody can say of this ball whether it's moving or not.
Therefore, it doesn't appear to manifest any energy.
You can't say it's moving, and you can't actually say it's still.
There's no way of thinking about it. Now,
introduce into our universe a second ball,
and we notice that they get further apart.
Now, one of them is moving, or both are moving,
but we can't decide which. We only know there is energy here,
there is motion. Why do we know there's energy? Because the space between
them alters, either increases or decreases.
Now let's have three balls, and you
find two of them stay close to each other.
The other one gets further away. Now, which one is moving?
The majority is going to decide. The two that stay together are
going to say we are moving away from that one. Or else,
if they want to argue it differently, they say we are standing still and that
one is moving away from us. You see, all these
views are equally true. But if an argument starts up,
the majority is going to win. But the point is,
you see, space and energy are fundamentally related.
There is no manifestation of energy without space.
Also, we can drag in time. But I don't want to make it complicated.
I want to make this little image as simple as possible, so as to understand
the importance of space, that is to say, of the surroundings,
of things, of the background. And the background is
ignored in ordinary consciousness. But in mystical consciousness, the background
background becomes important.
You become aware vividly of the fact that
you as a an individual imply
by your existence everything else that exists or
ever has existed or ever will exist.
You can't exist as the kind of person you are without all that.
Now that's the secret to the connection between you and the cosmos.
Just as a back doesn't exist without a front in
just that sort of way, all of it doesn't exist without
you, and you don't exist without all of it.
Even if you die, you see and disappear totally.
Nevertheless, the fact that you have existed
is still a fact. And a universe in which there
has been a person like Socrates is quite
a different universe from a universe in which there hadn't
been a person like Socrates. Socrates having
existed is a symptom of the way things are so
fundamentally we get a picture of the cosmos in which
the self, the real I is the whole
thing, just as we say of an individual human
body. You are John Doe and that's all of you.
Although if we look at you very carefully under an electron microscope,
we will find that molecules in your blood are further apart
than the earth and the sun. What makes you think you're a unity?
It's quite a thought. Well, it's space.
And so in the same way as such a relationship
exists between our, our galaxy and other
galaxies and so on, it's obvious.
So then by
various conventions and social institutions,
we develop the impression that this isn't so. We learn to ignore.
We learn not to notice certain things. And you
know, not noticing is very, very important in
the Hindu theory of politics.
All the what our spiritual virtues have
political counterparts. For example,
in the spiritual domain, the word upaya,
up a y a means merciful
techniques for awakening people,
clever devices used by a teacher in
the politic. In the political domain, the word upaya means Cunningham
deceit. Likewise in the spiritual domain,
upeksha means equanimity.
In the political domain, upeksha means overlooking.
When for example, the boss of a big concern finds
that one of his employees is taking out a little bit of the petty cash.
Now he figures out is this man worth it?
Are his services really worth it? And shall I merely
ignore the fact that he's doing this? That would be upeksha.
Now in our whole society we do an enormous amount
of upeksha. The things we
overlook. There are obvious things
that we don't talk about. There is a taboo side to life that we
don't mention. It's we're supposed to overlook
it. You know, when silk stockings were first in invented with
a fine mesh type, a present of several dozen of
them was sent by important American businessman
to the Queen of Spain.
And they were returned by her chamberlain with
a letter which said, you should recognize that her majesty
the Queen of Spain has no legs.
In other words, those legs don't officially exist.
So only what exists officially is
what is noticed and as we say, noted noteworthy.
Make a note of it in your mind in your date book.
Noting and noticing notation. You see,
they're all based on the same idea, what we
attend to. But there are a lot of very
attention worthy things that we ignore.
But part of the whole game, you see, of a cosmos is played
in this way. Imagine the cosmos as a great
harp. You know, the angels are
supposed to play harps in heaven. Now the
actual harp, they Play is the total possibility
of vibrations. Now you know about
the spectrum of light, that is a series of vibrations,
so is the spectrum of sound. Then beyond light,
there are other vibrations which are not picked up by our
senses, but instruments pick them up.
And then there must also be many vibrations as yet not
picked up by any instruments that we have.
Now, what is, you see, what we call nature is
a system of picked up vibrations.
Some vibrations aren't picked up and therefore nothing appears.
That's why it seems that the space around things, because the vibrations there
aren't picked up, they're not noticed.
And this is why there is a whole domain of Hindu and Buddhist philosophy
called tantra. Tantra refers to the idea
of weaving. And so when you have a warp
and a woof,
the weaver decides what threads are going to be picked up
and appear on the front, which is what everybody's going to look at. And what
threads will be overlooked, repressed, put behind the
scenes they'll be behind. And so it will appear
that we have a birdie here and a birdie there and a birdie there,
and no connection between the birdies. Actually, if you look on the other side,
you will see that the red threads which made the birdies against the white background
continues only that's not noticed.
So in this way, we are taught from childhood.
We are indoctrinated in a system of social institutions that
are simply rules about what is to be noticed
and what is not to be noticed. That's why children are sometimes
very odd questions about things that adults don't notice.
The famous story of the the little boy who's been taken
to a concert where a lady is singing and
he says, mama, why does she scream when she yawns so?
And in the same way, inventive poets
put together images that people never thought of before.
It's like Yeats's famous phrase, the be loud
glade, you know, it is a beautiful idea for
a nice glade to be beloud.
And everybody says, wow, think of that. We never thought of that before. We never
thought of it in just that way. We didn't know notice that.
Then, you see, we don't notice the
most obvious thing of all. That's of course, the last
thing that we would notice. What is most obvious and
the question, the fundamental koan, as it would be called in Zen,
is what is it you haven't noticed?
You've been listening to Alan Watts in another offering from the Being in
the Way podcast. I hope you'll Visit us@AlanWatts.org
and there you'll find a great selection of recordings, including previews
from our new streaming channel, along with biographic materials and
links to these podcasts in video form.
This program has been produced in conjunction with the Ram Dass Be
Here now podcast network, and our theme music is by
Zakir Hussain, courtesy of Moment Records.
For more offerings by Moment, please visit MomentRecords.com
this is Mark Watts. Thank you for listening.