Supposing the water at each place where a finger of
water stretches out over dry ground and doesn't go any further
because the land is too high. The water were to say
to itself, I failed. We would say it was neurotic water.
Just wait and it will find a way.
Now, when you find you see that there's this predicament
that I've been describing to you,
that there's no way of transforming yourself to
become this fearless, joyous,
divine being as distinct from the quaking mass.
When you say no way,
this is not a
gloomy announcement.
It is a very, very important communication telling
something.
Because the. Like the land is telling the water. This isn't the
way to go.
There's another way. Cry over here. So in the
same way, life is telling you that's not the way to go,
it's telling you the.
The message underlying this is you cannot transform yourself,
is giving you the message that
the you that you imagine to be capable of
transforming yourself doesn't exist.
In other words, an ego and
I separate
from my emotions, my thoughts, my feelings, my experiences.
Who is supposed to be in control of. Cannot control
them because it isn't there.
And as soon as you understand that, things will be
vastly improved.
Now we can go into this. What do you mean
by the word I?
We're going to make some experiments in this on some number
of different levels, but the ordinary way. What do you mean by the word I?
I myself. Your personality,
your ego. What is it?
Well, first of all, obviously, it's your image of yourself.
It's composed of what people have told you about yourself,
who you are, how they've reacted to you and given you an impression that
that's the sort of person you are.
It's all your education goes into this, the style
of life you put on and so forth.
But it's an image, it's an idea, it's your thought about
yourself. And I suppose yourself is in
fact not this, but is to
begin with your total physical organism,
your psychological organism.
And beyond that,
an organism doesn't exist as an
isolated thing any more than a flower exists without
a stalk, without roots, without earth.
So in the same way, although we are not stalked on the ground,
we are nevertheless inseparable from
a huge social context of.
Well, to begin with, parents,
siblings, people who work for us, everything. I mean, it's.
It's just impossible to cut ourselves off from a
social environment and also furthermore, from a
natural environment. We are that.
There's no clear way of drawing the boundary between this organism
and everything that surrounds it. And yet the image of ourselves
that we have does not include all
those relationships.
The point, though, is,
with all this, the first thing we have to understand is
what I will call deep listening.
And very few people ever really listen because
instead of receiving the sound, they make comments on it
all the time they're thinking about it.
And so the sound is never fully heard.
You just have to let it take over, let it take you over
completely.
Then you get the samadhi state of becoming it.
And it
also means that you abandon
your socially nervous personality.
Well, one of the reasons why people don't sing
is that they hear so many masters on records and
they're ashamed of their own voices and
think, there's no point singing unless I'm good at it.
Well, that's like saying there's no point my doing anything at all unless
I'm particularly gifted at it, which is ridiculous.
But singing is
of course, very good for you. But we won't mention that
as it brings in too much purposiveness into it.
It's like a child will make
noises because of the absorbing interest of making noises.
It embarrasses the hell out of some people.
You say, what are you laughing at?
Sa.
Give me some of that. Give me some of that.
The title of these talks that I'm giving here is Mind Over
Mind.
And I'm going into all
the various problems which have to do with
the control of the mind.
So it all comes down to this basic question that
human beings have
for a long, long time been concerned about transforming
their minds.
Is there any way in which one's mind can be transformed?
Or is it simply a process which is nothing more than a vicious circle?
I could ask, why have you come here this afternoon?
What were you looking for? Would it
be too presumptuous of me to say that you were
looking for help? That you
hoped you would hear somebody who had something to say
that would be of help and relevance to
you as members of a
world which is running into the most intense difficulty.
And one naturally says the reason
why we are in such a mess is not simply
that we have wrong systems for doing things,
but we have the wrong people.
The systems may be all right, but they are in the wrong
hands. Because we are all,
in various ways, self seeking, lacking in
wisdom, lacking in courage,
afraid of death, afraid of pain,
unwilling really to cooperate with others,
unwilling to be open to others. And we all think that's
too bad. If only I could be the right person.
I would like to improve so in so many people's
minds and from so many different angles,
there is this urgent feeling that I must
improve me.
Now in this question, can I
improve me? There is the obvious
difficulty that if I am in need of improvement,
the person who's going to do the improving is the
one who needs to be improved. And there
immediately we have a vicious circle.
And so I might introduce what I'm going to say
by saying it from different points of view.
For example, if you're interested in communications,
it will be the problem of feedback.
Or if I may put it in theological terms,
how does man follow the will of God? If the
will of man is perverse,
how then do you get grace?
Why is grace given to some and not to others?
If I cannot follow the will of God by my own effort,
because my will is selfish, how will my
will which is selfish be transformed into
an unselfish will? If I cannot do it,
then grace must do it. If grace
has not already done it, why not?
Because I didn't accept it.
But by definition I had no power to accept it because my will
was selfish. Must I then become a Calvinist
and say that only those people who
are predestined to receive grace will be able to
live the good life?
Then we come back to
the inadmissible position that
people who live evil lives and do not get grace
because they are not predestined to it out of the infinite wisdom
of the Godhead, then God himself must be held responsible for their evil
deeds.
People fall from grace.
Why do they? You see, we're just talking about the same old problem,
but we've put it a step up. But it's the same problem.
How can I improve myself?
Was the first problem. The second problem is how can I accept grace?
They're both the same problem, because you've got to make a move
which will put yourself out of your own control into the
control of a better. If you
don't believe in the Christian kind of a God, you can believe in the Hindu
kind of a God, who is your inner self.
You see, you've got a lower self, which you can call your ego.
That's that little scoundrel fellow that's always out
for me. But behind the ego there is the Atman,
the inner self, the inward light, as Quakers would call
it, the real self, the spirit, which is substantially
identical with God. So you've
got to meditate in such a way that you identify with your
higher self. How do you do that? Well, you start by watching all
your thoughts very carefully.
Watching your feelings, watching your emotions,
so that you begin to build up a sense of separation between
the watcher and what is watched,
so that you are, as it were, no longer carried away by your own stream
of consciousness. You remain the witness, impassively,
impartially suspending judgment and
watching it all go on.
Who is this self behind the self? The watching
self? Can you watch that one?
It's interesting if you do,
because you find out, of course, that this is just as
the problem of grace is
nothing more than a transposition of the first problem. How am
I to be unselfish? By my own power.
It becomes, how am I to get grace? By my own power?
So in the same way we find that the watching self,
or the observing self behind all our thoughts and feelings, is itself
a thought. If I desire not
to desire, is that not already desire?
How can I desire not to desire?
How can I surrender myself when
myself is precisely an urge
to hold on, to cling, to cling to
life, to continue to survive? I can see
rationally that by clinging to myself I may
strangle myself.
How can I outwit me?
How can I one up me?
You see, the reason you want to be better is the reason why you aren't.
Shall I put it like we
aren't better because we want to be.
If you say you want to improve,
then you ought to know what's good for you, but obviously
you don't, because if you did, you would be improved.
So we don't know Sa
all stars are free.
We are aboard the ferry boat Vallejo,
which is tied up at the north end of Sausalito, close to San.
And this is where I live. And you may think this
place is rather weird, but that's because I've
always loved weird things. I remember when I was a
little boy, people used to say to me, alan, you're so weird.
Why can't you be like other people? Well,
I thought that was just plain dull, like having the same thing for
dinner every day. And as is well said, variety is
the spice of life.
And when I think over the weirdest of all things I
can think of, you know what it is?
Nothing. Tagung. The great
emptiness. The whole
idea of nothing is
something that has bugged people for centuries,
especially in the west, because we have a
saying in Latin, ex nihilo, nihil fit, which means
that out of nothing comes nothing.
You can't, in other words, get something out of nothing.
And it's occurred to me that this is a fallacy
of tremendous proportions that lies at the root
of all our common sense. Not only in the west,
but in many parts of the east as well. And it comes up as
a kind of terror of nothing. A put down on nothing,
on everything to do with nothing. Everything associated with nothing.
Such as sleep, passivity,
rest.
What has struck me is that nothing,
the negative, the empty.
Is exceedingly powerful.
Nothing is more fertile than emptiness.
I would say, not ex nihilo nihil fit. Out of
nothing comes nothing. But I would say you can't have something without
nothing. So how do we
basically begin to think about the difference between
something and nothing? I can say there is a cigar in
my right hand. And there is no cigar in my left hand.
And so we get the idea of is here and isn't.
Or empty here. But behind that,
of course. Lies the far more obvious contrast of
solid and space.
Now, we tend to think of space as nothing.
When we talk about the conquest of space.
There's a little element. Notice of hostility in that phrase.
But actually, we're talking about the conquest of distance,
space as such. That is to say, whatever it is that lies
between the Earth and the Moon. And the Earth and the Sun.
Is considered to be just nothing at all.
But to suggest how very powerful and important this
nothing at all is. Let me point out to you.
That if you didn't have space. You couldn't have anything
solid to begin with.
Without space outside the solid. You wouldn't know where the solid's edges
were. For example, you can see me on the camera.
Because you see a background here and
all around me. And that background shows up my outline.
It's, for example, difficult to see a hand unless
there is a contrasting background. Were there no background
of the hand, the hand itself would vanish.
Nothing is more fertile than emptiness.
But you always have to have a background to see a figure.
You just can't do without it. To have the whole
idea of there being only space and nothing else at
all. Is not only inconceivable. But perfectly meaningless.
Because we always know what we mean by contrasts.
We know what we mean by white in comparison with
black. They must come into being together.
Because of the inseparability of these opposites. They always go
together. This, as it were, hints at some kind of unity
which underlies them. You don't have first something,
then nothing. Or first nothing, and then something. This unity
is called Tao. Space and form,
in that sense go together. As the fundamental things we're dealing with in
this universe. That which is void precisely
form. And that which is form is precisely
void.
Now it's amazing what doesn't exist in the
real world.
In the real world, there aren't any things,
nor are there any events. That doesn't mean to
say that the real world is a perfectly featureless
blank. It means that
it is a marvelous system of wiggles.
You cannot have the ups without
the downs. Now, the same thing is true of all
life together. We shouldn't really contrast
existence with non existence. The unconscious
is, so to say, the part of experience which is doing
consciousness. Just as the trough manifests
the wave, the space manifests
the solid, the background manifests
the figure. So it's interconnected.
And so the many, many patterns of interconnections.
Lock it all together into a unity. Which is, however,
much too complicated for us to think about. Except in very,
very simple, crude ways.
But I am part of this.
And so all that side of life which you call unconscious,
unknown, impenetrable. Is unconscious
and is unknown. And is impenetrable because it's
really you.
Nothing is what brings something
into focus. Nothing. And this nothingness,
symbolized by the Krishna.
Is your own eyeball, your own consciousness.
And the clear space in
which all the stars have breathing to be seen.
Every living body is something like the flame of a candle.
This living thing that you're feeling like
the gyroscope top. It's your own life.
Because you can see, very simply, that you would not
understand the experience that you call voluntary
action and decision. Being in control and
being yourself. Unless, in opposition to
that, there was something else you
couldn't realize self and control and will.
Unless there was something other out
of control. And instead of will, won't.
It's the two together only. That produces the
sensation. That you call having a personal identity only.
There is a funny thing about human consciousness. Which has been worked out
very carefully in gestalt psychology. Which is that our
attention is captured by the figure rather than the background.
By the relatively enclosed area rather than the diffuse
area. And by something moving rather than what is
relatively still. And to all those phenomena
that in this way attract our attention. We attribute a
higher degree of reality than the ones we
don't notice. That's only because,
for the moment, those are more important to us. Consciousness,
you see, is a radar that
is scanning the environment to look out for trouble.
Just in the same way as a ship's radar is looking for rocks
or other ships. And the radar, therefore,
does not notice the vast areas of
space. Where there are no rocks, no other ships.
So in the same way, our eyes, or rather
the selective Consciousness behind the eyes only pays attention
to what we think is important. And so in this way,
we have this rather myopic way of looking at things.
And we screen out from attention
anything that is
not immediately important. To a scanning system
based on sensing danger.
But quite obviously, you, as a complete individual.
Are much more than the scanning system.
You are in relationships with the external world.
That, on the whole, are incredibly harmonious.
Going back to this illustration of every living body. Is something
like the flame of a candle.
The energies of life in the form of temperature,
light, air and food and so on.
Are streaming through you all at this moment. In the most magnificently
harmonious way. And you're,
all of you, far more beautiful than any candle flame.
Just sitting in these chairs, just going,
no.
Only we are so used to it. We say about that,
so what? Show me something interesting.
Show me something new. Because it's a
characteristic of consciousness. That it ignores stimuli
that are constant.
When anything is constant. It says, okay, that's safe. It's in the bag.
Needn't pay attention to that anymore.
And therefore, we eliminate systematically from our
awareness. All the gorgeous things that are going on all
the time. And instead only become focused on the
things. The troublesome things that might happen to upset it.
Which is all right. But we make too much of it
and become. We make so much of it that
we identify our very selves. I ego with
the radar, with the troubleshooter.
And that's only a tiny fragment of one's total being.
So that if you do become aware.
That you are not simply that scanning
mechanism. But you are your complete organism. Then very
swiftly in turn, as a consequence of that. You become
aware that your organism is
not the way you think about it. When you look at it from
the standpoint of conscious attention. From the standpoint of the ego.
From the standpoint of the ego. Your organism is
your kind of vehicle. Your automobile in which you go
around.
But from a physical point of view.
Your organism is again, like the candle
flame or the whirlpool. It is something which is a continuous
patterning or activity of the whole cosmos.
The key idea here is pattern.
Let's suppose. I'm going to borrow a metaphor from Buckminster Fuller.
Suppose we have a rope.
And one section of this rope is made of manila hemp.
The next section is cotton. The next section is silk.
The next section is nylon, and so on.
Now, we tie a knot in this rope.
Just an ordinary one over knot. You find by putting
your finger in the knot. You can move it all the way down. The rope.
Now, as this knot travels, it's first of all made
of manila hemp. It's then made of cotton. It's then made of silk.
It's then made of nylon and so on. But the knot keeps
going on. That's the integrity
of pattern, the continuing pattern, which is what you are.
Because you might, you know, be for several years. You might be a vegetarian,
and you might be a meat eater and so on. And, you know, your constitution
changes all the time. But people, your friends, still recognize you because
you're still putting on the same show. It's the same pattern that
is the recognizable individual.
But we are trained in our language. The very structure
of the language we talk deceives us into misunderstanding
this. Because when we see a pattern,
we ask, what's it made of?
Like, you see a table, is it made of wood, or is it made of
aluminum? But then when you inquire into
what is wood and how does wood differ from aluminum?
The only thing a scientist can tell you is the different patterns, that is
to say, the different molecular structure of the two things.
And a molecular structure is not a description of
what something is made of. It is a description of what dance it is performing,
what motions, what kind of a symphony. This is because
basically all phenomena of life are musical.
And gold differs from lead in exactly the
same way that a waltz differs from a mazurka.
It's a different dance, and there isn't
anything that's dancing. That is a deception
we get into because we have two parts of speech in our grammar. We have
nouns and verbs. And verbs are
supposed to describe the activities of nouns.
And this is simply a convention of speech. You could have a language
with only verbs in it. You don't need any nouns. Or you could also have
a language with nouns only and no verbs.
And it would perfectly adequately describe what's
going on in the world.
So if you were used to speaking with a language that had one
part of speech, you could say just as much as we can with two
and be a lot clearer. Only at first it would
sound awkward, but you'd soon get used to it. And then when you got
used to it, it would be a matter of common sense that the patterning
of the world is not some kind of stuff that's patterning.
You don't have to seek for a substance underlying the whole thing. It's just patterning.
And we're all that.
Now. We come here right at the start to an extremely important
principle, which is the
different points of view you get when you Change your level of magnification.
That is to say, you can look at something with a microscope and see it
a certain way. You can look at it with the naked eye and see it
in a certain way. You look at it with a telescope, and you see it
in another way. Now, which level of magnification
is the correct one? Well, obviously they're
all correct. They're just different points of view.
You can, for example, look at a newspaper photograph
under a magnifying glass. And where with the naked
eye, you will see a human face with a magnifying glass, you will see a
profusion of dots rather meaninglessly scattered.
But as you stand away from that connection of dots.
Which all seem to be separate and apart from each other,
they suddenly arrange themselves into a pattern.
And you see that these individual dots add
up to some kind of sense.
Now, you'll see at once from this illustration that maybe
you, when you
take a myopic view of yourself, as most of us do,
but you may add up to some kind of sense that is
not apparent to you in your ordinary consciousness.
Well, it is claimed, you see, that some human beings have broken through
to that vision. That they slipped
somehow or other into states of consciousness
where they see the apparent disintegration
and disorganization of
everyday life as the
functioning of a totality which
at its level is completely harmonious.
And you could say, aha, at last I see. I got the
point. I've seen how all this makes sense.
That's what it is. That's what we notice.
But what this insight depended upon was
your overcoming the
illusion that space separates
things.
We tend to see the universe itself really consisting
in all the stars and galaxies.
But the space in which all this happens is sort of written
off as something that isn't really there.
But what one has to realize is that the space is
an essential function of the things in the space.
After all, you can't have separate stars
unless there is a space around.
Eliminate the space, and you will see you couldn't have this phenomenon at all.
And vice versa, you couldn't
have the space. They wouldn't be there in any sense whatsoever
if there weren't the bodies in it. So the bodies in
the space and the space are two aspects of a single
continuum. They're related together in exactly
the same way as a back and a front.
And you just don't get one without the other.
So the moment you see that intervals, that space is connective,
you can understand at once how
you are not just
to be exclusively defined as
A flash of consciousness that occurs between two eternal
darknesses.
And what you call yourself as a living organism.
Say I am my whole body at the very least.
Now, what is that body? That body is recognizable.
And I recognize my friends when I meet them again. Good luck.
And you recognize me. Although the last time any
of you saw me, I was absolutely something entirely
different from what I am now. Just as
the flame of a candle is never a constant,
the flame of a candle is a stream of hot gas.
Only you say the flame of the candle as if it were a constant.
Well, it is a recognizably constant pattern.
The spear shaped outline of the flame and its coloration is
a constant pattern. But in exactly the same way we
are all constant patterns. And that's all we are. The only
thing constant about us at all is the doing rather than the
being. It's the way we behave, the. The way we dance.
Only there's no we that dances. There's just the dancing.
Just as the flame is the streaming of hot gas.
Just as a whirlpool in a river is a whirling of streaming
water. There is no
thing that whirlpools.
There is the whirlpool. And in the same way, each one of us is
a very, very delightfully complex undulation of
the energy of the whole universe.
Only by our process of miseducation,
we've been deprived of the knowledge of that
fact. Not as if there was someone to blame for this.
Because it's always with our own tacit consent.
Because life is basically a game of
hide and seek.
Because life is pulsation.
On and off. Here it is, and now it isn't.
All life, you see, is this flickering in and out.
And by being this pulsation,
we know it's there.
See, you don't know what you mean
by on unless you know what you mean by off.
In the darkness that comes before your birth,
there was no you. And in the eternal
darkness that follows your death, there is likewise
no you.
Sa.
What do I desire?
Well, when we answer that question in a naive way,
we figure out that we want a desire.
What we want is to control everything.
To create girls that don't grow old,
apples that don't rotate, clothes that never wear out,
conveyances that get from one place to another instantly. So we don't
have to wait power available to do anything that you
could conceive and do it just instantly like that.
To get this funny technological omnipotence.
But if you take time out to think about that
and really go into it with your full strength of imagination
and find out whether that's where you want to be.
You will soon see that's not what you want.
Because the moment you have a situation where
you are really in control of things, that is to say, in which the future
is almost completely predictable,
you will see, as I said last night, that a completely predictable
future is already the past. You've had it.
That's not what you wanted. You want a surprise.
You don't know what that's going to be because obviously it wouldn't be a surprise
if you did. You want a pleasant surprise,
but like you say, what sort of a surprise would be pleasant?
And you can't really answer that because you know,
if there are to be such things as pleasant surprises, there must also be unpleasant
surprises. There must be rude shots.
So you're like somebody taking one
of those wishing well boxes, you know, tubs, you know, where you
fish in and you bring out a package and you don't know whether you've
got a dead rat in it or a new camera.
And that's the way that's. That seems to be the thing that really excites
people.
But quite certainly there comes out of this inquiry a
feeling of real disillusionment
with the ideal of power.
To be in power, to be in control is
not something that any sensible person wants.
Imagine the situation of big brother,
Mr. J. Edgar Hoover,
Heinrich Himmler,
to be glued day and night to
a highly defended office with
telephone, television screens,
watching, peeking, spying on everyone and anything,
getting all this information together. Why you could never leave the office.
I mean, the people character, I suppose, like say, Edgar Hoover goes home in the
evening and. But when he's back
home, you know, there are guards sitting outside the door.
There's that hotline telephone going to some. Something.
He's always having to be in control and
he can't take any time off. He can't go for a
walk in the park with a friend or go innocently to
the movies or sit down and just
relax and have an undistracted party in the baths at Big Sur
here. What a pauper. This guy is completely deprived
because he wants to be in control, because he wants power.
People are frustrated in love. Be if you're
jilted. There's a natural tendency in a human being to seek
power as a substitute, and that's a very
negative thing. It's like having a bad temper to
seek power after you're frustrated in love. You should try and get back on the
love beam because nobody Wants
power. Now, you may
say that shirking responsibility, that if
you were a really responsible person, you would go out for power and
try to use power to the best possible advantage for
the benefit of all. All right,
what would be the benefit of all?
Ask them, what do you want me to do with this
power? I'm dictator. What would you like me to do?
Well, nobody knows because they haven't thought it through. They think
of all sorts of short range things and they are largely conflicting
and confusing because they're not well thought out. But again,
when it finally comes down to it, nobody wants to be God.
Now then, when Oriental philosophy and
religion was first introduced the Western world,
it was introduced under the auspices of people who were fascinated
with power.
It was introduced in the latter part of the 19th century when we
had heard all about evolution and how the human race was going on
to ever greater heights. And we would eventually develop Superman
according to Nietzsche or D.B. shaw and
H.G. wells. Remember all that early fantasy
of where evolution would lead through the development
of technology. And so at this time,
people like HP Blavatsky were talking about the
mysterious wisdom of the east, and they phrased
it, they commended it to us in a technological spirit,
that there was psychic technology, that there
was something that you could go way beyond anything that could be done through the
physical sciences.
You could cause your physical body to
disintegrate to another
level of vibration and then transmit it and reassemble it somewhere else.
You could live as long as you like because you control the fundamental processes.
You could determine if you decided to die where you would be reborn.
Exactly. You would be a complete master
of life. And so there are still innumerable books
being sold which present oriental philosophy and religion
in this light. That charlatan Lobsang
Ramper, who writes about
Tibetan mastery, people read that
because they. They think that there may be a way
of beating the game.
So therefore, the wise men of Asia were represented
through this kind of propaganda
as masters of life. As, for example, people whose
emotions didn't bother them, who could put
up with any amount of pain by simply turning off their feelings,
who could foretell the future,
who could read your thoughts,
and who were above all kinds of ordinary human
frailty.
Well, when I first met Buddhist
priests, Zen masters,
swamis, all these wise men from the east,
one of the first things that impressed itself upon me was that they were perfectly
ordinary human beings.
They had bad tempers, they were fussy
about certain things. They just acted
as I would expect human beings to act. And so at first I was very
disappointed. I thought they had feet of clay,
that they didn't come up to these promises of psycho technology.
But after a while I got to realize why. Not that they had already thought
all that through. They had thought through what
might be done if one had all these powers. And it decided
that wasn't what they wanted. The powers
of this kind in Sanskrit are called siddhi S I
D D H I.
But there is hardly one decent scripture or text on
yoga that does not say again and again, if you get siddhi,
ignore them, go on
to something else. These are only the foothills. These are
furthermore, not only foothills, but. But they are seductive.
Blind alleys won't
take you anywhere at all.
Now, I think that this is the greatest possible
lesson for the Western world to learn, because we are
so hung up on the idea of power, of control,
of being able to make everything go the right way. And if
we've never thought it through, when you get control of it, what are you going
to do with it?
The self is
the basis of all being.
And being is not something into which we come,
but out of which we proceed.
In popular language, we say, I came into this world as
if you came from somewhere else altogether, from outside.
But you don't. You come out of this world just
in the same way as the leaves come from the tree.
And so in that way you are an expression of it.
And the self meaning itself,
self meaning,
identity, self meaning,
basis, ground is
what everybody fundamentally is.
Then I went on to discuss the world as
the self, in the sense of the cosmos as
the self. The great cycles of time,
the world is manifested and then again withdrawn.
And now I want to go on to discuss the
human world as the self.
Well, now there
have in the known history of mankind been
about three types of
culture. We'll call them hunting cultures,
agrarian cultures,
and industrial cultures.
The hunting culture seems to have been the earliest.
And agrarian
cultures arose when hunters learned to
farm and therefore had to settle
in certain places. And it
was then that men built cities.
And when we pass from the
hunting to the agrarian culture, we notice two
very important changes occur in
the hunting culture. Every man is
expert in the whole culture.
That's because he spends a good deal of time alone in
the forests or on the hills.
And so he has to know how to make clothes,
how to cook, how to build,
how to fight,
ride, and all those things.
But as soon as people become settled
in cities, we get a division of labor,
because it's obviously more practical when you're all living together for some
People to specialize in some things and some in others.
Now then, reasonably enough, the first communities
are stockaded enclosures. They are made
of palings. And so we speak of people being
within the pale and beyond the pale.
So here is a primitive stockaded community.
And as often as not, this community
will settle at a crossroads for
obvious reasons. Where roads cross, that's where people meet.
And so it's liable to have four
gates and these crossing main streets.
And that immediately establishes four divisions of the
city. In Hindu society, there are four castes
based on the four fundamental divisions of labor.
And number one is the caste of priests,
and they're called brahmana. Number two
is the caste of warriors and also rulers,
and they're called kshatriya.
Number three is the caste of merchants and tradesmen,
and they're called vaishya. And number four are
laborers and they are called shudra.
So those are the four principal
roles in
the world of settled humanity.
So now then, those are the roles.
Those are, you might say,
masks in this game called the social
game. Now then,
when you enter society, you are born into a caste.
And this is very understandable in a community where you
don't have a generalized system of education,
you don't go to school, and therefore
you learn what to do in life from your parents
and your family. So if
you grow up as a carpenter's son,
it never occurs to you to do anything else but carpentry.
Why would you?
You might become a better carpenter than your father.
But still that would be the natural thing to do.
It's only when one
is exposed to school, people begin
to talk about, well, what do you want to be in life?
That people get the idea that they might be anything.
You see, what happens is this, then, that an individual
who all his life long has played the social game is
then says, well, now I've done that.
I've assumed this role. I've become identified.
But now who am I really?
In order to find that out, I have to go off by myself.
Why? Because you
have a role conception, a mask conception
of yourself because other people tell you who you are.
We are constantly in every social interchange,
in the most common remarks, telling other people
who they are. Everybody around you
is telling you what you are and who you are by expecting
certain behavior from you, which, if you're a
reasonable and socially inclined person, you perform because that's
what's expected of you.
So you are told who you are. You have
a political and social analog of
the manifestation and withdrawal of
the worlds of the Lord playing
the game, or the self playing the game of being all of us.
And then the self realizes
in terms of an individual life, that it is the
self. And so you can have this
sensation, you see, of total unity with the
cosmos, of the expansion
to infinity or contraction to infinity,
without forgetting society's game rules with regard
to you. In other words, it doesn't mean that you forget your address,
telephone number, Social Security security number. You remember all that,
and you can play that game when necessary.
But you know it's a game sa.