Imagine for a moment that life itself is a dance and you are the dancer.
Now consider this. If you were to move with the confidence that each step,
each sway would take you exactly where you need to be,
wouldn't you dance with more grace, more joy, more ease?
In the same way, when you act as if everything always works out for you,
the entire rhythm of life shifts to support that belief.
You see, reality is not fixed or rigid. It bends.
It moves in response to the energy we bring to it.
When we walk through life, assuming that things are bound to fall apart, that obstacles
are inevitable, we invite just that.
But if we move forward with the quiet assurance that the universe is
on our side, that things will unfold in our favor,
suddenly life begins to reflect that very certainty
back to us. It's not about blind faith,
nor is it about pretending challenges do not exist.
It's about meeting those challenges with a mindset that transforms
them. By embracing the unknown, by stepping into
uncertainty, with a heart full of trust, you discover a
strange and wonderful thing. Life flows more freely.
Problems become opportunities. Setbacks become detours
that lead to places you didn't even realize you needed to go.
To act as if everything works out for you is not to deny reality,
but rather to reshape it. We must understand that our thoughts,
our beliefs, have a profound influence on the reality we experience.
Think of your mind as the sun casting light over the landscape of
your life. If you cast a shadow of doubt, fear and
uncertainty, the world will appear dim, harsh.
But if you radiate trust, positivity and calm, everything takes on
a different hue. One that invites growth, one that breeds possibilities.
And then there's the beauty of detachment. When you let
go of the need to control outcomes, when you stop clinging to how things should
be, you create space for how things could be.
In that space, life breathes. It moves
with a kind of wisdom that often surpasses our understanding.
The outcome may not be what you expected, but you trust that
it is what you need. Resilience naturally
follows this trust. Acting as if things always work
out does not mean you won't face challenges. But it means you'll
meet those challenges with an inner knowing that somehow they are part
of the process. Even the hardest moments contain
within them the seeds of transformation. With each
difficulty you learn, you adapt, you become stronger.
You begin to notice, too, how your energy attracts what surrounds
you. When you carry the belief that life supports you,
opportunities arise that match that belief. People are drawn to
your confidence not because you hold the answers, but because you trust the unfolding
of your own journey. The world opens to those
who move through it with a sense of inner faith.
And most importantly, this way of living roots you firmly in the present.
It removes the burden of constantly fretting over an unknown
future. You are here now, acting with the certainty
that whatever comes, you will meet it with grace. You'll find
the path. You'll grow.
In the end, the choice is yours. Will you live with fear,
clinging to every outcome? Or will you choose the freedom that
comes with trusting life's flow? Acting as if
everything always works out for you isn't about forcing life
into a box. It's about allowing it to bloom in ways you
never thought possible. Trust. Move and know
that in the grand dance of life, every step leads you exactly
where you need to be. The way we perceive the
world shapes the reality we experience. Our thoughts, beliefs and
attitudes serve as a lens through which we interpret every event,
interaction and moment in our lives.
If you expect obstacles, you will find them at every turn. But if you
expect things to flow smoothly, life tends to mirror that expectation.
Perception is a powerful force. It colors our interpretation
of what's happening around us. Consider two people experiencing the
same event. One sees a setback, while the other sees a stepping stone.
It's not the event itself that differs, but their perception of it.
This difference in how we view life can drastically alter the quality of
our experience. By shifting your mindset and acting as though
things are always working out for you, you change the way you interact with
the world. Opportunities begin to appear where there one
seem to be. Dead ends and challenges become avenues for
growth. Life responds to the energy you bring
into it. When you view the world through a lens of possibility,
it reflects the possibility back to you.
It's not magic. It's the way the mind filters information and focuses
on what aligns with your internal beliefs.
If you believe that good things are meant for you, you will
start to notice them. Whereas if you believe the opposite,
your mind will filter the world in a way that confirms your doubts and
fears. The more you embrace the idea that everything works
out, the more you begin to live in harmony with that idea.
This shift in perception opens you up to new experiences and
deeper insights and a broader perspective on life's events.
By reshaping how you view your circumstances, you step into a
reality that aligns with your more optimistic outlook.
You begin to experience life not as something happening to you, but as
something co created with your own awareness and energy. This realization
is liberating. It gives you the ability to shift
your world from the Inside out, knowing that your perception,
more than external factors, defines your reality.
Uncertainty is a natural part of life, yet so often we resist it,
craving stability and control over the unfolding of events.
But the truth is, life is an unpredictable flow,
and no matter how much we try to plan or anticipate,
the future remains unknown. In embracing uncertainty,
we shift our mindset from fear to openness. We stop seeing the
unknown as a threat and start viewing it as a space of possibility.
When you act as if everything works out for you, you no longer
cling to rigid expectations about how things should unfold.
Instead, you allow life to surprise you. This doesn't mean abandoning
all plans or goals, but rather recognizing that the path to
those goals may not always be clear or linear. Often,
the greatest gifts come in ways we never anticipated. The detours
and unexpected turns are part of life's richness. And when we
open ourselves to uncertainty, we allow space for these
gifts to enter. There is a kind of freedom
in not knowing what comes next. It relieves the pressure of having
to control every aspect of our lives. When we embrace uncertainty,
we learn to trust the process. We move with the current
of life rather than against it, flowing through challenges and opportunities alike
with grace. This mindset helps us remain flexible,
adaptable, and more resilient in the face of change.
Life, in its wisdom, often leads us to exactly where we need
to be, even if we can't see the path clearly from where we stand.
By stepping into the unknown with the belief that everything will work out,
we are not ignoring the risks or challenges. We are simply trusting that
whatever comes, we will find our way through.
We stop wasting energy on trying to predict or control outcomes,
and instead focus on responding to life with presence and courage.
In the end, it's about accepting that we don't need to have all the answers.
The unknown becomes a playground for growth, creativity, and new experiences.
When you act as if life is unfolding in your favor, even uncertainty becomes
less daunting. It becomes a partner in your journey,
rather than an obstacle to be feared.
Thoughts and intentions are like seeds planted in the soil of our minds.
What we think and intend sets the stage for what unfolds in our
lives. When you act as if everything works out for you,
your thoughts align with that belief and your actions follow.
This isn't just positive thinking. It's a deeper understanding of how your internal
world shapes your external reality. Every action you take
stems from the thoughts and intentions you hold. When those thoughts are rooted in
confidence and trust, your entire approach to life shifts.
Your mind is Constantly interpreting the world and
the thoughts you dwell on create the filters through which you see everything.
If your thoughts are clouded by fear, doubt, or negativity, you will
likely interpret life's events in a way that confirms those feelings.
However, when your thoughts are grounded in the belief that life supports you,
that things are always working out in your favor, you begin
to see possibilities where others might see obstacles.
It's not that the external world changes, but your perception of it
does. Intentions act like a compass,
guiding your actions toward your desired outcomes. When your
intentions are clear and aligned with positivity, they direct your
energy in a focused way. Imagine starting your day with the intention
that everything will work out no matter what challenges arise.
This doesn't mean difficulties disappear, but rather that you approach
them with a mindset of trust and adaptability.
Your intentions shape how you respond, and how you respond shapes
your experience. The power of thought and intention also
extends to how we influence the energy around us. Thoughts carry
energy, and when you focus on the belief that life supports you,
that energy radiates outward. It influences not
only your mood and behavior, but also how others interact
with you. People are drawn to those who exude
calm, confidence and positivity. The energy you
project attracts experiences that resonate with it. It's as
though life mirrors back the vibration you send out.
Moreover, the act of setting intentions shifts your focus from
passivity to active creation. Rather than waiting for
life to happen to you, you become a participant in shaping your own reality.
You begin to see that life is not something to be feared or controlled,
but something to be engaged with mindfully and purposefully.
When your thoughts and intentions are aligned with trust,
your actions naturally lead you to outcomes that reflect that inner
state. Ultimately, the power of thought and
intention reminds us that our reality begins in the mind.
The more consciously we cultivate thoughts of abundance, trust, and peace,
the more our actions reflect those qualities, creating a reality
that mirrors back our deepest intentions.
Detachment from outcomes is not about apathy or indifference.
It's about freeing yourself from the need to control every detail of how
life unfolds. When you act as if everything
works out for you, you release the pressure of constantly striving for a
specific outcome and instead trust the flow of life.
This doesn't mean you lack ambition or don't set goals. It means you
stop clinging to the idea that your happiness or success depends on things
turning out exactly as you planned.
Attachment to outcomes creates tension.
When we are fixated on a particular result, we often close ourselves off
to other possibilities that may be even better suited for us, by becoming
too focused on a narrow idea of success, we miss the broader
picture of what life is offering. Detachment allows us
to stay open, to recognize that there are countless ways for things to
work out, many of which we may not have envisioned.
The paradox of detachment is that by letting go of the need for
things to unfold in a specific way, we actually invite more
favorable outcomes. When you're overly attached to a certain result,
you become rigid in your approach. And that rigidity can
block the natural flow of opportunities.
By embracing detachment, you create space for unexpected
solutions, for life to surprise you with paths you hadn't
considered. This openness invites a more fluid,
adaptable way of being.
Letting go of attachment to outcomes also brings a sense of peace.
So much of our stress comes from trying to control what is ultimately beyond
our control. When you detach from the outcome, you place your
trust in the process. You act with intention,
but you are not attached to the idea that only one specific
result will bring you happiness or fulfillment. You recognize that
the journey itself holds value and that whatever happens
along the way is part of your growth.
This mindset encourages resilience.
When things don't go as planned, you don't see it as failure,
but as part of a larger process that's unfolding.
You adapt, adjust, and move forward without feeling crushed
by disappointment. Detachment gives you
the flexibility to shift and flow with life's changes, knowing that
no single outcome defines your worth or your success.
In letting go of the need for control, you embrace trust.
You trust that whatever happens, it is working out in your favor,
even if it doesn't appear so in the moment. This faith allows
you to act without the burden of constant anxiety over whether you'll achieve
a specific result. Instead, you can engage fully
in the present moment, confident that life is unfolding as it should.
Resilience is born from faith, a deep rooted trust
that no matter what happens, you have the strength and capacity to endure
and grow. When you act as if everything works
out for you, you cultivate this inner resilience, knowing that
challenges are not the end of the story, but simply part of a larger journey.
Faith doesn't mean blind optimism or ignoring difficulties.
It means holding onto the belief that even when things seem uncertain or
tough, there is a greater unfolding at play and you will
find your way through. Faith acts as a steady foundation
when the winds of life grow turbulent. It's an inner assurance that
while you can't always predict what will happen, you can trust in your ability to
navigate whatever comes your way. When you approach
life with the mindset that things will work out, you become more
flexible in the face of adversity. Obstacles don't feel
like roadblocks. They become opportunities to adjust,
adapt, and grow stronger. Resilience emerges
because you don't view setbacks as permanent failures, but as temporary
detours that may lead to unexpected growth or new directions.
This kind of faith fosters a calmness that carries you through difficult times.
It's not about denying hardship, but rather about acknowledging that
even in hardship, there's a way forward. When you believe that
life supports you, you're less likely to be overwhelmed by temporary setbacks.
You know that you have the strength to overcome them,
and that with time, things will realign in ways that may be
even more beneficial than you initially imagined.
Moreover, faith empowers resilience by helping you maintain perspective.
Life is full of ups and downs, but when you hold onto the belief that
things will ultimately work out, you don't get stuck in the lows.
You understand that whatever challenge you're facing is part of a larger
picture, and you trust that the difficulties you encounter
are only temporary. This belief allows you to keep
moving forward with hope, even in the face of uncertainty or
difficulty. Resilience through faith also
means that you trust in your own ability to grow from hardship.
It's not just about getting through difficult times, but about emerging from them with
greater strength and wisdom. Every challenge becomes a
chance to deepen your understanding of yourself, to refine your approach to life,
and to cultivate more inner strength. In this way, faith in
yourself and in the process of life transforms obstacles into stepping stones for
greater resilience. Ultimately,
when you act as if everything works out, you reinforce a cycle
of resilience. Each time you face a challenge and come through it,
your faith in yourself and in life grows stronger.
This faith becomes the bedrock that allows you to keep going,
knowing that no matter what happens, you have the inner resources to weather
any storm and come out on the other side.
Positive energy has a natural magnetism drawing toward
you. The experiences, people, and opportunities that align with
the frequency you project. When you act as if everything works
out for you, you emit an energy that is calm, confident, and open
to possibilities. This energy doesn't just affect
your inner state, it ripples outward, influencing your environment
and how others perceive and respond to you.
The mindset of believing that life supports you not only changes
how you navigate the world, but also attracts situations that
reflect that belief. This magnetism is rooted
in the principle that like attracts like. When you carry
a sense of optimism and trust Your actions, words, and even your presence
radiate that energy. People are naturally drawn to
individuals who exude positivity, not just because it feels
good to be around them, but because they represent possibility.
Positive energy is infectious. It lifts the mood of
those around you, creates a sense of ease, and encourages others to open up,
collaborate, and engage with you. On a deeper level,
opportunities also tend to align with the energy you project.
When you move through life with the expectation that things will work
out, you're more likely to spot opportunities that others may overlook.
It's not that the opportunities weren't there before, but your mindset, one of
openness and receptivity, allows you to recognize them more easily.
Easily. This heightened awareness,
combined with your positive energy, makes you a magnet for success,
drawing circumstances that align with your inner confidence
and trust in life. Moreover,
positive energy helps to foster resilience in the face of challenges.
When difficulties arise, as they inevitably do,
your positive outlook allows you to navigate them with a sense of calm and purpose.
Instead of being weighed down by negativity or fear, you approach
problems with the belief that they can be overcome, and this belief shapes
your response. It makes you more resourceful, creative and determined,
which in turn attracts solutions.
Positive energy also influences the relationships you cultivate.
People are drawn to individuals who seem grounded, optimistic and
kind. When you act as if everything is working out for you,
you naturally attract others who are on the same wavelength, people who uplift,
support, and inspire you. This creates a
powerful feedback loop. The more positive energy you project,
the more you attract positive influences into your life,
which further reinforces your mindset.
At the same time, it's important to remember that positive energy doesn't
mean ignoring the negative or pretending that challenges don't exist.
It's about choosing to focus on the possibility of good outcomes,
even in the face of difficulty. By maintaining an
attitude of openness and trust, you remain aligned with a flow of energy that
attracts favorable circumstances and nurtures growth.
This doesn't guarantee that everything will always be easy,
but it ensures that your outlook will continuously draw the best out
of whatever situation you face.
Ultimately, the magnetism of positive energy is a reflection
of the inner state you cultivate. When you trust that
life is working in your favor, your energy naturally reflects
the trust. You move through the world with a
sense of lightness, and this lightness becomes a powerful force,
drawing to you the very things that support and uplift your journey.
Living in the present moment means fully immersing yourself in the here and
now without being pulled by the regrets of the past or
the anxieties of the future. It's a state
of mindfulness where your attention is focused on the current experience,
free from the need to control what will happen next or relive what has already
happened. When you act as if everything always works out for
you, living in the present becomes a natural byproduct
of that mindset. Instead of constantly
worrying about how things will turn out, you trust that whatever unfolds
will be for your growth and benefit. By living in
the present, you free yourself from the mental chatter that often clouds your
perception. So much of our stress comes from projecting fears about
the future or ruminating on past mistakes.
But when you are grounded in the moment, you realize that all you truly have
is now. The past cannot be changed, and the future is uncertain.
What you can control, however, is your awareness of the present moment. And in
that awareness lies great power.
Being fully present allows you to engage with life more deeply.
You notice the richness of your current experience, whether it's a conversation or
a quiet moment, or even a challenge. You become more attuned
to your surroundings, your emotions, and the people around you. When you
act with the belief that things will work out. You stop wasting mental energy on
scenarios that may never happen. You invest your energy in what you're doing right
now, trusting that by staying present, you are best preparing yourself for whatever
the future holds. Living in the present
also means accepting uncertainty without anxiety.
When you trust that everything is unfolding as it should, you no longer
feel the need to constantly anticipate what's next.
You allow life to take its course, engaging with each
moment as it comes, knowing that future moments will take care of themselves.
This doesn't mean you lack ambition or direction. It simply means you are no longer
weighed down by the constant pull of what ifs. You are free to
experience life as it is, rather than as you think it should be.
Furthermore, being present enhances your ability to respond to life's challenges with
clarity and calmness. When you're not preoccupied with outcomes or
trapped in future worries, you are better able to see situations for what
they are. And you can respond with intention rather than reaction.
This presence of mind gives you the space to act in alignment with your values
and desires, making choices that are rooted in the reality of
now rather than in fear of the unknown.
In relationships, living in the present allows you to connect with others more
genuinely. You're not distracted by thoughts of what you need to do
later or by judgments about what has happened before.
Instead, you are fully available to the person in front of you, listening Engaging
and being open to the richness of that interaction. This presence
fosters deeper, more authentic connections as you are truly attuned
to the moment you're sharing with someone else.
Ultimately, living in the present moment aligns you with the flow of life.
It removes the need for constant control and opens the door to greater peace,
clarity and fulfillment. When you trust that everything is
working out for you, you release the mental burdens of the past and future,
allowing yourself to fully embrace and experience the present where life truly
happens. Empowerment comes from recognizing
that in every moment, you have the ability to choose how you respond to life.
No matter what circumstances you face, your power lies in your response,
whether that's in your thoughts, your attitude, or your actions.
When you act as if everything works out for you, you tap into this empowerment
because you're no longer reacting from fear or doubt.
Instead, you make conscious choices that reflect trust, optimism,
and a belief in your ability to navigate whatever comes your way.
Choice is a powerful tool because it gives you ownership of your experience.
While you can't always control the external events of life, you have full control over
how you choose to perceive and engage with them. By making
the decision to focus on possibilities rather than obstacles, on growth
rather than setbacks, you shift the trajectory of your life.
Every choice you make, no matter how small, shapes the path
ahead. When you choose to act with the belief
that things will work out, you begin to see opportunities even in challenges.
And this mindset fundamentally changes how you move through the world.
Empowerment through choice also means embracing responsibility for your life.
It's easy to fall into the trap of believing that life happens to you,
that you are a victim of circumstance. But when
you understand that your choices, both in thought and action, create your reality,
you reclaim your power. You are not at the mercy of external forces.
You are a co creator of your experience.
Each time you choose faith over fear, possibility of a limitation,
you are steering your life toward a more empowered, fulfilling direction.
This kind of empowerment extends beyond the immediate moment.
The more you practice conscious choice, the more you build a sense of self trust.
You begin to recognize that no matter what life throws at you, you have the
inner strength and wisdom to choose your response. This builds
resilience and confidence because you are no longer dependent on external
conditions for your sense of well being. Instead, you draw strength
from the knowledge that you always have the ability to choose your next step and
that choice is where your power resides.
Furthermore, choice allows you to align your actions with your values and
desires. When you act as if everything works out for you,
you're not just reacting to life, you're proactively creating the kind of life you want
to live. Each decision you make becomes a reflection of your belief
in yourself and your vision for the future. This alignment
between your beliefs and and your actions creates a sense of harmony and purpose,
empowering you to live more authentically and intentionally in
relationships. The power of choice is equally transformative. You can't
control how others behave, but you can choose how you engage, how you
communicate, and how you set boundaries. By choosing kindness,
understanding and respect, you cultivate healthier, more fulfilling connections
with those around you. Empowerment through choice allows you to navigate even difficult
relationships with grace, because you are anchored in your own ability
to decide what's right for you.
Ultimately, empowerment through choice is about realizing that you are
the architect of your own experience. Life will present you
with countless circumstances, some of which are beyond your control.
But within every situation, you have the power to choose how you think,
how you feel, and how you act. When you act
as if everything is working out for you, you are making a conscious choice to
trust in life, to believe in your own resilience, and to engage
with the world from a place of strength and possibility. This is
the true essence of empowerment. In the
end, acting as if everything always works out for you is not just a mindset,
but a way of living that transforms your entire experience of life.
It begins with perception. Understanding that the way you see
the world shapes your reality. By embracing uncertainty
and detaching from rigid outcomes, you free yourself to flow with
life's unpredictability. You harness the power of thought and intention,
recognizing that your inner world influences the outer.
Resilience is built through faith, faith in yourself, and in the process,
knowing that even challenges serve your growth.
Through this journey, you discover the magnetism of positive energy which
attracts opportunities and people aligned with your highest good.
Living in the present moment allows you to experience life fully without the
weight of the past or the anxiety of the future. And ultimately,
you find empowerment through choice, realizing that in each moment, you have
the power to shape your reality through the decisions you make.
This way of being is not about avoiding difficulties or pretending life is always
easy. It's about choosing to trust that no matter
what happens, you are capable of navigating life's complexities with grace,
openness and strength. When you act as if everything works
out for you, you align yourself with the natural flow of life,
creating a path where challenges become opportunities, uncertainty becomes
possibility, and life itself becomes a journey of continual growth and unfolding.
You are a fluke. You are A separate
event.
And you run from the maternity ward to the crematorium and that's it,
baby, that's it.
Now, why does anybody think that way? There's no
reason to, because it isn't even scientific.
It's just a myth. And it's invented
by people who wanted to feel a
certain way, they want to play a certain game.
But we have this hostility to the external world because of the
superstition, the myth, the absolutely unfounded
theory that you yourself exist
only inside your skin. We feel
we have been hypnotized, literally hypnotized by
social convention into feeling and sensing
that we exist only inside our skins. There is in
our whole way of thinking the idea that we are a
soul, a spiritual essence of some
kind imprisoned inside a body,
and that we look out upon a world that is foreign
to us.
Should you or not commit suicide? This is a good question.
Why go on?
And you only go on if the game is worth the candle.
And so really, a satisfactory theory
of the universe has to be one that's worth betting on.
That's a very. Seems to me absolutely elementary common sense.
If you make a theory of the universe which isn't worth betting on,
why bother? Just commit suicide.
But if you want to go on playing the game, you've got to have an
optimal theory for playing the game.
Otherwise there's no point in.
Is absolutely absurd. To say that we came into this world.
We didn't. We came out of it.
You see, when you make something,
you put it together,
you arrange parts, or you work from the outside to
the inn as a. As a sculptor works on a stone or as the
potter works on clay. But when you watch something growing,
it works in exactly the opposite direction. It works from
the inside to the outside. It expands,
it burgeons, it blossoms.
You as a human being, you grow out of
this physical universe in just exactly the same way that an apple
grows off an apple tree. So let's say
the tree which grows apples is a tree which apples.
And a world in which human beings arrive is a world that peoples.
And so the existence of people is symptomatic of
the kind of universe we live in.
But you see, we. We curiously twist it.
We say, well, first of all, in the beginning there was nothing but gas and
rock. And then intelligence happen
to arise in it. You are a fl.
But we're thinking in a way, you see, that disconnects the
intelligence from the rocks.
Where there are rocks, watch out,
watch out, because the rocks are going eventually to come
alive. It's Only a
matter of time. Just in the same way as the seed, the acorn is
eventually going to turn into the oak because it has the potentiality of
that within it. Rocks are not dead.
From a strictly physical, scientific standpoint,
this organism is a continuous
energy with everything else that's going on.
And if I am my foot, I am the sun.
Sa.
There are no such things as things,
that is to say, separate things or separate events.
That is only a way of talking.
If you can understand this, you're going to have no further problems.
You. You can't have an experience of nothing.
Nature appalls a vacuum. So after you're dead, the only
thing that can happen is the same experience or the same sort of experience as
when you were born.
In other words, we all know very well that after people die,
other people are born, and they're all
you, only you could only experience it one at a
time. Everybody is I. You all
know you're you. And wheresoever
beings exist throughout all galaxies, it doesn't make any difference.
You are all of them. And when they come into
being, that's you coming into being. Really.
The fundamental, ultimate mystery, the only thing you need to know to understand
the deepest metaphysical secrets is
this, that for every outside there is
an inside, and for every inside there is an outside.
And although they are different, they go together.
Buddhist philosophy speaks of the four
invisibles.
Water to the fish,
air to the bird,
mind to mankind,
and enlightenment to the ignorant.
Because, you see, you never know
your own element.
Now, it's impossible, therefore, to give a
definition of consciousness because we
don't know anything outside it, just as the fish doesn't know anything outside water
and the bird doesn't know anything outside air.
We don't know unconsciousness.
We only know when we have been unconscious.
And so we are in a very difficult
fix to attempt to define the subject of
this seminar. We all know
what it is, and yet none of us know what it is.
We know we're conscious.
It's the same sort of problem as to try to say what color your eyes
are. I don't mean whether they're blue or brown, but the color of the
iris, the lens of the eye,
because we say it has no color, it's transparent, it's like pure glass.
And yet that might be a color to
somebody who had a different kind of eye.
An Englishman and an Hindu were once sitting in the backyard of
the Hindu's home.
And the Hindu was talking about
the necessity of a background for the perception
of any figure. So he said
against what background do you see those flowers? And he
said, against the background of the hedge.
And against what background you see the hedge? He said, the background
of the hills. And against what background
do you see the hills? He said, the background of the sky,
he said. And against what background do you see the sky?
The Englishman fell silent.
The Hindu said, it's the background of consciousness.
There, you see, we reach a limit and
you can talk until all is blue about whether
consciousness and reality are the same thing,
whether there really is ever any such thing as pure unconsciousness,
whether consciousness is eternal, whether, as the
subjective idealists would say in philosophy, there is primarily
mind and all so called physical
and material existence is something in mind or something in consciousness.
You can debate that subject forever and ever and ever and come out nowhere.
There is no answer to the question when asked
in that way. But it is helpful
as a start to make things at once more simple
and perhaps a little more difficult by
overcoming at the beginning the
traditional opposition between the spiritual and the material,
or the mental and the material,
by the trick of talking about all
things, whether spiritual or physical,
in terms of pattern.
Because that's all anybody can really talk about.
You see, it's fundamental to our common sense, which was
highly influenced by Aristotle in the book of Genesis,
that all forms are composed of some substance in
roughly the same way as sculptures are made of stone
or pots made of clay. But a serious
physicist no longer thinks in such terms about the material world.
He doesn't think it's made of anything.
Because what the physical process
of nature is, is patterns. You could say
patterns of energy, but that's using the old
ceramic language. Patterns aren't made
of energy. The patterning is the same thing as the energy.
So if you use the verb patterning as what the
universe is, then you get something
that you can talk about. You can describe patterns, you can measure them.
You could say what a pattern is doing. Although a pattern isn't a
thing, a pattern is a verb. It is a process, it's an
activity. So we can say patterning is
what is going on. And consciousness is a
kind of patterning, as we shall see. Just so
are flowers and human beings and stars,
trees, water, air,
everything, even space itself is a form of patterning.
And this means, in other words,
that the universe is what physicists
would call an energy field.
And likewise, consciousness is
a field in the sense,
say, that space is obviously a field, that is to say, an area
in which things happen. That's the primary meaning of field.
A field is a playing field. A field in which something happens
like an arena. Only when you use the
word field in more, in the sense of physics, you mean
a field of forces like a magnetic field,
like a gravitational field. And the curious
thing about fields is that they exercise their energy
in a non mechanical way. For example,
if gravity were non field,
that is to say, if it were the ordinary sort of exercise of energy,
like the propagation of heat, or like someone
pulling. Then when you put something on the ground, you put
a good heavy lead plate on the ground that would
be absorbing so much gravitational energy. And therefore anything
you put on top of the plate would be less acted
upon by gravity than the lead plate itself. And then
anything on top of that would be still less. And you would reduce the
energy of gravity by piling things up. But you don't. It doesn't make the slightest
difference to the gravitational field.
So in the same way, if you take an electrical coil, say surrounding a plastic
tube, you can put a current through that and
you create a field within the tube. You can put
your hand inside the tube and nothing will happen to it. But the minute
you put something that is like steel inside the tube,
it will get hot. But no heat will be generated until
the steel is inside the tube. Because the
coil plus the steel equals heat.
But the coil has to polarize with the steel
inside before anything happens at all. So that
shows us that what is operating as a field.
Now think
then of the world as a field
characterized by patterning, which. For which another
name is energy.
And we are
going to have to treat consciousness
in rather the same way.
All people who are in a rush are
not related to the material present.
First thing, let's take. You're in a rush to get coffee. When you go to
get up in the morning, what do you do? You take instant
coffee. And that's a punishment for being in a hurry.
It doesn't taste of coffee. Not really.
So because you, you, you forced it. It's like forcing the growth of
tomatoes. They don't taste of tomatoes anymore. Forced apples,
they're called delicious. They're nothing but wet pith.
So this, this,
this is showing that we aren't here,
we're insane, we're not all there, as they say.
But trying to get to something.
The result, the thing we thought we wanted, the thing that we thought
would be what would make us happy. You got to get something now.
It's true, in order to not be hungry, you have to
eat.
And therefore when you eat, there's a certain satisfaction,
feel. All right. But then when you
begin to consider that life is going to wear out
and there are all sorts of problems, disease, change and misfortune and
you get depressed. And then in order to feel happy, you eat
when you don't need to eat.
Then you begin to get obesity and indigestion
and wonder why the possession of all this great food isn't doing
anything for you, it's supposed to.
And so in the same way with. With property of all kinds,
when it is used to get the thing that
you look forward to in the future and don't seem to have now,
it becomes a complete delusion and
you can't understand because you think that the possession of these things ought to make
you happy. The admin have persuaded you
that if you could get this kind of car, this kind of yacht, this kind
of house, this kind of scene, whatever it may
be, you should. That that's the thing in life, that's what's important.
And it doesn't make people happy at all. And then they wonder why it doesn't
and feel cheated and they have to go to psychoanalysts
and churches and things like that to. To be persuaded
that it's coming. Sometime, somehow the thing
that is always seems to be missing. And there's nothing missing at all.
Except, I mean, supposing you're absolutely starved and you just don't
have the normal flow of energy through your organism. Then of course you
need food, or if you're freezing,
you need shelter. But in the ordinary way, when you are
fed and sheltered, there isn't anything missing.
It's all here, but nobody is
here to see it. Everybody is wandering
after something else in the distance.
And of course this is preeminently true with
two other aspects of life. I've discussed housing,
furniture and clothing. But more specifically,
food in the white Anglo Saxon
Protestant culture is unbelievably bad when
you consider it, by and large. The reason being that we eat
food because it's good for us.
And that's a dreadful thing to do because it
means that you look at the
food from the point of view of abstract dietetics
rather than concrete taste.
And wherever dietitians get interfering with
cooking that is utterly destroyed in
every university,
in every university from coast to coast,
where you would think would be centers of culture.
The institutional food is unbelievably
abominable and the,
the scholars are ashamed to come out about it
because, and protest and, and lay down the law
because they're supposed to be devoted to higher things.
And after all, what you eat just so long as it's got the right chemicals
in, it isn't very important what this is.
You see, the trouble with that is two things to
eat in order to live. Sort of that it's good for
you. What do you mean,
good for you? It means that it helps you to go on into the
future.
But what is the point of going on into the future when
all the meals ahead of you,
these unappetizing things, are just gonna enable you
to go on into the future?
And the second thing is that eating in this spirit
is very disrespectful to all the creatures you have killed
in order to eat. It's even disrespectful to an onion to
eat it improperly. Onions are living creatures.
And if you cut up an onion for. For dinner, you should reverence the
onion, you should respect it. Because if you don't
have a feeling of love for the onion, for the fish, for whatever
you eat, you won't cook it properly and you won't enjoy it.
Cooking is a process of loving and.
And it is a paying of. Of respect to these marvelous beings
which we ingest in order to go on living.
So this entirely futuristic dietetic attitude
to food is again, you see, a question of
purely quantitative thinking, of lack of relation to
the material world. I may make
one other rather important aspect of life as lovemaking.
Here again is a subject entirely neglected in our education from
any practical point of view. I mean, a lot of theoretical works,
some of which are fantastic and grotesque as
a fine art. When you compare what
goes on in most bedrooms with the things that are suggested in the Kama
Sutra, the difference is amazing.
That there could be a real great art as
between lovers, husbands and wives and so on is
something, again, that we don't consider. Because once again,
although sex is fun,
we. We go about it not really because we enjoy it.
We can't admit that, but it's good for us. It's a healthy outlet.
And also it's necessary, of course, for having children.
And that's also something for the future.
The existence, the physical universe is
basically playful. There is no necessity for it whatsoever.
It isn't going anywhere. That is to say,
it doesn't have
some destination that it ought to arrive at,
but that it is best understood by analogy with music.
Because music as an art form is essentially
playful. We say you play the piano, you don't work the piano.
Why music differs from,
say, travel. When you travel, you are trying to get
somewhere. In music, though,
one doesn't make the end of a Composition.
The point of the competition, of the composition, if that were so,
the best conductors would be those who played fastest and
there would be composers who wrote only finales. People go
to concert just to hear one crashing chord because that's the end.
Same way in dancing, you don't aim at a particular spot in the room.
That's where you should arrive. The whole point of the dancing is the dance now.
But we don't see that as something
brought by our education into our everyday conduct.
We've got a system of schooling which gives a completely
different impression. It's all graded.
And what we do is we put the child into the corridor of
this grade system with a kind of come on, kitty, kitty,
kitty. And now you go to kindergarten, you know, and that's a great thing
because when you finish that, you'll get into first grade and
then, come on, first grade leads to second grade and so on. And then you
get out of grade school, you've got high school and it's revving up. The thing
is coming. Then you're going to go to college and by Jove, then you get
into graduate school. And when you're through with graduate school,
you go out to join the world and then you get into some
racket where you're selling insurance and they've got that quota
to make and you're going to make that. And all the time the thing
is coming, it's coming, it's coming, that great thing,
the success you're working for. Then when you wake up one day about 40
years old, you say, my God, I've arrived,
I'm there. And you don't feel very different from what
you always felt.
Look at the people who live to retire and
put those savings away. And then when they 65,
they don't have any energy left. They're more or less impotent and
they go and rot in an old people's senior citizens community.
Because we've simply cheated ourselves the whole way down the line.
We thought of life by analogy with a journey,
with a pilgrimage which had a serious purpose at the end. And the thing
was to get to that end. Success or whatever it is, or maybe heaven
after your death.
But we missed the point. The whole way along it
was a musical thing and you were supposed to sing or to dance while the
music was being played.
Courage of star before
you left. How light
carries on endlessly
even after death.
The shortness of
brightness. I'll explain
the infinite.
How rare and beautiful
it truly is that
we exist.
That is a way of demonstrating the Basic experience,
which underlies some of the major forms of Oriental
philosophy. And actually this way of
demonstrating it is taken from a kind of Chinese and Japanese
Buddhism called Zen, which I'm going to be talking about quite
a bit today, because Zen is one of the best examples
of a philosophy, shall we call it,
in which this experience is dominant.
Zen, of course, is a Japanese word and it's
spelled Z, E, N,
and that is the Japanese way of pronouncing the Chinese word
chan.
And this in turn is the Chinese way of pronouncing an
Indian Sanskrit word, yana.
And Dhyana refers
to the kind of experience which has been
represented in this circle. Another word for it would
be a third, a second Sanskrit term,
shunya.
And the nearest we can translate shunya is in English,
is emptiness or void.
And so we might say this is an experience of
the void before
trying to explain what this is. And, you know, the funny
thing is it really can't be explained because it has to be felt,
because it's a transformation of one's basic feeling, one's basic
consciousness of life. But I should mention first
that it is characteristic of Eastern philosophy
to be based on experience rather than ideas.
You see, philosophy in the Western world,
especially as it's taught in our universities and academies,
is mainly a matter of thinking. It's a matter
of trying to arrive at certain clear,
positive ideas, ideas about the nature of man,
the nature of the universe, and so on and so forth.
And also, religion in the west is somewhat similar because religion
is largely concerned with belief in certain ideas.
In these basic forms of Eastern philosophy, on the other hand, such as Zen,
which is a kind of Buddhism or Taoism, the basic
native philosophy of China, or in Venice, Vedanta,
which is the central form of Indian philosophy.
What is basic to them is not ideas,
but a way of experiencing, a way of feeling.
And this might be called, as it is here, the void
demonstrated by the circle,
because it is not a void which is just emptiness.
This isn't the idea that there are people
in the backward world of the backward worlds of Asia who
think that the universe is ultimately nothing at all.
It is rather that the void represents
complete spiritual freedom. Or you might
say, if you don't like the word spiritual, complete psychological
freedom. And therefore I
want to try, if I can, to communicate to
you, to give you some idea of what this experience
is in Japanese. In Zen it is called satori.
I'll write that down. It's an unfamiliar word,
S A T O R
I. And I
like the way that that's pronounced in Southern Chinese.
They pronounce it because
it's something that happens to you suddenly.
Now, let me try, if I can possibly,
to put into some sort of words what this experience is.
This experience which, so far as they are concerned,
is the objective of human
life. To get this is
to understand the meaning of human nature and destiny
only because it's a transformation of consciousness, because it's something
you feel rather than something you think. It is, for this reason,
difficult to put into words. But it is as if
you saw quite suddenly, and indeed this
experience could have happened to you. It can
come without warning to anybody. And so what I'm going to be saying
may strike a familiar ring in some ears, but it
is as if quite suddenly, you became totally
convinced that the way everything
is in this universe and at this moment is
absolutely right. And that's almost putting
it too weakly. I'm not trying to talk about
a sort of Pollyanna feeling where we say, well,
this is the best of all possible worlds, and everything, however evil and
however wrong, is going to work out all right in the end, because it's a
means to an end in some master design. I'm not saying that.
I'm saying it is suddenly feeling that
everything is right the way
it is now, however appalling,
however terrible, and you know it
beyond a shadow of doubt.
There are two other aspects to this experience as well,
and although you feel them all together, we have to talk about them separately.
While the first aspect is feeling that everything, just as it is,
is so right that you could say of it,
this is why I'm alive. This is what life's all about.
The second is that everything you see and feel seems
to come to life in an extraordinary way. You feel the world as you've seen
it before was seen almost in a dream, but it
is as if just the ordinary things that were confronting you suddenly went
yah. And came alive.
And the third aspect of it is that you no longer
feel yourself and what you are experiencing
to be separated. Although you don't lose
the feeling of the outline of your skin. You don't forget
that I, or Joe Doak is a possible name by
which you can refer to yourself. Nevertheless, it suddenly
seems to you that your skin is no longer what divides you from
the world. It's what joins you to it. What you see outside you
is also you. Now, we ordinarily
restrict the idea of ego,
of inus or of unis, to some
sort of psychological entity or
process inside us which is in control of things.
And we identify ourselves with a sort of controlling center.
But in this experience, it is as if that center was suddenly
enlarged to include the whole universe.
You almost feel as if you were God. Except that in
Eastern thought, one doesn't think. Think of God as a kind of omnipotent
person. I mean, there are lots of people in our asylums
who say, well, I'm God. I was like the story of the woman who insisted
that she was God. And to humor her, someone said, well, if you're God,
will you please explain how you managed to create the universe in six days?
She said, I never talk shop. It isn't
feeling God in that sense as if you could do anything.
But it is feeling that you and
this whole world are one.
And that in this experience of oneness
and the sudden coming alive of everything. And the profound
rightness. That's the only word I can use. The profound rightness of
each moment, of this moment, however far it may
seem to be, short of one's ideals of perfection,
this is it.
And you say, having seen this, I can
die content. This is what it was all about.
Underneath it all, there's this vast realm of
conscious presence. There is a presence there without which
you wouldn't be able to perceive anything. You wouldn't be able
to think anything. It's a little bit like
I compare it sometimes to before you
live on the surface of the ocean. You are a little ripple on
the surface of the ocean. And this ripple
only knows itself as a ripple.
And it looks at other ripples and
sometimes feels threatened by other ripples. Or wants to use other ripples
to enhance its own sense of self. And it's always fearful.
It always compares itself to other ripples.
A very unpleasant and frustrating way to live.
It hasn't realized the depth of its being
because the ripple is only a temporary expression of the vastness
of the ocean. But it doesn't know that.
So if the ripple for a moment comes to us, if the.
The continuous thought. In this analogy,
the ripple, of course, is the human being and
the ripple. When the ripple stops thinking for a moment,
and this is the key, for a moment,
you come to a cessation of the stream of thinking.
And what's left when you're not thinking about your
history, your personal history or
the future, you're just becoming aware of this
moment, yourself, this moment.
But what is that self? It's no longer the historical
self. You can't say very much about it.
There is an underlying sense of presence,
of alive, conscious presence.
It's still but still alive.
The awakening can begin with
realizing that you are not the thoughts that go through
your mind. That's the beginning. Now what has
arisen at that moment? Awareness.
Suddenly you realize that there is a dimension
of consciousness in you that's not thinking but
just conscious. And that is your essence identity
to be rooted in that. It's ultimately
very simple. I don't know why they don't teach that at school.
I mean, the most important life lesson is
the transcendent dimension of life of who you
are. To find all the ancient teachings using
different terms and different words. They all point
to, to this possibility of realizing the transcendent
dimension of who you are. Whether the
Buddha calls it, the Buddha actually calls it.
The translation is sunyata, emptiness.
But better translation would be spaciousness.
That's the essence of who you are, Sunyatta,
spaciousness. Jesus talks about the
kingdom of heaven, which in my translation is
not. I translated kingdom, I translated
as dimension and heaven, which is the
vast heaven. When you look up at the sky,
that's the closest thing you can get to spaciousness in
the sense perceived world. The closest thing you can get to spatience.
The look at the vastness of the sky or heaven. In many languages
heaven and sky is the same word. So you look at the
vastness of sky, which is vast, spaciousness.
So the kingdom of heaven is the dimension of spaciousness.
It's a dimension of consciousness. This is why then they asked Jesus,
where is the kingdom of heaven? When is it going to come?
And he said, the kingdom of heaven cannot come with
science to be perceived. You can never say it's over here or it's
over there, because kingdom of heaven is within you.
In fact, he was saying it is the essence of who you are.
Consciousness is. But it's not only the essence of who you are, it's the
essence of the universe itself. Because you are,
you are just a microcosm of the universe.
So when you realize the essence of who you are, the universe is real,
its own essence through you. This little thing through
you.
The ideas of Alan Watts and Eckhart Tolle are fundamental
contributions to the wisdom on this channel. But the animations displayed
here are merely the tip of the iceberg. If you want to dive
deep into the philosophies, we recommend checking out their audiobooks
on Audible. We are truly blessed to have access to
life enhancing perspectives at the click of a button. And Audible
makes it just that easy. Go to audible.com afterschool
or text afterschool to 500500 to listen for free
to the audiobooks of Eckhart Tolle, Alan Watts,
or any audiobook of your choice from Audible's vast selection
of audiobooks, podcasts, and more.
Audible makes it easy to absorb the information while you were cooking,
cleaning, exercising, or on the go.
Right now, for a limited time, save 60% on your
first three months of Audible. That's only 5.95amonth.
Give yourself the gift of listening. For more, go to
audible.com afterschool or text after school
to 500500 IT.