Now, existence, you see, is something that is spontaneous.
The Chinese word for nature means
that which happens of itself.
Your hair grows by itself, your heart beats by itself.
You breathe pretty much by itself. Your glands secrete
their essences by themselves. You don't have
voluntary control over these things. So we say it
happens spontaneously. So when you
go to sleep and you try to go to sleep, you interfere with the spontaneous
process of going to sleep. Try to breathe,
you know, real hard, and you find you get balled up in your breathing.
So if you.
You go to be human, you just have to trust yourself
to have bowel movements and go to sleep. Sleep and digest your food.
Of course, if something goes seriously wrong and you need a surgeon, that's another matter.
But by and large, the healthy human being doesn't,
right from the start of life, need surgical interference,
and he lets it happen by him, by itself.
So. So with the whole picture that is fundamental to it,
you've got to let go and let it happen.
Because if you don't, you're going to be all clutched
up. You're going to be constantly trying to
do what can happen healthily
only if you don't try.
But we have a strange anxiety in us that if we
don't interfere, it won't happen.
And that's the root of an enormous amount of trouble.
But the basis of it all is this. Then if
we say, you must survive or I must survive,
life is earnest and I've got to go on,
then your life is a drag and
not a game. Now,
it's my contention, my personal opinion, this is my basic metaphysical
axiom, shall we put it that way, that existence,
the physical universe, is basically playful.
There is no necessity for it whatsoever.
It isn't going anywhere.
That is to say, it doesn't have
some destination that it ought to arrive at.
So then in music,
though, one doesn't make the end of
a composition the
point of the competition, of the composition. If that was so, the best
conductors would be those who played fastest,
and there would be composers who wrote only finales.
People go to concert just to hear one crashing chord, because that's
the end. Same way in
dancing, you don't aim at a particular spot in the room. That's where
you should arrive. The whole point of the dancing is the dance.
Now, but we don't see that as something
brought by our education into our everyday conduct.
We've got a system of schooling which
gives a completely different impression.
It's all graded. And what we do is we put
the child into the corridor of this grade system
with a kind of come on, kitty, kitty, kitty. And now you go to kindergarten,
you know, and that's a great thing because when you finish that, you'll get
into first grade and then, come on, first grade
leads to second grade and so on. And then you get out of grade school,
you've got high school and it's revving up. The thing is coming. Then you're going
to go to college by Joe. Then you get into graduate school. And when
you're through with graduate school, you go out to join the world and
then you get into some racket where you're selling insurance and
they've got that quota to make and you're going to make that. And all
the time this thing is coming, it's coming, it's coming, that great thing,
the success you're working for. Then when you wake up one day, about 40 years
old, you say, my God, I've arrived,
I'm there. And you don't feel very different from what you always
felt. And there's a slight letdown because you feel there's a hoax.
And there was a hoax, a dreadful hoax.
They made you miss everything by expectation.
Look at the people who live to retire. Put those savings
away and then when they 65,
they don't have any energy left, they're more or less impotent and
they go and rot in an old people's senior citizens community because
we've simply cheated ourselves the whole way down the line.
We thought of life by analogy with a journey,
with a pilgrimage, which had a serious purpose at the end.
And the thing was to get to that end, success or whatever it is,
or maybe heaven after you're dead.
But we missed the point. The whole way along it was a musical
thing and you were supposed to sing or to dance while the music was being
played.
We see, don't we? All that we experience is
understandable as a spectrum of vibrations. There are different
kinds of spectra. There's the spectrum of light, there's the spectrum of sound.
We can also think of spectra of smells,
of tactile feelings, of emotions and
so on. All down the line. We are, as it were, living in the midst
of a woven tapestry of many dimensions
in which the warps and the woofs are all these different spectra
of various kinds of vibrations. And as on
the loom, the warp crosses the woof.
And if you didn't have one, you wouldn't have the other.
It takes two to reveal the pattern.
So see yourselves as patterns
in a weaving system.
You wouldn't Be here if it weren't for the interlocking of all these different
spectra dimensions.
So then here they go, and these things are vibrating.
Now, when it reaches a certain point, you say,
oh, that's too much. When it reaches another point, you say,
it's not enough. Why, there's nothing here. I don't
feel a thing. Now I gotta go to sleep.
But on the other end, you say, no, no, no, no, you're going far
enough. If you go any further, that's got to tear things apart.
I can't withhold this tension. See,
now. So some people will say, all right, now, now, relax, relax, relax,
take it easy, take it easy. But often, you see, the point is you can't
do that. So then what
I would say to the person who cannot relax, I will stress
his tension, go the other way. In other
words, go with the line of least resistance. Say, okay, you're tense
about all this. Now, let's say really tense.
Let's scream, no, no, no, no, no. See,
you get violent inside. This is not to happen,
see? But so that one way or the other, you see,
it doesn't matter which you go, you begin to get into this
thing, which is what is happening when
the boat of life begins really to rock,
yet rocking with it by whatever way is open.
But you are not going to force the issue here.
Instead of saying to you, you should be doing it another way than you're doing
it. I will be saying, now find out the way. You must do
it and
go that way.
Now, this is a general principle of
an art. And we will find there is a kind
of. There are limits to this art and how it
can be used and so forth. But once the general principles are
clear, there aren't many serious problems left.
That if you begin to look at it in that way,
you will begin to realize that
ecstasy by one road or another is inevitable.
That indeed, ecstasy is, in a way, the nature of existence.
There is a universe for the simple reason that it's ecstatic.
What else is all this fireworks about?
It is just like music in this ecstatic thing going
off. And you have to be certainly
careful in a little way here. That any initiation into a
deep wisdom is apt at first to demotivate you.
You think, what the hell am I doing? And all these projects,
building this up and that up. Or doing something to save the world and so
on and so forth. Why, that whole thing is nonsense.
Yes.
See, our problem is we don't really know how to stop. We've got something
started and we see it's going in a wrong direction. And I think
the difficulty is to borrow an old Chinese saying
that when the wrong man uses the right means, the right means
work in the wrong way. In other words, there's something wrong with
the way we think. And while that is there,
everything we do will be a mess. Now, what is it
that's wrong? Now, as far as I can see,
the basic mistake is that
we've invented this wonderful system of language and
calculation and
that it is at once too simple to
deal with the complexity of the world.
And also, we are liable to confuse that system
of symbols with the world itself, just as we confuse,
say, money with wealth. A lot of people are in business
to make money instead of wealth. When they make the money, they don't know what
to do with it. And so, in the same way we
confuse happiness with status,
and we confuse ourselves as living organisms, which are
one with this whole universe, with something we call our personality.
Now, what is our personality?
Our personality is what we call our image,
our image of ourselves and also our thought about ourselves,
our idea of ourselves. This is the person,
in other words, what people meet and understand. And what I
understand as Alan Watts is a big act,
which is not really me. Because in
the image of Alan Watts, there are not all my unconscious
processes, both psychological and physical. The construction of
my brain is not contained in the concept Alan Watts.
And the concept Alan Watts does not contain the inseparable
relationships which I have with all the rest of the universe.
And therefore, that concept is a fraud.
And when it's mistaken for the real me, there's a confusion.
Because if somebody says to me, alan Watts, do something
about it. The concept Alan Watts can't do anything,
in other words, because it's only a concept,
you can't make it lift a weight, just as three
is a concept. Three, the number. You can't make just plain three
do anything. So also, you can't wrap up parcels with the equator.
It's a useful imaginary line, but it can't do anything.
But we all feel that this concept of ourselves, which we
call our personality or our ego, can do something because
we think it really exists. And I'll tell you why we think it exists.
What happens when you. If I were to say to you,
now, look hard at the television screen, really look at it,
what do you do as distinct from just watching it in the ordinary way?
When you say, now, I really gotta see that, what do you do?
Notice that you tighten muscles all around here,
that you frown a little, you clench your teeth Perhaps.
Now, what has that got to do with seeing anything clearly?
Absolutely nothing to do with it. Same thing when you listen carefully.
Now, listen, catch everything that's said. Or you start tightening
up around your ears. That has nothing to do with hearing clearly.
Now, from the moment we were little children, when teachers in class
screamed at us, pay attention. We go tight in various
ways. Either to see or hear
more clearly, to concentrate or to will something which is
supposed to be difficult to do. And that constitutes
a habitual tension over the whole body that's there almost all the
time. And that feeling of unnecessary tension is,
as it were, the material sensation upon which we fasten this
concept of I. We hang it on to that feeling.
The concept is not us. The feeling of tension is
completely phony. It has nothing to do with success in seeing, hearing or acting.
And so we get the marriage of an illusion with a falsehood.
And that we call ourselves. And no wonder we feel cut
off from everything, alienated, frightened of life and death.
So what has to happen is we have to come back
to a sane view
of our own life, which is
the way we really are. An organism functioning in
terms of the whole environment, with the whole environment. Instead of
this funny little separate personality. But how are we going to do that?
People say you can't change human nature overnight. You're asking
us to give up the ego. And that's the most difficult
of all things to do. Actually, it isn't,
because the ego doesn't exist. But of course, if you
try to give up your ego with your ego. Then it will take
you to the end of time. Because this is the
point. You can't transform yourself.
You can't make yourself sane. You can't make yourself loving.
You can't make yourself unselfish.
And yet it's absolutely necessary that we be that way.
It's absolutely necessary.
If we are going to hand over the direction
of nature to nature, which is what it comes to.
It's absolutely necessary that we let go
of ourselves. And it can't be done.
Not by anything that we call doing it. Acting,
willing, or even just accepting things. You can't
do it. Why? Because you don't
really exist as that kind of a separate ego or personality.
It's just an idea based on a phony feeling.
So when it comes down to it,
it's shocking news for us,
for the human race, for our pride.
You're only making a mess by trying to put things straight.
You're trying to straighten out a wiggly world. And no wonder you're in trouble.
So you can't do anything, so you can't transform
yourself. And what can you do?
What happens then? If you actually realize you've come to a dead end and
the human race has come to a dead end, in my opinion,
what then? Commit suicide?
Or is there something else? What happens
when you just wait? There's nothing you can do.
You watch and
all you see is what goes on that is happening of itself.
You are breathing, the wind is blowing,
the trees are waving, your blood is circulating,
your nerves are tingling. It's all going on with itself.
But you know that's you, that's the real you,
the you that goes on of itself.
It's not the symbol,
it's not the person, it's you
that's happening. As when you breathe. Yes, you can get
the feeling that I am breathing by shoving your breath. But your
breath goes on day in and day out without
you doing anything about it or even thinking of it. The same way your brain
is functioning without your forcing it. So when
you come to a dead end, and we are individually and socially
now at a dead end,
this is the moment of which it is said man's extremity is God's opportunity
because we have to stop. And when we stop,
we find a world that is happening rather than being
done, being shoved. And that happening,
as distinct from doing, is our fundamental self.
And our fundamental self is not something just inside the skin.
It's everything around us with which we
connect. When you look out of your eyes
at nature happening out there, you're looking at you.
I'm not going to say what we should do from then on,
but simply that before we think of
doing anything in this critical situation,
we realize the completely illusory nature of the
beings that we think we are and
get back again to the beings that we really
are, which includes
all this outside
world no longer left outside.
So long as you are trying to make progress, you will go up.
But up always implies down.
So while you are trying to get better and better and better, that means that
when you get to the best, you can only go on to the worst.
And so you go round and round and round, ever chasing the illusion
that there is something outside yourself, outside your
here and now, be attained, that will make things better.
And the thing is to recover from that illusion. So a Buddha
means somebody who has woken up and discovered
that running around this thing may be fun and
it may be good to run around, but if you think you're going to get
something out of it, you're under A move because you're forever the
donkey with a carrot suspended on his own ho.
Now then, it goes on to say that there's only one place, one point
in this wheel from which you can become a Buddha, and that's here.
The devas are too happy to become Buddhas or
to worry about becoming a Buddha. The Narakas are too miserable,
the Asuras are too angry, the animals are too dumb, and the
pretties too frustrated. Only in the middle position,
the position of man, which is, you could say, the equal position,
the position of sufficient equanimity to begin
to think about getting off this rat race,
is only from there, you see, can you become a Buddha.
So the position of a Buddha may be represented either as not
on the wheel at all or is right in the middle of makes no
difference. And so he
is just as, in a way, the axle point, the still point of the turning
world, as to use T.S. eliot's phrase,
is the unmoved center, the unmoved mover,
supreme mobile, the axle tree of the world, Also the
navel. That's why yogis are said to contemplate their navel.
Navel isn't on their tummy. It's this place, the navel
of the world. So that's the scheme
of cosmology, of ancient Indian
cosmology, in which Buddhism arises.
So you see, therefore, a Buddha is one
who awakens from
the illusion of samsara,
that is, from the thought
that there is something to get out of life,
that tomorrow will bring it to you, that in the course
of time it will be all right.
Therefore, one is set, pursuing time as if
you were trying to quench your thirst by drinking salt water.
Now, I can exemplify this a little more strongly
by relating Buddhism to the social
system in which it arose.
A Buddhist monk
is sometimes called a shramana,
S R a M a N, a shramana.
This is closely allied to the word shaman.
And a shaman is the holy
man in a culture that
is still hunting. It isn't settled, it isn't agrarian.
There is a very strong and important difference between a shaman and a
priest. A priest
receives his ordination from his superiors.
He receives something from a tradition which is handed down.
A shaman doesn't. He receives
his enlightenment by going off into the forest by himself,
to be completely alone.
A shaman is a man, in other words, who has undergone solitariness.
He's gone away into the forest to find out who
he really is, because it's very difficult to
find that out while you're with other people. The reason
is that other people are busy all the time telling you who you are
in many, many ways. By the laws they impose on you,
by the behavior ruts they set on you,
by the things they tell you, by the fact that they always call you by
your name, and by the fact that when you live among people, you have to
be in a state of ceaseless chatter.
But if you want to find out who you are before your father
and mother conceived you, who you really
are, you almost have to go off by yourself,
go into the forest and stop talking, even stop thinking
words. I be absolutely alone.
Listen for the great silences.
And then if you're lucky, you recover from the illusion
that you're just little me with so and so.
And you attain the state of nirvana, which means
the blown out state,
the relieved state, the sigh of relief. Nirvana may
be translated into English as whew.
I've at last discovered that I don't have
to survive. I can
survive, of course, but I don't really have to.
Because you discover, you see, that what you
really are doesn't have to survive.
Because it's what there is, the real
you, is it?
Or that tat tvam asi,
that art thou, as the Hindus say.
So then, in the
normal life of India, which is not
a hunting culture but a settled culture,
there are priests, but there is something beyond
the priest. That is to say, when a
man or woman has fulfilled
his or her life in the world of society,
it's the normal thing to do for a person
to quit their status in society and
become what's called a forest dweller.
That is almost, you see, to go back to the hunting culture,
they divide people into two classes. Grihasta, which means
householder, and vanaprastha, which means forest dweller.
And the older people all hand over their
occupations and positions to their children
and into the stage of vanaprasta, or become
a shramana and go outside the stockade.
I'm speaking metaphorically. They sometimes do, actually, they sometimes
don't, and become a nobody.
They give up their name, that is to say, the label
which designates who they are in terms of caste or class.
They become unclassified people.
That's why, strictly speaking, you see, Hinduism and Buddhism are not religions.
You can classify the religions. You can say, what's your denomination?
Baptist, Methodist, Catholic,
Presbyterian, Episcopalian, Quaker, etc. Etc. Etc.
You see? But strictly speaking, a vanaprasta,
a shramana, has no label. He is an
unlabeled bottle.
So in
the Time when the Buddha lived, about 600
BC,
the Hindu system had become
somewhat decadent.
It isn't altogether clear what had happened,
but it is certain that it did seem in some way to be in need
of reform.
And so there were many reasons
for this. And the Buddha, as a young man,
being basically troubled by the great problems that we're
all troubled with, the problem of suffering
and the problem of what all this universe is about,
he endeavored to follow the methods
that were then being used by people who were shramanas
or vanaprastas, forest dwellers.
And at that time, it's very apparent that the main method that
these people were using was an ascetic discipline,
starvation, very arduous
meditation practices, probably self
flagellation and things of that kind.
And it said that for seven years he practiced these austerities,
but he found out that they didn't lead
to liberation. And all the people who were practicing them knew they
didn't either. But they felt that that was only because they weren't doing it
hard enough.
And so he propounded instead the middle way,
the way that led to liberation
from the rat race that I've drawn here, neither through
austerities nor through pleasure
seeking. See, these are the two ways, the two paths.
The people who say the
whole point of life is to enjoy it, to get the most out of it,
you see, the other people who tried that and then they found it was
sour grapes or something, you know, or they burned their fingers in the pursuit of
pleasure. The girl that was so beautiful eventually fell apart or just turned into a
shrew and whatever it was.
And so they said, instead, let us
torment ourselves. A lot of people enjoy
this or get something special out of it. I was in Mexico the
summer, and what I went there for was to study Mexican Catholicism,
where they make a great cult of suffering.
And I was very puzzled about this and wanted to understand.
And everywhere, you know, they have these ghastly tormented
Christs all drooling with blood, hanging on crosses
in very contorted positions. And I realized
there are certain people who, who find that the
sitting on the tip of a spike is the realest place in the world.
Because when you're on the tip of a spike, you know, you're there.
There's no doubt about it. And also, you know,
that you're expiating for everything this
somehow by sitting on this, on the spike,
you are paying for your guilt.
And so long as you hurt, you're all right.
See? So these shamanas were doing
something of the same kind.
And The Buddha became enlightened, became a Buddha.
He woke up at the moment when he gave up
that kind of quest. The moment he gave up, as we
should say, trying to take the kingdom of heaven by storm.
Now what does this mean?
It means that in
his time,
the way of liberation had become competitive,
which meant it was on the wrong track.
There are a lot of people who we call it the holier than thou
attitude. But we find it today with some objectionable
Westerners who go over to Japan to study Zen Buddhism
and then come home and brag about the great disciplines they've undergone
and say, I sat with my legs crossed in one position for
10 hours as distinct from somebody else who only sat for 5 and
always has a tendency, you know, to have a marathon and be in a competition
with others or with oneself about these things.
But the moment you do that, you're back on the wheel.
The best thing you can get by asceticism is to get up to the Deva
world. You can't get anywhere else by it.
You may get down to the Naraka world by asceticism too.
Read the story Thais by Anatole France.
So he found, you see, that the. The real
path, the Middle way.
The meaning of the Middle Way is that it's the
path that can't be followed.
Because to get you onto the middle way,
I have to get into a dialogue with you, you see, and you say to
me, because after all, it's always the student that raises the problem,
not the teacher. You say, well, now, what's the
right thing to do? I say back to you,
why are you looking for the right thing to do?
And then you have to consider your situation where you are.
You say, well, I'm looking for the right thing
to do because I feel that I'm in the wrong situation. I don't have
peace of mind. Why do
you want peace of mind? Because my
mind is disturbed. Then in other words,
you as a disturbed mind, are trying to find peace of mind.
Your quest for peace of mind is the same thing as having a disturbed mind.
Now, if you don't have a disturbed mind, you won't ask peace of mind?
Well, how can I quiet my mind? Why are you asking to quiet your mind?
Because it's disturbed. You see where you are?
So in this way, by this dialogue, the. The guru,
the teacher, brings a person back to center.
So then this is the point. All Buddhist teaching is
a dialogue, really and truly. The man
who goes out and leaves society
and becomes in monk is
a little bit Too much Buddhism
involves this act as a preliminary
gesture. But what it
comes to in the end is the position of
what's called a bodhisattva. A bodhisattva
means somebody who went out of society or
we should say, gave up the world in some way, took on the
the robe, took on the discipline.
He found what he was looking for, but his
finding it was absolutely simultaneous with his coming
back into society.
It is called a bodhisattva, as distinct
from a Pratyaka Buddha, which means a private
Buddha, one who goes out and doesn't come back.
And the Bodhisattva is considered as having a superior attainment,
superior insight.
So the important thing to remember then is Buddhism is a
dialogue and
its teaching is a method and not a
doctrine. Now, the teaching of Buddhism
is summed up in what are called the four Noble Truths.
The truth of suffering, the truth about the origin
of suffering, the truth about the ceasing of suffering,
and the truth about the way to the ceasing of suffering.
Dukha d u h k h
a is the Sanskrit word we translate
suffering,
discord, frustration, something like
that. That's always the problem, you see.
And this because of suffering is the reason why human
beings seek out teachers and
saviors. I hurt
and I don't want to hurt. So that's the
universal problem, see that everybody brings.
So then the teacher replies to this problem by
saying,
you suffer because you crave things.
Trishna T r I s
h n a from which we get our word. First,
Trishna, craving or desire is
the cause of suffering. That's the second truth.
Now the Buddhist analyzes this. That's the
world is dukkha because full
of frustration. And it's also characterized by impermanence
and by non
entity ness.
That means that no thing exists independently.
Everything is a thing only in relation to everything else.
Therefore there are no separate things, no real selves
or souls or egos.
And trying to cling to the world which
is necessarily changing, trying to have a separate
self and to protect it, all these things are
trishna, they are the cause of dukkha.
So the teachers having said this,
then the student comes back and says, well,
how do I get rid of Krishna if
Krishna desire is the cause of suffering, couldn't I
get rid of desire so as not to suffer?
And the teacher says, well, you try.
And this then is the first part of the discipline. To try not
to desire, to calm your mind,
to practice centering, to practice getting
rid of all what they call klesha K L
E S A disturbing thoughts,
distractions, evil passions,
immoderate appetites and come to upeksha or
equanimity of mind.
And so the student practices that, that and
this is a very difficult and arduous discipline. And all the time
he sees the teacher watching him with a slightly sour expression on
his face and he knows, of course, or thinks
he knows that the teacher is fully aware
of his inmost thoughts. Because you know, it's the Indian
way. They go to meeting with the teacher and the teacher sits under
a tree and smokes a cigarette or a pipe or something and
all the students sit around cross legged and they, they meditate.
Sometimes the teacher meditates and they can see him
occasionally looking at them like this and
they think, oh, teacher knows what I'm thinking because
he has the power of infinite vision, you see, and all seeingness.
And this bugs them completely because you see,
you remember how it was in school when you were trying to do something,
the teacher walked around and looked over your shoulder. It puts
you off completely. And so the Hindu
teacher or the Buddhist teacher deliberately puts his students off
and finally he raises in their minds an insoluble problem
that if you are trying to stop desire so that you will not
suffer, aren't you still desiring to stop desire?
Or the students may very well find that out for themselves and
they say to the teacher, but how are we to stop desire when we are
desiring to stop desire?
So then the teacher can engage them in an extremely marvelous
trap,
which is to say he
can, he can play it in a number of different directions. One direction is
to say, well, don't try to stop all desire,
but try to stop as much desire as you can stop.
You see where this is going to go? Then they're
going to say, well,
I'm a little excessive about the desiring to stop desire.
Well, if you're naturally excessive about it, he says,
try to be as slightly excessive as you
can see.
Now do you see what's meeting here? If you follow
that course, you are
being brought to center in
the same way as I demonstrated before.
You're being brought to yourself to accept yourself
as you are here and now totally.
But you can't do that directly because if
you try to accept yourself, you will always find
that in yourself there is a spirit of the non acceptance
of things and you have to accept that.
So the teacher would say don't try to accept yourself
more than you can accept yourself. Accept yourself as much
as you can accept yourself because then
you see, you are also accepting the part of you that doesn't accept.
Or he may try on another tack. He may say,
all right, now, if you've seen that it's that
desiring not to desire is simply another
form of desire,
you, you're trying, for example, to get rid of your
sensuous appetites. You are
going to give up booze and women and foie
gras or whatever it may be.
You then think, well, now, yes, this I must
do.
And eventually you find that
you are becoming proud
of your success in mastering your appetites,
and you're beginning to depend on that.
So the teacher says, do you see? You're in the same trap as you
always were. Formerly you sought
spiritual security in booze and women and
so on. Now you're seeking it in holiness.
Formerly you bound yourself with chains of iron. Now you're bound
with chains of gold. Formerly you boasted to all the boys how
many sins you committed. Now you're boasting before the Lord of
how many virtues you have. Same trap.
Why do you do it? So the
student eventually finds there's no way at all to
not desire.
Even desiring not to desire is desiring.
Even trying to accept oneself is a way
of trying to escape from oneself. Because one hopes,
psychotherapeutically, that by accepting yourself you
will get rid of your nasty symptoms.
So you're not accepting them. You're not accepting them by the gimmick,
by the pretense of trying to accept them.
So this is the way.
Well, now really, when we go back then to falling in love
and say it's crazy falling,
you see, we don't say rising into love.
There is in it the idea of the fall.
And it is goes back, as a matter of fact, to extremely
fundamental, fundamental things, that there
is always a curious tie
at some point between the fall and
the creation. Taking this ghastly
risk is the
condition of there being life,
you see, for all the life is
an act of faith and an act of gamble.
The moment you take a step,
you do so on an act of faith, because you don't really know that the
floor is not going to give under your feet.
The moment you take a journey, what an act of faith.
The moment you enter into any kind of human undertaking
in relationship, what an act of faith, see,
you've given yourself up, but this
is the most powerful thing that could be done.
Surrender, see? And love is an act of surrender
to another person.
Total abandonment.
I give myself,
take you wear anything you like.
So that's quite Mad.
Because you see, it's letting things get out of control.
All sensible people keep things in control.
Watch it, watch it. Watch it.
Security, Vigilance.
Watch it. Police. Watch it. Gods, watch it.
There's better. Watch the car.
So actually, therefore,
the, the, the course of wisdom, what is really sensible
is to let go, is to commit oneself to give oneself up.
And that's quite mad. So we come to the strange conclusion that
in madness lies.
Look, will you be absolutely genuine with me?
No deception please. I want you to
do something that expresses you without the slightest
deception.
No more role acting, no more playing
games with me. I want to see you now.
Imagine, could you really
be that honest with somebody else?
Especially a spiritual teacher. And you
know, he looks right through you. He sees all
your secret thoughts. And he knows the very second
when you've been a little bit phony.
And that bugs you. In other words,
when you're challenged to be perfectly genuine.
It's like saying to a child, now darling, come out here
and play and don't be self conscious.
Or it's like I would say to you, now look, if you come here tonight
at exactly midnight and put your hands on this stage,
you can wish and have granted any wish you want in provided
you don't think of a green elephant.
And so everybody will come, they'll put their hands here and they will
be very careful not to think about a green elephant.
Well, now do you see the point that
everybody, if we transfer this to the dimension of,
of spirituality where the highest ideal is
to be unselfish,
to let go of oneself.
When you are trying to be unselfish,
you're doing it for a selfish reason.
You can't be unselfish by a decision of the
will anymore. Then you can decide not to think of a green
elephant. There is a story about
Confucius who one day met Lao
Tzu, who was a great Chinese philosopher.
And Lao Tzu said, sir, what is your system?
And Confucius said, it is charity and love
of one's neighbor and elimination of self interest.
Lao Tzu said, stuff and nonsense.
Your elimination of self is
a positive manifestation of self.
Look at the universe. The stars keep their
order. The trees and plants
grow upwards without exception. The waters flow
the like. This all your nonsense about
elimination of self is like beating a drum in search of a
fugitive. So in this way
these are all examples of the thing that trickery the
master is playing on you.
You came to him with the idea in your mind that
you are a separate, independent,
isolated individual. And what he is Simply saying to
you is, show me this individual.
So after a while you see what happens is this.
When the student finds that there is absolutely
no way of being his
true self,
not only is there no way of doing it,
there is also no way of doing it. By not doing it,
you can't do it by doing something. You can't do it by not doing
something. So in this way,
what is called the Zen problem or koan is
likened to a person who swallowed a
ball of red hot iron. He can't
gulp it down and he can't spit it out.
Or it's like a mosquito biting an iron bull.
It's the nature of a mosquito to bite,
and it's the nature of an iron bull to be unbitable,
and both go on doing their thing. That is their nature.
And so nothing can happen.
Absolutely, you're up against it.
Absolutely no answer to this problem.
No way out. Now, what does that mean?
If I can't do the right thing by doing,
and if I can't do the right thing by not doing, what does it mean?
It means, of course,
that I, who essayed to do all this,
am a hallucination.
There is no independent self to
be produced. There is no way
at all of showing it,
because it isn't there.
So you recover from the illusion. You suddenly wake
up and think,
what a relief. And they call that satori.
That's awakening, the first step in awakening.
Let me try and translate this.
When this kind of experience happens, you discover
that what you are is
no longer this sort of isolated
center of action and experience locked up
in your skin.
The teacher has asked you to produce that thing.
So in the same way, when your own inner sense of identity
changes from being the separate individual
to being what the entire cosmos
is doing at this place,
you become not a puppet,
but more truly and more expressively an individual
than ever. There is a Chinese
proverb that if the wrong man uses the right
means, the right means work in the wrong way.
Let us assume that our technological knowledge
is the right means. What kind of people
are going to use this knowledge? Are they going to be people who hate nature
and feel alienated from it,
or people who love the physical world and
feel that the physical world is their own personal
body?
But you see this whole attitude of using technology as
a method of fighting the world will
succeed only in destroying the world.