This is a point of view which is successful
to a certain degree.
It goes well up to a certain level, after which it begins
to develop complications.
As I think it over, it seems to me that the high civilizations of
the world have produced exactly three
different views of the constitution of nature,
of the physical universe.
And to enumerate them, I would call them, respectively,
nature as a construct, nature as a drama,
and nature as an organism.
The first view, nature as a construct, has, until very
recently, been characteristic of the Western world.
The view of nature as a drama has been largely
characteristic of India. And finally
of nature as an organism has been
characteristic of the Far East.
I'd like to compare these three views and point
out certain
of their advantages, disadvantages, and the
ways in which they complement each other.
And I think part of the interest of this is that our thinking,
more and more I've been fascinated by this, that our thinking
about the world is strongly
influenced by analogies,
by sometimes analogies that are almost hidden.
They're so far back in the history of the
thought of any given civilization or culture that
they are taken as something more than analogies. They're taken
almost, you could say, as logical patterns.
And they are basic to our grammar, to our common
sense, and to our attitudes in
ways that often go unsuspected.
Why don't we start with the Western view of the world
as a construct? By this
I mean the physical world has
historically in the west been looked upon as a
created or manufactured article,
the work of a creator external to the world.
And this view has continued in many ways even
after the rise of deism in the 18th century and the general tendency
of the scientists to dispense with the
hypothesis of the Creator.
The idea still remains that the world is
a construct analogous to a
machine. And indeed, obeying laws
or plans in the same way as a machine obeys a
blueprint. Even though the
lawgiver and the planner himself seems to have disappeared.
The basic metaphor, though underlying this, is not so
much the machine as the.
The work of clay, the pot, or the sculpture
of the modeled figure.
For as you know, it is said in the book of Genesis that the Lord
God created Adam out of the dust of the ground and breathed
the breath of life into his nostrils.
And so our language, our poetry, is full of
allusions to the
fact that we are really, after all, clay imperial
Caesar, dead and turned to clay, might stop a hole
to keep the wind away.
And because of this figure,
it is, as I have often said,
fundamental to our common sense. That the world
is formed, matter the
form being the shape of the part, the matter being the clay.
And thus we think of life as being basically
something done to a medium. The medium
is stuff, a kind of formless and
of itself inert and unintelligent goo,
which requires an external agency
to give it form and intelligence and life.
And naturally, because we have thought this way for so long,
it's a terribly difficult idea to abandon, to get out of our heads
the notion that in
the same way that tables are made of wood and houses of stone,
so we tend to think that trees are made
of wood and mountains of stone and people
of flesh, and all of it eventually reducing itself
to the primordial goo,
the universal clay, the primal matter,
the formless original
water over which the spirit of God is said to have moved
in the beginning of all time.
Now, beyond the idea
of the the world as a
work of pottery lies the more sophisticated idea
of the world as a mechanism. In this Western
view of the world as a construct,
as soon as men began to understand mechanical
principles, it became extraordinarily convenient
to make analogies between various
types of machinery and
things to be found in the world. And it is really
upon this analogy that the great achievements of
Western technology have hitherto been based.
And it's really very difficult to think that we
could have devised our technology and that our practical
sciences could have made such progress without
the idea of the analogy between the world and a
constructed machine.
You see, one of the most fundamental things
about a machine is that it is an assemblage of parts.
And the successful measurement and
description of nature depends
upon the calculus, upon reducing it to parts. You know,
the word calculus originally meant pebbles.
And pebbles were one of the oldest methods of calculating,
counting pebbles in a funny
kind of association of words.
Calculus is also calculating
in the sense of having a calculating attitude.
Scheming.
And scheming is associated with. With turning things to
calculi or stones.
It is a sort of killing
the world, reducing it from the living to the dead,
from the organism to the machine. But nevertheless,
it has had the most marvelous consequences so far as we are concerned.
And the cultures which thought of nature by analogy with drama and
by analogy with organism, did not produce the
technology that we in the west produced. Let me just
for a moment contrast the other attitudes.
The Indian attitude of the world is a drama.
In Hindu thought, the world is not thought of as
being made or constructed by God,
but as being actually God himself playing
a game. The idea
of one single divine actor
who is playing all the parts of all
the creatures in the world imagining himself to be them,
assuming as it were myriads of masks
behind which there is simply one wearer of the
mask.
In a forthcoming book,
the second volume of the Masks of God, it's not published yet, but I've just
seen a copy, Joseph Campbell contrasts
the way in which the myth of the one who became
two, the one that became many,
has gone in two quite different directions.
Beginning in ancient Sumeria,
which constitutes, as it were, a sort of cultural watershed,
it has flowed eastwards in one way and westwards in another
to the east. The idea that the One,
the Godhead, in other words, split itself and
dismembered itself into many parts quite voluntarily, and thus became
the world as a play to
the West. The theme of the one who became many
is different because, as he points out in the Book of Genesis,
it is not the divine who becomes male
and female, it is the creature. In the Upanishads,
say the Brihad Dharanyaka Upanishad,
the divine self,
is described as a saying
in the beginning of time, let me become two. And he splits into male
and female, and thus generates the world. But in the Book of
Genesis, it is not the Godhead who splits,
it is man, the creature who is split into Adam
and then into Eve.
But thus, in the eastern world, we have the dramatic
view. In India in particular. And although
it's interesting to note that in, say, in the writings
of the great philosopher Shankara
and others, you very often encounter the analogy of the potter
or of pots as representing the world, the roles
are reversed.
The it is the clay is used as the
symbol for the divine reality.
Just as pots are all made of clay, or as
jewels are all made of gold, so all
things in the world are of one divine substance, which is of the nature
of the Godhead or Brahman. It's interesting,
the different use of the simile.
And so from the standpoint of the dramatic
view of the universe,
all the divisions and distinctions of the world are looked
upon as being a kind of. As if
they are in play, they are not quite serious.
And this contrasts very sharply with
what has been the characteristic Western view that the distinctions in
the world are the most important things about it,
that they are deeply serious. The distinction
of good and evil is an eternal distinction, as is the
distinction between the Creator and the creature.
The world, in this view, is not a drama.
It is played not by actors,
but by what we call real individuals,
even real persons, although, funnily enough, as I
suppose you know, the word person is originally Persona,
the megaphone mask worn by actors
in classical Greek drama.
Then thirdly, there is the organic view characteristic
of China.
In this, there is no real thought of there
being a divine creator or a divine actor behind
the world, but rather the world is
thought of as being self moving
and self creating. The word for
nature in Chinese means what is of itself.
So when
in the West a child asks its mother,
who made me? And she replies,
darling, God made you. And the child asks, but who
made God? She has to say, nobody made God.
And that is a great puzzle to the child who thinks
of the world as a construction.
And it may be explained to
the child, if you like, that God makes himself.
He exists of himself because he is existence.
To put it in more theological language,
he has the attribute called aseity,
from the Latin assay. By himself.
Perhaps some kind of infant terrible would
ask the question, well, if that's true of God,
why couldn't it be true of the world in the first place? Why did
you have to make that additional step? If he did so,
he would be thinking more or less in the Chinese way,
which does not think of the world either as an
artifact or of some maker, or as a mask
or appearance worn by some sort of deeper
reality. He doesn't, in other words,
have a two level view
of nature as an appearance, underneath which
there is something else to explain it.
He sees it all rather as self evident,
as being something which regulates itself
and indeed orders itself.
There is a certain sense, you see, in which the Chinese view
is fundamentally, or you could almost call it anarchical,
or if you don't like that word, you could call it democratic.
A world which is self governing,
not even through a president,
but self governing in every way. A great and colossal
anarchism which
moves itself in the same way as you and
I move our fingers,
without directing them in the sense that we know exactly what
we're doing and how we move them, we don't.
Now, I've said that the
Western view is probably what
made it possible for us to develop
our highly advanced technology.
By thinking about the world as a construction,
we could think about the laws or principles
or plans or regularities upon
which it was based.
We could think, for example, of the calculus of number
as the basic
characteristic of the law upon
which nature is based.
By doing that, we caught onto the idea of thinking
of all things as reducible to atoms,
to parts, to bits.
And then by thinking of bits, we found that
we could measure the world very accurately,
describe its regularities very accurately.
And that gave us an astonishing degree of control over it.
But this is a point of view which is successful
to a certain degree.
It goes well up to a certain level. After which it begins
to develop complications.
For one thing, you could say it has complications. Which are psychological
on the one hand. And practical and technical on another.
From the psychological point of view,
its complication is that when it becomes
commonsensical to us to look at the world as a mechanism.
We begin as humans, as people
capable of feeling and love. To feel the external
world rather alien to us.
Yes, it's a machine.
It's a great big automatic
mechanical arrangement.
Which in essence is simply stupid
energy.
We thereupon feel that it has nothing in common
with ourselves. And perhaps even
though we try to give the same sort of account of
ourselves. And try to reduce our brains and emotions
to some kind of neurological computer mechanism.
That makes us, in a way, hate ourselves.
For as soon as we start thinking of ourselves as automata.
We begin ethically and psychologically
treating ourselves as automata. We lose respect for ourselves.
And thereupon feel
that what is central to us.
The feeling center, the person,
is trapped in a cosmos.
That is a mechanical nightmare,
foreign and strange.
We can see ourselves as a kind of ghastly accident.
And I don't wonder that this engenders.
Certain kinds of suicidal tendencies in our culture.
So much for the psychological point of view. From the technical point of view,
the analogy of nature with mechanism.
Develops its own disadvantages. After a certain point.
That is to say, the disadvantage of trying to
manage the physical universe. As if it were indeed
an assemblage of separate parts or
separable parts. For the first sort
of person to notice this mistake. Would be the
extreme surgical or medical specialist.
Who knows, for example, all about hearts
or about stomachs. But very little about brains or lungs
or glands. And who treats
one organ at a time. And becomes unaware of the imbalances
inflicted upon other organs. By what he's done to the organ in
which he specializes.
Also, in the same way, the specialist
always tends to
see the units of nature. And to be unaware
of their connections or relations. Relationships which
are, after all, inseparable relationships with all the other parts.
There is, you might say, also another technical disadvantage,
again. Which develops only in the course of time. To this
particular mechanical analogy.
And that is that when you
begin to rely more and
more.
Upon minute
and careful description of the world for
dealing with it. And that, of course, involves the reduction of the world to
describable units.
The world then becomes terribly complicated.
And it becomes increasingly difficult to keep track of
all the minute units that, that you've described.
Hence the difficulty of specialists in the various sciences communicating with
each other, and the difficulty of the scientific specialist in
communicating with the layman. The whole thing becomes
much too complicated to manage.
And this then means that the
more we know, the greater our skill
in managing the world as a mechanical
construct, the more
difficult it becomes to control, because it becomes
increasingly complex. We talk endlessly about the
increasing complexity of political,
social and economic affairs which
makes the problems of the world increasingly unintelligible
to even the average well educated citizen.
Now, it has been suggested that
the Western view,
nature as a construct, has in some ways done
its job,
and that from here on we need to
explore to a greater degree other
views. Perhaps the organic view of the Chinese,
wherein we
get a peculiar harmony of points of view with
our own sciences, biology, ecology and so
forth, as if somehow
this view had been tucked away in
a store cupboard, waiting for us
to be available at just the time when we
needed it.
The problem here is an entirely new one,
because we are so used to thinking of our problems
of controlling and understanding the world in
terms of the methods of mechanical science.
Not so long ago,
I was talking to Lynn White,
who used to be president of Mills College,
and he was saying that our academic world
values only three kinds of intelligence,
whereas he said there are many more. There are at least seven.
I don't remember what all the seven were, but he said the kinds
of intelligence that we value are first of all mnemonic,
which is the ability to remember,
computational intelligence, the ability to figure,
and verbal intelligence, the ability to read,
write and talk. But he said there is also social intelligence,
and there is also kinesthetic intelligence,
kind of intelligence, kinesthetic, in which we learn as
children to walk, to run, to throw and catch balls,
and to do all kinds of extremely complex and
very subtle actions without being able to describe
or count what we're doing.
Perhaps in handling far more complex
matters than catching balls or
skiing or riding bicycles,
we may have unknown resources of kinesthetic intelligence
for dealing with some of the problems that now face us.
Here is the germ of an idea which
Chinese culture and Far Eastern culture in general
suggest to us. Perhaps they themselves
have only dimly begun to explore these things.
But I think that it's in that direction that
the future of practical philosophy and government
of the world may lie.
Well, now, there are, as I said in the history of mankind,
three theories of nature. The first theory
is the Western theory, which is that nature
is a machine or an artifact.
We inherit this from the Hebrews,
who believed that nature was made
by God in somewhat the same way as a
potter makes a pot out of clay or a
carpenter makes a table out of wood.
It is not insignificant that Jesus is the son
of the carpenter.
Our tradition has been to look upon the
world as a construct.
And somebody knows how it was put together.
Somebody understands, and that is the
constructor, the architect, the Lord God.
But it so happened that in the 18th century,
Western thought began to change. They became
increasingly doubtful as to whether there was a
maker, whether there was a God.
But they continued to look upon the creation as an
artifact, as a machine.
And by the time of Newton,
people were explaining the world in terms of
mechanism. And we are still under the
influence of that idea. Because, after all, in things like Life magazine
and so on, when they give you an article
on human physiology,
they usually make drawings which show
the human being as a kind of mechanism,
as a sort of factory. And they show how the
peristaltic action carries the food in and how it's processed
by this organ and that organ as just as if a certain
product is fed into a factory cow at one end and it comes out canned
corned beef at the other. Just in such
a way the human is illustrated. And so too,
in some kinds of rather degraded medicine
that is now practiced. When you go to the hospital
for a medical examination, you are treated as a machine.
They process you. You're not a person. You are
put in a wheelchair immediately. Even if you look
perfectly healthy and can walk, nevertheless, they have to have you in this wheelchair,
and they put you through a process. And the heart specialist
looks only at your heart because he can't understand anything else. The Oto
rhino laryngologist, which. Which means an ear, nose and throat man,
looks at that section of you, and he doesn't know about anything else.
And maybe a psychiatrist takes a look at you, and goodness
knows what happens there, and so on and so on. Everybody looks at you from
their specialized point of view as if they were a bunch of mechanics examining
your automobile. Because, as I said
last night, we just asked for this
because most of us consider ourselves as chauffeurs
inside our bodies, which we own in the same way as you
own a car, and when it goes wrong, you take it to the mechanic to
fix it. You don't really identify
with your body, just as you don't really identify with your car.
So here is this whole theory of nature which has grown
up in the west as an artifact,
something made. Now,
let Me take a second theory of nature. This is an Indian theory,
East Indian nature,
not as an artifact, but as drama.
Basic to all Hindu thought is the idea that the world is
Maya. That is a Sanskrit word which
means many things. It means magic,
illusion, art,
play. All the world's a stage.
And in the Hindu idea there is the ultimate reality of
the universe is the Self, which they
call Brahman or Atman.
That's what there is, the Self,
Universal, eternal, boundless,
indescribable. And everything
that happens, happens on the self. Like you say,
it's on me. The drinks tonight are on me.
Or like we say, when you hear the radio,
it's on the speaker. You see everything you
hear on the radio.
Flutes, drums, human voices,
traffic noises, any imaginable sound.
All those sounds are vibrations of the diaphragm in the speaker.
But the radio doesn't tell you that.
The announcer doesn't come on and say every morning,
good morning, ladies and gentlemen, this is kqed.
The following sounds that you are going to hear are vibrations of
your the diaphragm in your speaker. And they're not
really human voices or musical
instruments, but just that, they never let you in on that.
And in exactly the same way the universe doesn't
let you in on the truth that all sense
experiences are vibrations
of the self, not just
yourself, but the self. And all of us
share this self in common because. Because it is pretending
to be all of us.
Brahman, the ultimate principle,
plays hide and seek eternally.
And he does it for unspeakably long periods of time. The Hindus measure
time in what is called a Kalpa K, a LPA.
That's 4,320,000 years.
Don't take this seriously. It's not meant to be taken literally,
but just for an unspeakably long time. The Brahman,
the self, pretends that it's lost and
is us. And all our adventures and all our troubles
and all our agonies and tragedies, it gets mixed up in them.
Then, after the period of 4,320,000 years has elapsed,
there is a catastrophe. The universe
is destroyed in fire. And after
that, the Brahmin wakes up and says,
well, good crazy. What, what an adventure that
was. He wipes the sweat off his brow and says,
let's rest a while. So for another 4,000,320 000
years, the Divine self rests and knows who it is.
It's me. Then it says, well,
this is rather boring. Let's get going again. Let's get mixed
up. And it does it in a very strange way because
the way the Hindus time it, the first period of
getting mixed up, getting lost, is beautiful. That's the
longest period. Everything's right,
it's just life is glorious. Then it has the next period in which
things get a little wonky. Something is vaguely
out of order that doesn't last so long.
Then the next period, the third, is when good and evil
are equally balanced.
And that's still not so long. Finally comes the
shortest period when everything bad triumphs and
the whole thing blows up and we begin all over again.
We're supposed to be living in that now. It's what's
called the Kali Yuga, the Age of
Darkness. And it began on Friday, February 23,
3123 BC and it
has 5,000 years to run.
But as it goes on, time gets faster, so don't worry.
So you see, that's a theory of nature as a drama,
it's a play. Now, there's a third theory
of nature which is Chinese,
and this is very interesting.
The Chinese word for nature they
call zhang.
And this expression means of itself.
So what happens of
itself? Or we might say
spontaneity. It almost means
automatic, because automatic is what is self moving.
Only we associate the word automatic with machinery.
But what is
of so of itself is associated in the Chinese mind not with
machinery, but with biology.
Your hair grows by itself, you don't have to
think how to grow it. Your heart beats by itself.
You don't have to make up your mind how to beat it.
That's what they mean by nature. The poem
says, sitting quietly, doing nothing. Spring comes
and grass grows of itself.
So their principle of nature is called a dao.
Tao pronounced dao in the Mandarin
dialect, Tao in the Shanghai dialect,
to in the Cantonese dialect. Take your choice.
Dao means the course of nature.
And Lao Tzu, who was a philosopher who
lived little later than 400 B.C.
wrote a book about the dao. And he said the dao
which can be spoken is not the eternal dao.
You can't describe it. He said,
the principle of the dao is spontaneity.
He said, the great Dao flows everywhere, both to the
left and to the right. It loves and nourishes all things,
but does not lord it over them. It accomplishes merits
and lays no claim to them.
So there is a very great difference between the Chinese
idea of dao as the informing
principle of nature and the Judeo Christian
idea of God as nature's lord
and master. Because the Dao
does not act as a boss.
In the Chinese philosophy of nature, nature has
no boss.
There is no principle
that forces things to behave the way they do. It is
a comparison completely democratic theory of nature.
Do you mind if I talk for a while about something I love
about water and the ocean? Ever since
I can remember anything at all, the light,
the smell, the sound and motion of the sea has
been pure magic.
Even the mere intimation of its perfect gulls
flying a little way inland,
the quality of light in the sky beyond, hills which
screen it from view, the lowing of
fog horns in the night. If ever I have to get away from it
all, and in the words of a Chinese
poet, wash all the rungs of life from my pores,
there's simply nothing better. And to climb out onto a
rock and sit for hours with nothing in sight but sea and
sky. Although the rhythm of the waves beats
a kind of time, it's not clock or calendar
time. It has no urgency. It's timeless
time. Because I
know I'm listening to a rhythm which has been
just the same for millions of years.
And it takes you out of the world of relentlessly ticking clocks.
Clocks, for some reason or other, always seem to be marching.
And armies never march to anything but doom.
But there's no marching rhythm. Motion waves.
It harmonizes with the breath.
It does not count our days.
Its pulse is not in the stingy
spirit of measuring, of marking out how much still remains.
It's the breathing of eternity.
Especially early in the morning and towards evening,
when the distinction of sky and water becomes uncertain,
when the whole of space becomes opalescent, the sort
of pearly lips luminous grey. And the rising or setting
moon, this straw yellow,
blessed with the white cries of gulls
and with the patterns of masts and ropes and boats at
anchor, which put me in
mine with landfills gone that way,
and of all the voyages of which one is dream.
But under the surface of both sky and water,
there's the grim business.
Men and birds against fish, fish against fish,
the tortuous process of life continuing by
the painful transformation of one form into another.
To preachers who don't anticipate and
reflect imaginatively upon this holocaust of
eating and being eaten, it's perhaps not so terrible.
But poor man skillful
beyond all other animals. By being able to sink in
time and knowing the future, he dies before
he's dead. He shrinks from the shark's teeth before they bite
him. He dreads
the alien germ long, long before its banquet
begins. Here is a Gull
that has picked a crab from a tide pool.
Sprawled now upon the sand, the crab
shrinks from the walls of its shell, resounding to
the tap, tap, tap of the gull's beak.
Who's that knocking at my door? I suppose the
shell of the crab, the clam or the muttle
is the boundary of its universe.
To put ourselves in their position, we should have to imagine a knocking sound,
louder and louder, that doesn't come from anywhere in particular
from the door or the walls or the ceiling or the floor.
Think of a knocking that comes from everywhere,
that beats against the boundaries of space and consciousness,
that comes as the intrusion of an utterly unknown
dimension into our own familiar world.
Let me in. Let me in.
Surrender to this agony and you will be
transformed into me. Dying to yourself.
You will become alive as me. There's no way of getting
around it is that the gull isn't
rapacious or greedy. It's just that he's being alive at
all is the same thing as eating crabs.
Sea birds are transformations of fish. Men are transformations of
wheat, chickens and steers.
To object to this inseparability of pleasure and
pain, life and death,
is simply to object to existence. But of course,
we cannot help objecting when the time comes.
Objecting to pain is pain,
so far as we know. The gull and the fish don't philosophize.
They enjoy life when they're eating it and hate it when being eaten.
They don't reflect upon the process as a whole and say how rough it
is that we have to work so hard for a living. Or it's
just hell having to watch out all the time for those girls.
I'm sure that in their world this is something that just goes along with life,
like having eyes or feet. But man,
with his astonishing ability to stand aside from him himself and think
about himself. In short, to comment
on life. Man has done something which confuses his own
existence down to its roots.
Perhaps the ghastly mistake was just that
step in man's evolution which made it possible
for him to comment, to reflect upon life as a whole.
In being able to stand aside from life and think
about it, he put himself outside it and found
it alien.
Perhaps thinking about the world and objecting to
its whole principle are simply two aspects of the same mechanism.
But aren't there also times when we
speak of something that we know as a subject,
the subject of this book, the subject I am now studying?
Would it be possible to subject to life instead of objecting
to it? Now,
if the Gals and the fish don't philosophize.
They have no consciousness of life being either good as a whole or bad
as a whole. So when we philosophize
and pity the poor fish, that's just our problem.
From its own standpoint,
the world of animals and insects doesn't find itself
problematic at all.
There's not the slightest evidence to suggest it.
I'm quite sure they don't lecture each other about their duties.
Or worry about where they're going when they're dead.
Isn't it then, rather an enormous
relief for us men to see that the
plant and animal world is no problem to itself.
And that we are wasting intellectual energy in making
moral judgments about it? We seem
to feel that the thing which
knows, that it knows is one's essential self.
Our personal identity is
entirely on the side of the commentator.
I think our difficulty is that our consciousness
is too superficial. As if all our sensation were
in the tips of the fingers and not in the palm.
Are we misled by the fact that we move freely on
the earth. And aren't rooted to it in the
same way as trees to the ground, ground and fingers to the hand?
Now we know that the atom, molecule,
cell of any particular organism is what it
is by virtue of its place and
its membership in the pattern of the whole.
So I think this is why I love the ocean.
It's the most difficult part
of nature to mess up with
emblems,
symptoms of man's dissociated consciousness.
It's an environment in
which the awareness of our roots can awaken.
In which space, so real because
of the light and picture color, can be seen to
be joining things instead of separating.
And I've just discovered that that
knocking on the wall of space and consciousness.
Was my own feeling.
Sa foreign.
Let's consider the power of holding your deepest aspirations close
to your heart. There's something almost sacred in
the things we dream of and long for. Aspirations aren't
just wishes. They're reflections of the core of who we are and who
we yearn to be. They're not defined by anyone else's
vision of success or happiness. They are intimate parts
of our inner worlds. Shaped by our unique experiences,
values and the depths of our imagination.
When you keep those aspirations protected, you create a
space that is entirely yours, untouched by
the expectations or judgments of others. This isn't
about secrecy. It's about preserving the purity of something
that's deeply personal.
Imagine a delicate plant that needs the right conditions
to grow. Too much exposure, too much handling.
And it doesn't thrive.
Similarly, sharing our dreams too openly can sometimes expose
them to influences that pull us away from their true essence.
Sometimes, well meaning people can't help but impose their own fears
or limitations onto what you're trying to create.
Maybe they don't see your vision as clearly as you do.
Or perhaps they don't understand the journey you're on. They might
suggest safer routes, smaller goals,
or more predictable outcomes because they're looking at it through their own
lens, not yours. Their input, though often loving,
can create clouds around your vision, making it
harder for you to see where you truly want to go.
There's a delicate strength in letting your aspirations live in this
quiet space within yourself. When you don't feel pressured to
explain them, defend them, or justify them, you have more freedom to
explore them fully, to play with them, and to see where
they lead without interference. You are not constantly
having to reframe your dreams to fit someone else's understanding
in. Instead, you're creating them according to your own truth.
This inner freedom, this privacy,
lets your aspirations grow more authentically without
bending to outside opinions or expectations.
And here's another thing. There's incredible power in mystery when
you keep a dream or goal private. It has room to develop and
develop and evolve without the weight of outside science scrutiny.
You can experiment, make mistakes, and grow in ways that might
not make sense to others, but are perfectly right for you. Right for you?
By giving yourself this space, you're less likely to be swayed
or discouraged by outside opinions because the dream belongs to
you, and only you fully understand its purpose and importance.
It's like nurturing a hidden spark. You tend
to it carefully, knowing that in time, it will become a fire
all its own, bright enough to stand on its own without anyone else's
validation. By keeping your aspirations
close, you're also choosing where to invest your energy.
Sometimes the act of explaining your dreams or defending them
to others can drain you. This energy is better
spent fueling the journey itself, taking steps,
learning, adjusting and growing.
Imagine carrying a precious treasure. You wouldn't stop every
few steps to show it off. You'd keep moving,
focused on the journey itself, knowing that you're headed
somewhere significant. By holding back
from sharing, you keep your energy intact,
fully available for the road ahead.
And perhaps most importantly, by holding your aspirations close,
you give yourself the gift of adaptability.
If you share a dream too early, it can start to feel set
in stone, almost as though you're locked into that version of it.
But when it's just between you and yourself, it can shift and
Change, you are free to adjust it as you learn more
about yourself, as you encounter new experiences,
as you discover new possibilities. This flexibility
is essential because life is constantly evolving and so are we.
What felt right at one point may need adjustment as we grow and
change. And by keeping your aspirations close, you allow
them to be living, breathing things rather than fixed destinations.
In this way, your aspirations become a source of strength,
A quiet but powerful force that guides you forward.
They're like a compass, one that points you toward your true north.
And every time you make a choice that honors that inner direction,
that supports that quiet dream, you're reinforcing
a foundation of trust within yourself.
You're saying, I trust myself to know what's right for me.
I trust myself to go at my own pace, to make my own decisions,
and to create a path that true to who I am.
Keeping your aspirations private isn't about isolation.
It's about nurturing a sense of independence and inner
peace that doesn't rely on external approval.
When the time comes and you feel ready to share,
your aspirations will be so deeply rooted that they won't be
easily shaken by the winds of opinion.
There'll be a part of you fully formed, able to
stand strong in the light of day. But until then,
you hold them close, allowing them the space to grow and unfold naturally,
free from the weight of others expectations.
In the end, the choice to keep our deepest aspirations
close is a choice to honor ourselves, to cultivate a
life guided by inner truth. It's a reminder that
not everything has to be shared to be real or validated, to be worthy.
Sometimes the most powerful journeys are the ones we take quietly,
with a sense of reverence for the unique path we're on.
And when we allow ourselves this space, we come to realize that
our dreams are not defined by others perceptions or expectations.
They are shaped by our own courage, commitment and
clarity. So hold your dreams close.
Let them grow undisturbed. When the time comes, they'll be
ready to shine in a way that is authentic and unshakable.
Until then, keep nurturing that spark, knowing that you
are on a path of your own making. One that will lead
you exactly where you're meant to go.
Let's talk about the value of keeping some of our vulnerabilities
to ourselves. Now when I say vulnerabilities,
I don't mean hiding away parts of who we are or pretending
that we're something we're not.
Vulnerabilities are the tender places within us,
the parts of ourselves that are sensitive to the world and because
of that, they deserve care, attention. These are
the things that might evoke a strong emotional reaction if exposed
too openly. Our doubts, our fears, our uncertainties.
These are the parts that, when shared too freely,
can sometimes lead to misunderstandings, misjudgment, or even misuse.
We live in a world that tells us to share, to be open,
to let others in. And in many ways,
that's a beautiful thing. Connection and openness are
what make us human. But there's also a quiet wisdom in
understanding that not everything within us needs to be put on display,
that some things are more precious when kept within a sacred,
private space. Our vulnerabilities,
in particular, benefit from this kind of protection.
Not because we're ashamed of them, but because they are still
in the process of being understood by us.
You see, there's a period in which our vulnerabilities need to
mature, in which we need to fully understand them
before we can reveal them to the world in a way that's constructive,
rather than exposing them in a way that leaves us feeling shaken or uncertain.
It's a bit like tending a young plant when
it's still delicate. It needs shelter and protection, a safe
place to grow stronger roots. If we take that plant
and expose it to harsh winds and conditions too soon,
it might not survive. In the same
way, exposing our vulnerabilities too early
or too openly can leave us feeling more fragile,
less sure of ourselves, as though we've given away a part of our
foundation before it was strong enough to stand on its own.
Now, when we hold certain vulnerabilities close, we're creating a
kind of inner sanctuary. A place where we can process,
reflect and understand ourselves. We give ourselves
chance to sit with those parts of ourselves, to explore them
without needing to explain or justify them to anyone else.
It's in this quiet space that we begin to understand what
those vulnerabilities mean to us. Where they come
from and how they shape us.
Are they reflections of past wounds? Or perhaps of a longing
we haven't fully embraced? When we take the
time to sit with our vulnerabilities, they begin to reveal
their true nature. And we come to see them not as
weaknesses, but as sources of strength. As parts of
our humanity that connect us to others on a deeper
level. The irony, of course,
is that when we keep our vulnerabilities close,
we often strengthen our connections with others rather than weakening them.
When we don't feel the need to share every tender part of our ourselves immediately,
we create a foundation of inner confidence.
And that confidence allows us to engage with others more freely
without seeking validation or reassurance.
We are not looking to others to make us feel whole, because we
are doing the work within ourselves, holding space for our own
growth, our own understanding. This self
reliance doesn't mean we are isolated or, or closed off.
It simply means that we're able to engage with others from a
place of wholeness, of quiet strength.
There's also a kind of peace that comes with knowing that some things
are ours alone. When we accept that we don't have
to reveal everything about ourselves, we experience a freedom
from the pressure to perform, to seek approval,
to seek approval, to scow a version of our.
And when we have strong boundaries, we're able to offer more of ourselves,
more of our presence to the world. Because we're not giving
away our essence in ways that leave us feeling depleted.
Over time, as our understanding of our vulnerabilities deepens,
we may choose to share them. But by then, they're no longer
fragile parts of us. They're integrated aspects
of our experience, parts of our story that we share with strength and clarity.
We're no longer sharing from a place of needing reassurance.
Instead, we're sharing as a gift, an offering that
may resonate with others and invite connection.
But until that time, we nurture our vulnerabilities,
knowing that they don't need to be seen to be real. They don't need to
be spoken to be valuable. They simply need our care
and understanding. So let your vulnerabilities
remain close. Keep them as quiet guides, as companions on
your journey. Know that they are precious not
because they're hidden, but because they remind you of
your humanity. They remind you that you're on
a path of self discovery, one that honors
both your strengths and your tender places.
And as you walk this path, remember. Remember that your vulnerabilities
are not weaknesses to be fixed. They are pieces of your wholeness,
Parts of the beautiful intricate mosaic that makes
you who you are in the end. By holding
space for our own vulnerabilities, we give ourselves a gift
far greater than validation. We give
ourselves the gift of self trust, of inner peace.
We allow ourselves to be whole, complex and wonderfully human.
And that is a strength that needs no audience, no approval.
It is simply enough. Let's take a moment
to talk about intuition and instinct. Those deep, often quiet
voices within us that don't speak in words, but are knowing.
Now, we might think that intuition is just about following a
sudden hunch or listening to a gut feeling. And sometimes it.
It is. But it's also about something far subtler.
Intuition is the wisdom that arises from a place beyond the
mind, a place untouched by analysis or logic.
It's not about figuring things out. Rather, it's about recognizing what
we know on a level that can't always be explained.
The difficulty for many of us is that we've been taught to
distrust this kind of knowing, to dismiss it as unreliable
or even naive. We're trained, after all,
to live in a world that values evidence, logic,
reasoning. And while these are useful tools,
they're not the only tools we have. They're just louder.
They take up more space in our minds.
But there's a quiet strength in listening to what the heart or the gut
tells us, in tuning into the messages that can only be felt, not explained.
Think about the times in your life when you just knew something was off
or when you felt an unexplainable pull toward a certain direction.
That's intuition. It doesn't ask for proof.
It simply tells us this is the way. The reason
intuition is so often undervalued is that it doesn't
conform to our need for certainty. The mind craves
answers, conclusions, a way to wrap everything up in a neat
package. But intuition doesn't work like
that. It speaks in shades, in impressions, in feelings
that are often ambiguous. It's more like a compass
than a map. It points us in a direction without showing
us every step along the way. And that ambiguity,
that inability to know in a concrete sense, can be uncomfortable.
But life itself is full of uncertainty. In embracing
our intuition, we're learning to navigate life without
needing to control every outcome, to trust that even if
we don't have all the answers, we can still find our way.
Now, how does this connect to the idea of self reliance?
Well, when we lean on our intuition, we're practicing a
form of inner trust. We're telling ourselves, I don't
need to look outside of myself for every answer.
There's something profoundly empowering in that.
It means we're no longer waiting for external validation,
for someone else to tell us that we're on the right track.
Instead, we turn inward, we listen, and we learn
to rely on what we feel rather than on what we think we should
do. This shift from external guidance
to inner trust is transformative. It's what allows us
to stand strong even when others around us
might question or doubt our path. Because ultimately
it's our path and only we can walk it.
When we talk about trusting intuition, it doesn't mean we reject rational
thought or dismiss the value of reason.
Intuition and logic can coexist beautifully.
Logic helps us navigate the physical,
tangible aspects of our lives, while intuition guides
us in a more subtle realm. It shows us things
logic cannot, like where our true passions lie or what might
bring us a sense of peace. Often,
intuition is that feeling of resonance when something just feels right,
even if we can't explain why. It's an alignment,
a moment when everything clicks into place and we recognize
that we're exactly where we need need to be.
But here's the thing about intuition. It requires stillness
In a world full of noise, distraction and constant information.
Listening to that inner voice means quieting the outer voices.
It means creating space to feel and to listen deeply.
This is why so many of us struggle to connect with our intuition.
We're simply too busy, too wrapped up in the daily hustle,
to pause long enough to hear it. But if we
slow down, if we allow ourselves to rest in silence,
we begin to notice a shift. The mind quiets,
the heart opens, and that inner knowing begins to emerge.
It's a gentle process, but a powerful one.
And with time, it becomes second nature, a reliable
companion guiding us through life's uncertainty.
Now let's address the fear that sometimes comes with trusting
our intuition. Many of us worry that if we follow our
instincts, we might make a mistake or that others might not understand our
choices. We think, what if I'm wrong? But intuition
isn't about being right or wrong. It's about aligning with what feels
true for us in that moment. Even if it
leads us down a path that others don't understand.
Or as it seems illogical to the outside world,
it's still our truth. And in following it, we're honoring
our own unique journey rather than conforming to
someone else's expectations.
In trusting intuition, we're cultivating a sense of resilience.
We learn that we can face challenges without needing to
know every answer in advance. That we can embrace the unknown with
without fear. And in this trust, we find freedom.
We're no longer bound by the need for approval or certainty.
We move forward with a quiet confidence, knowing that even
if we don't have a map, we have a compass.
And that compass, that inner guidance, will never lead us astray.
So as we go through life, let's learn to honor this part of ourselves.
Let's give ourselves permission to feel, to trust,
and to follow what resonates with us on a deeper level.
Let's remember that we carry within us a wisdom that transcends
words, one that doesn't need validation or proof.
This is A wisdom that is uniquely ours, a quiet knowing
that is always there, ready to guide us. And in honoring
it, we honor the truest part of who we are.
In the end, intuition is a gift. It's a reminder
that we are not just thinking beings, but feeling beings too.
We are whole, complex, capable of logic and mystery alike.
So let's walk this path with our eyes open, our hearts
attuned, and our intuition as our guide.
And remember, sometimes the greatest strength lies not
in knowing every step, but in trusting the next
one. When we think about resilience,
what often comes to mind is an image of stoic toughness and unyielding
strength that can weather any storm without bending or breaking.
But true resilience isn't about being rigid. It's about being adaptable.
It's the quality that allows us to bend with the wind,
to shift and move with the challenges that life inevitably brings our
way. To cultivate resilience,
we have to recognize that life is dynamic.
Everything around us is in constant motion, and nothing stays
the same for very long. When we try to hold
on tightly to things, to cling to the past or to resist change,
we're only fighting against the natural flow of life.
And that resistance becomes exhausting. It drains our energy and
leaves us feel. Feeling stuck and frustrated. Real resilience,
however, is like water. Water flows around obstacles,
changes its shape to fit its container, and is unafraid
to transform itself in response to whatever lies in its
path. So resilience is not a matter of
puffing it out or forcing ourselves through pain.
It's about developing the flexibility to respond to life in
a way that allows us to remain balanced and connected to ourselves,
no matter what is happening around us. This kind of
resilience requires a level of trust, a trust that whatever
comes our way is ultimately serving our growth, even if it's
difficult to see that in the moment.
The way we build this resilience is through an acceptance of
uncertainty. Now, I know that's not always easy.
As humans, we have a natural desire to seek control, to create
stability and credibility in our lives. But here's
the truth. The more we try to control everything, the less resilient
we actually become. Because life, in its
essence, is uncontrollable. It's unpredictable,
and our attempts to control it only create tension within
us, a resistance that makes us brittle and vulnerable
when challenges inevitably, inevitably come.
Imagine you're standing in the middle of a river and
the water is flowing around you. If you try to stand perfectly
still and resist the current, you'll find yourself struggling,
even getting knocked over. But if you allow yourself
to move with the flow, you find balance. This is the heart
of resilience, learning to flow with life rather than against it.
In this way, resilience becomes less about enduring
and more about embracing. It's about trusting
that we can navigate whatever comes not by rigidly bracing
ourselves, but by learning to move with grace and ease through
whatever life brings. A big part
of this resilience comes from understanding that our thoughts
and emotions, while powerful, are not the entirety of
who we are. Yes, we might feel fear,
disappointment, or frustration when
life doesn't go as planned. But those feelings
are just passing experiences. They're like clouds
drifting across the sky here one moment and gone the next.
The problem is we often cling to those feelings,
letting them define us rather than recognizing them
as temporary. We get swept up in our thoughts,
thoughts, allowing them to pull us in all directions instead
of seeing them as waves on the surface of the ocean, while our true
nature lies in the still, deep waters beneath.
When we recognize that we are not our thoughts or our
emotions, we begin to cultivate a deeper sense of inner peace.
We no longer feel the need to react to every little thing that happens.
We become less attached to outcomes and more present to what's happening
here and now. This presence, this groundedness,
is the foundation of resilience. It's what allows
us to stay calm and centered, even in the face of
uncertainty or difficulty. In cultivating
resilience, it's also helpful to develop a sense of perspective.
Sometimes when we're faced with challenges, it can feel like
the whole world is crashing down around us. But if
we step back, even for a moment, we often find
that the situation isn't as overwhelming as it seems.
It's just one chapter in the story of our lives, not the whole
story. This perspective allows us to approach
life with a sense of curiosity rather than fear.
Instead of asking, why is this happening to me?
We begin to ask, what can I learn from this? This.
How can I grow through this experience?
Resilience in this way becomes a process of transformation.
It's not about avoiding pain or difficulty. It's about using
those experiences as opportunities for growth.
Just as fire refines gold, the challenges
we face refine us, stripping away the layers of fear,
doubt and insecurity to reveal the strength and wisdom within
us. And the beauty of resilience is that each time
we overcome a challenge, we grow stronger,
more capable, and more compassionate. We learn
to face life with an open heart, knowing that no
matter what happens, we have the inner resources to handle it.
And so, as we move through life, we don't need to brace ourselves
against the world or harden our hearts to avoid pain.
Instead, we can cultivate resilience by remaining open,
by embracing change, by trusting in our ability to navigate the
unknown. This is the true strength of resilience.
It doesn't come from fighting against life, but from flowing with it,
from finding peace within ourselves, no matter what
storms may come. So remember
this resilience is not about avoiding the storm storms. It's about learning
to dance in the rain. When we cultivate resilience,
we find a strength within us that is unshakable. A calm
that no storm can disturb. And in that calm,
we find the freedom to live fully, to embrace
life in all its beauty and mystery, without fear.