Sa we
get more real as we get smaller. You see,
that's simply saying that the smaller things are the more real things.
Well, that's a ridiculous argument, because you can play it exactly in the opposite direction.
You can say, oh, no, no, no, no. Since all small things only
exist relatively, that is to say, in relation to each other.
The only real thing is the big thing.
So all those small particles are relatively unreal.
The only thing that is real is the whole universe,
and that's so big that nobody can conceive it.
So do you see? All philosophical argument is a
game playing with people, arguing with each other
in words, playing up and down the
scale of arguing as to which level
of bits,
collections of bits or bits whatsoever, which one
is real. I've noticed a
very funny thing in observing with my experiments with psychedelics,
that psychedelic conversations are
absolutely perfect examples of what is going on and
always has been going on in philosophy.
People start talking with each other, having very animated
conversations about nothing at all except the processes of
grammar. In other words, let's imagine
a conversation in which nothing specific is mentioned.
No proper names are used, no proper nouns,
nothing is being referred to whatsoever. But all the
words that indicate more or less dimensions
of quality, dimensions of quantity, all the operative
words say words like
to be, to grow,
to diminish, to expand,
to contract. All these are operant words which
can be used with reference to all kinds of specifics.
But they get into conversations where all specifics are dropped
out and only operant words are used. And they dance with each
other by using these kinds of words.
And philosophers are doing exactly the same thing.
Philosophy is an intellectual dance of
a game that we play. Just like it might be Go, or it might be
chess or checkers or poker, where we take these abstractions,
the set of cards 52,
to the deck, and we play numbers
and orders against each other. See,
well, philosophers do just the same thing in all their arguments.
And you say, well, isn't that kind of silly?
Well, maybe it isn't, because life
itself, biology, is the same thing.
We have all these species that eat each other and
come on in different shapes and different forms and so on.
And there's a contest going on all the time to prove
whether the cats are more powerful than the mice or the humans than the rats.
And this constant thing is going on. But it
is the same kind of bubbledy, bubbledy, bubble, only it
takes instead of such a simple word as bubble,
which is a vibration in the air, it comes on as a mouse.
And a mouse is a very Complicated way of saying bubble.
And so in all this, you see when, when you get it, when you get
a game going of this kind,
there comes the point of what you might call emotional investment.
When you feel that the outcome
of this particular feature in the game is urgent.
See, this matters and
you do you see that that's what we mean by matter.
The word matter, meaning something substantial, something material,
also means important. It matters,
and it's up to you what you think matters.
We teach our children what matters,
what's important for them to learn, and we teach
them basically that it's important to live.
You must go on. That's terribly
important. When you get a schizophrenic child or a Mongolian,
so called Mongolian idiot, these children don't
realize that it's important to go on and they don't give a damn.
And they are very happy. But from our point of view,
incompetent, unadapted to society,
useless because they don't understand why
it's necessary to go on living. They're just going to have a ball where they
are. And generally what we would say
goof off.
And in a way, every being in this world is torn
between going on and goofing off.
We feel that's, that's the basis of our distinction between work
and play. Play is everybody needs
some time to goof off, but they must go back
to work. Because you've got to farm and fish and manufacture
and produce so that you can go on.
But when you see you have this terrifying urgency to go on
and feel you must, this is, this is important, this matters.
We screen out of our consciousness the fact
that this is our own volition and our own game.
Because we are captivated by the
illusion of the necessity and the importance of going
on to keep other people going on,
to keep children going on. People keep this thing up.
And the difficulty is that as we become disturbed
and anxious about this, it's more difficult
to keep the game going in proportion
as we are frightfully concerned to survive. We start fighting
other people, we start clobbering our neighbors who
are stealing our crops. And whatever it is, all the
old fights start. And it is these fights which
more than anything else at the moment, you see
are endangering the entire human project,
but all based fundamentally on the illusion that it's utterly
important that we survive.
A little while before he died, Robert Oppenheimer said,
it is perfectly obvious that the whole world is going to hell,
it's going to blow up. There is no way,
no, that it can be stopped. Except that
we don't try to stop it happening.
Because you see the panic. What's going to happen if
this bomb goes off? See, this more than
anything else will make it go off.
Because it's like a person who's looking down over a precipice and
starts to get unreasonable. He's terrified to fall
over it. And therefore suddenly all the strength goes out of his fingers
and his legs get wobbly and he's ready to fall
simply because of his fear of falling.
But you see, in all this, what underlies is
the illusion that
I am going on, that I constitute
a real continuity from this moment to the
next moment, to the next moment to the next moment.
What are you afraid of losing when you die?
Why, all the capital you've acquired during
your life, the experiences, the friends,
the status,
the skills, everything that you remember
would be destroyed. Ordinarily, when you die,
that's what. In other words, we are afraid of losing the past.
Now, it's perfectly obvious to me that
when you die,
yes, everything that you've acquired as
an individual and stored in your brain is dissolved
and distributed. But at the same time
it is equally obvious that you are not going to.
That when you die there won't be, following the moment
of death, everlasting nothingness.
That would be as ridiculous as to suppose that you went immediately to heaven
and joined the saints and angels.
The point is that when you die,
you are always reborn de
novo. That is to say, just as you were before.
When you came into this world,
there gradually arose into being the sensation of I.
And it stays there a while, it goes through a development and then
it drops off. But all the
time, everywhere, there are other eyes starting up. See whether
they be human, animal, anything you like, there being other galaxies,
etc. Always they're starting up. Now you
would say, is there? No, there is no connection between them.
No, in the same way, there is no connection between the molecules in your
hand and yet you say it is a hand,
but if you look at it under a powerful enough microscope,
the molecules in your hand are miles apart and you
would say there's no connection between. What's the connection
between this galaxy and other galaxies? Well, we can't
see any connection. And yet there are gravitational swings
whereby they respond to each other and move in a certain collective order.
So in a very similar way,
the constant appearance of beings who feel that they are I
constitute a wave motion and
they may be considered individually.
See, what we're doing in this. I'm not. Is not Setting down a doctrine,
but it is doing an exercise in perception.
You can see it either way. You can see yourself, in other words,
as existing only now,
that's the only you there is. The alternative
to that logically, is to see yourself
as everything.
Either it must be that you exist.
Bingo. Like that. You're a point. Instant bong.
You know, if you go and the Fillmore auditorium and dance,
they turn on stroboscopic light going
very rapidly, brilliant light, on and off, on and off, on and off, on and
off. And it seems that everybody is all the time going in and out of
existence.
Now, in a way that's a, a kind of exemplification
of the truth that we are vibrations and that everything does go
on and off, on and off, on and off all the time.
So the only real thing is the moment of on where you are now.
Got it, lost it, got it, lost it, got it, lost it. See, that's the
only thing that's real. That's one
pole. The other pole is the view that all
these on and offs, just like the molecules in your hand,
constitute a continuous reality.
But if you follow that line, you've got to add up not to just what
you are at this moment. You're going to add up to the whole universe
through the entire span of its existence in space and time.
Any middle position you take between these things is arbitrary.
Say, okay, I'm going to be so much. I'm going
to call myself this particular human being who lives for such and such
a time.
Okay, that's the way you want to play the game, as the rules
you've been told. And if you want to get attached to that
and hung up on that, you're going to say that matters. And so you
feel material.
And the Buddhist idea is simply saying,
don't get hung up on
a. What is called in Sanskrit drishti.
Drishti means a view,
a particular way of looking at things.
You say, that's. I'm looking at it from this point of view. This is
the way it seems to me to be. And I'm going to stick for that.
I'm going to get hung up on that. That is the meaning of, of attachment.
So in, in Sanskrit, the word sakaya, drishti means
the view of separateness. The view
that the, the separation of a certain
bundle of wiggles taken
out of the total wiggliness of all that there is, is me
and another bundle of wiggles is very definitely you. And to
get stuck on that, you see, and therefore to start a
fight about it. Therefore, to start crying and weeping and
gnashing of teeth, all about this thing being real.
See, that is what
these people are trying. All these Buddhist sages and Hindu
sages get people off that hangar
and say, wake up, wake up, wake up. Don't you understand?
The whole thing's an illusion.
Not that this is a word, to put it down and say that it's horrible
or bad. If you could see that the whole thing is an
illusion, you'd be happy as a lark and life would be
lived much more joyously by everybody. We would dance
together and give things away and stop, stop fighting.
If we really saw it was an illusion, we'd all be happy in our big
dream. But we are constantly saying to
ourselves and we are saying to our children, it's real, God damn
it, it's real. And death is going to be awful and sickness is
going to be horrible. You see, it's real and you better watch out. See,
you can see people say to me, you can say as a philosopher that
all this thing is. You can talk this way because you're sitting in a comfortable
place, you've got plenty to eat, but you watch when the thing hits you,
you'll laugh the other side of your face.
Well, I don't give a damn when
it happens. It'll happen, but it's not happening now.
And what I'll do when it does happen is the sufficient unto
the day is the trouble thereof. As if you let
yourself be free to react as nature dictates. When catastrophe falls,
you'll be okay. But if you go
through your whole life standing in a state of preparation for catastrophe,
and you know what's gonna happen,
you just torment yourself and get ulcers and
rotting brain long before it's necessary
for that to happen.
And I let you know
how. A moment
you wanna hold forever
in the palm of your hand,
only with you.
Why don't you really know what you want?
Two reasons that you don't really know what you want.
Number one, you have it.
Number two,
you don't know yourself because you never can.
The Godhead is never an object of its own knowledge.
Just as a knife doesn't cut itself, fire doesn't burn itself,
light doesn't illumine itself, it's always
an endless mystery to itself. I don't know.
And this I don't know, uttered in the infinite
interior of the spirit.
This I don't know is
the same thing as I love. I let go.
I don't try to force or control.
It's the same thing as humility.
If you think that you understand Brahma,
you do not understand and you have yet
to be instructed. Further, if you know that you do
not understand, then you truly understand. For the Brahman
is unknown to those who know it and known to those
who know it not.
And the principle is that
anytime you, as it were,
voluntarily let up control, in other words, cease to
cling to yourself. You have an access of
power because you're
wasting energy all the time in self defense trying
to manage things, trying to force things to conform to your will.
The moment you stop doing that, that wasted energy is available.
And therefore you are in that sense having that energy available.
You are one with the divine principle, you have the energy.
When you're trying, however, you act as if you were God.
That is to say, you don't trust anybody and you're the dictator and you have
to keep everybody in line. You lose the divine energy because
what you're doing is simply defending yourself.
So then the principle is the more you give it away,
the more it comes back. Now you see, I don't have the courage
to give it away. I'm afraid.
And you can only overcome that by realizing you
better give it away because there's no way holding on to it.
The meaning of the fact, you see that everything is dissolving constantly,
that we're all falling apart, we're all in a process of constant death.
And that the worldly hope men set their hearts upon turns ashes or
it prospers and likes snow upon the desert's dusty face lighting a little hour
or two is gone. You know all that Omar Khayyam jazz,
you know, the cloud capped towers, the gorgeous palaces,
the great globe itself I all which it inherits shall dissolve
and like this insubstantial pageant faded, leave not a rack
behind. All falling apart. Everything is,
that's the, the great assistance to you. The that
that fact that everything is in decay is your helper that
is allowing you that you don't have to let
go because there's nothing
to hold on to. It's achieved for
you, in other words, by the process of nature.
So once you see that you just don't have a prayer,
it's all washed up and that you will
vanish and leave not a rack behind.
And you really get with that.
Suddenly you find you have the power,
this enormous access of energy.
But it's not power that came to you because
you grabbed it came in entirely the opposite way.
The power that comes to you in an opposite way is
power with which you can be trusted.
If any one of us could at
this moment be as one about to
die genuinely
and honestly, we would understand
the mystery of life.
Because death is the source of life.
Just as we see in nature. When the leaves fall from the trees,
they mold and rot. And this supplies humus from which more
plants can grow. It's a cycle, life.
But in every way, symbolic and otherwise, Human beings
try to stop that cycle. It is not,
therefore, natural for us to wish to
prolong life indefinitely. But we live
in a culture where it has been rubbed
into us in every conceivable way.
That to die is a terrible thing.
And that is a tremendous disease from which our culture
in particular suffers. And we notice it, firstly, in the way in
which death is swept under the carpet. When one
gets to an extreme, that is to say, to the point where you realize
that there is nothing you can do about life, nothing you cannot
do about life, Then you're the mosquito biting the iron ball.
Well, so in the same way he said, look, you heard
a bomb coming at you. You could hear it whistle. And you
knew it was right above you and headed straight at you and that you were
finished. And you accepted it.
And suddenly there was a strange
feeling that everything is absolutely clear.
You suddenly see that there isn't a grain of dust in the whole universe that's
in the wrong place. That you understand completely,
absolutely, totally what it's all about.
Because you can't say what it is.
So, you see, this is always the opportunity presented
by death.
That if one can go into death with eyes open.
And have somebody help you if necessary,
to give up before you die,
this extraordinary thing can happen to you. So that
from your standpoint, in that position at that time,
you would say, I wouldn't have missed that opportunity for the
world. Now I understand why we die. The reason we die
is to give us the opportunity to understand what life's all about by
letting go. Because then we come to a situation that the ego
can't deal with. When we are no longer hypnotized
by that, Then our natural consciousness can see clearly
what all this universe is for.
So therefore, we have missed this golden opportunity
by institutionalizing death out of the way.
Instead of having a socially
understood acceptance
of death and rejoicing in death to
be important.
Existence does not have to go on any longer than a
moment. Quantitative continuity is of
no value. Who said you're supposed
to survive? Who gave you the idea
that it's a gas to go on and on and on?
And we can't say that it's a good thing for everything to go on living.
From a very simple demonstration that if we enable everybody
to go on living, we overcrowd ourselves.
That we're like an unpruned tree.
We can also look further into it and see that
if our death could be indefinitely postponed,
we would not actually go on postponing it indefinitely.
Because after a certain point we would realize that
that isn't the way in which we want it to survive.
Why else would we have children?
Because children arrange
for us to survive in another way.
By, as it were, passing on a torch so
that you don't have to carry it all the time. There comes
a point where you can give it up and say, now you
work.
It's a far more amusing arrangement for nature to
continue the process of life through different individuals than
it is always with the same individual. Because as
each new individual approaches life, life is renewed.
And one remembers how fascinating the most
ordinary, everyday things are to a child.
Because they see them all as marvelous. Because they see
them all in a way that is not related to survival and profit.
When we get to thinking of everything in terms of survival and profit value
as we do, then the
shapes of scratches on the floor cease to have magic.
And most things in fact, cease to have magic.
So therefore, in the course of nature, once we have
ceased to see magic in the world anymore, we are no longer
fulfilling nature's game of being aware of itself.
There's no point in it anymore. And so we die.
And so something else comes to birth which gets an entirely
new view. And so nature's self
awareness is a game worth the candle.
So then, when there is nobody
left to resist the
thing that we call change, which is simply another word for life.
And when we dispel the illusion that
we think our thoughts instead
of being just a stream of thoughts, and that we feel our
feelings instead of being just feelings,
it's like saying, you know, to feel the feelings is
a redundant expression. It's like
saying, actually I hear sounds.
For there are no sounds which are not heard.
Hearing is sound, seeing is sight.
You don't see sights. Sightseeing is a ridiculous
word. You could just say either sighting
or seeing one or the other. But sightseeing is nonsense.
So we keep the doubling our words. And this doubling
is comparable to oscillation
in an electrical system where there's
too much feedback. Where you remember in the old fashioned telephone
where the receiver was separate from the. From the mouthpiece,
the transmitter, if you wanted to annoy
someone who was abusing you on the telephone, you could make
them listen to themselves by putting the receiver to the mouthpiece.
But it actually didn't have that effect. It set up oscillation.
It started to howl. It could be very, very hard on the ears.
The same way if you turn a television camera at
the monitor, that is to say the television set
in the studio, the whole thing will start to jiggle.
The visual picture will be of oscillation like
that. And the same thing happens here when
you get to think, that you
think your thoughts,
the you standing aside the thoughts has
the same sort of consequence as seeing double.
And then you think, can I observe the
thinker thinking the thoughts?
Or I am worried
and I ought not to worry.
But because I can't stop worrying, I'm worried because I worry.
And you see where that could lead to. It leads to exactly
the same situation
that happens in the telephone. And that is what we
call anxiety trembling.
But this discipline that we're talking about of Nagajunus
abolishes anxiety because
you discover that no amount of anxiety makes
any difference to anything that's going to happen.
In other words, from the first standpoint,
the worst is going to happen. You're all going to die.
And don't just put it off in the back of your mind and say,
I'll consider that later.
It's the most important thing to consider now because
it enables you. It is the mercy of nature because
it's going to enable you to let go and not defend
yourself all the time. Waste all energies inside
self defense.
So go and
not defend yourself all the time. Waste all
energies in self defense.
Because he said every everything is Maya.
So the way it is being interpreted is Maya means it
doesn't exist. Maya does not mean it
does not exist. Maya means an illusion.
Maya means you are not seeing it the way it is.
But you see, however much you mask it under
lofty ideals. I mean the
most religious people in the world, the greatest saints are the veriest
rascals. I've known lots
of them. I must tell you
in confidence, I've known a lot of clergymen.
And the filthiest stories I have ever heard in my life were
told me by clergy clergyman.
So in Hebrew theology,
incidentally, that there is a thing called the
yetza hara. And in the beginning of time,
when God created Adam, he implanted in
him the yetzahara. And the yetzahara means the
wayward spirit. He put something funny in
man so that man would be a little
odd. And it was the result of the yetza
hara. That Adam was tempted by Eve,
who was tempted by the serpent to eat that famous fruit.
And. But the Hebrew believes that everything that
God created is good, including the yetzahara.
Because if it hadn't been for the yetzer hara, there would have.
Nothing ever happened. Everybody would
have obeyed God and God would have said, well, this is kind of a bore
now. But you see, you can't. You can't just get up
to someone and say, disobey me. Because if
they do, they're obeying. You see,
that's a double bind. Say to somebody, disobey me.
But God was much more subtle than that.
He didn't tell Adam to disobey him. He told him to obey.
But subtly, he put this yetza hara thing in like that,
so that God would say, well, I'm not responsible.
Well, this thing's going to happen on its own. Because what everybody wants
is something to happen on its own.
And everybody wants that because,
you see the sensation of being you,
this curious, lonely center
of awkward sensitivity, subject to the most peculiar
feelings and pains and anxieties and all that sort of thing.
All that is
an essential prerequisite for
feeling something else.
These two experiences go together if
you want. In other words, if you want
to be omnipotent and you want to live in a universe where nothing happens
except what you. Exactly what you will to happen.
In other words, you say, I would like to be God. If you think that's
the way God is. And everything is therefore totally under
my control. Everything is absolutely transparent
to my intelligence. I have no problems. A lot of
people coming on like they think they've attained this state, well, that's a
lot of bunk. Nobody wants to be in that position because
there wouldn't be anything to it. Because once
everything is under your central control, not just
nothing is happening. It's a ball from beginning to
end. So what?
Any one or any being whatsoever who has
a sense of centrality, who has a sense of selfhood, who has a sense
of identity, that sense of identity is inseparable
from something else going on that
is defined as not being me,
as not being under my control. And that may jump at any
time. It might even eat me.
So what I want you first of all to understand is
that these two sensations, one of being the
lonely, central, sensitive, vulnerable self,
living in the midst of a world that feels other,
that is not under your control.
I want to try and show you that these two sensations are
really one sensation, or rather two
aspects of one sensation. You couldn't have the one Experience
without the other experience.
Now this is a rather good thing to know because
it means that you won't panic if you discover this.
People who suffer from chronic anxiety are
always in doubt,
you see, about this relationship between what
I feel as myself and what I feel as something else.
Let's suppose you're anxious about your relationship with other
people. You walk into
a room like this restaurant here, and you sit
down at dinner and some stranger opposite to you,
you know nothing about the stranger and you begin,
maybe you feel a little reluctant to open conversation.
You don't know what kind of a. Whether this person is going to be sane
or some kind of a crackpot or some kind of a
awful stuffy square or you don't know what it is.
So you start fencing around a little. But you get
the feeling, you see, of now I better watch myself
because I do, after all, want to make a good impression. I don't want to
make an enemy. So you watch yourself.
And this
is a funny thing then begins called self consciousness.
And people say sort of to each other and usual
way in which strangers come on.
And also
there are there, there is involved in this encounter the
secret games that people are playing all the time to
defend themselves by putting other people down.
This is really a very wicked game. But every,
you see, every, every living being, if the truth be
told,
is a manifestation of everything
that there is in our, what is what we call
God in old fashioned language,
every human being is. And every one. As I
look around, I can see every one of you as the divine
being coming at me in a different way.
Crazy. But the thing is that what we do
is to try and prevent people from realizing that this is so
by pointing out them in the most subtle ways their limitations and
seeing if we can phase them put
a person off a little bit, make them uncertain, make them unsteady.
It's like all sorts of games you can play where if a
person wavers, he loses. But people
play that with each other all the time. And the reason
they do it is not the reason they think it is that the
gay. If everybody were perfectly clear that they were a manifestation of the divine
being, nothing very much would happen.
But so as to keep everybody a little bit unclear about it,
the whole thing bugs itself and
creates these little doubts. So what we are beginning with is
these little doubts, you see, these sensations of
blockage, of not
being very sure of yourself, but knowing very much indeed that you are yourself
and that you're alone. And it's all up to you.
The terrible feeling of responsibility.
So. But what I'm trying to point out to you is if you intensify
that feeling and bring it to its highest pitch. You will
immediately realize that you are aware of it
only by virtue of the entire sensation
of something else. Something defined as
not you. So the feeling of not you and
the feeling of you are relative.
They go together. And you can't have the one without the other.
And if you can't have the one without the other, that means there's a secret
conspiracy between the two. They are
really the same, but pretending to be different. Because the
whole idea is, if there wasn't a difference, you wouldn't know anything was happening.
I mean, if it was all the same. It's like that song of Bob Dylan's
which says something like.
Well, I'm just like a guy like you. I'm just like anybody else. No use
me talking to you, because you just like me.
So the whole point is then, if everybody of
us all were the same. And all shared the same ideas.
Exactly. And so on, there'd be no nothing to talk about, because everybody would
be a bore. There'd be just yourself echoing
back at you, you see. And you'd feel like a madman in a
hall of mirrors. Where everything you went there was just yourself,
you see, in all directions, just you. Well, that's no fun.
But you may think that I'm speaking in favor of some
kind of schizoid, pluralistic universe. No,
the whole point is this. That difference and
every kind of variety of differentiation.
Is the way through which unity is discussed, discovered.
I mean, this business about Vi Lance is
very important.
And the fact that men and women, for example, as a
primordial kind of difference. Never can really understand
each other Is tremendously
exciting.
Because that. That's a way by which something happens.
If it makes a difference, then it's there.
If it doesn't make a difference, it doesn't matter. And what doesn't matter doesn't
exist because it has no matter.
So however it is,
wherever you notice a difference,
the difference has two sides. What it is
and what it's not. And these two sides.
Since you can't have the one side without the other side, they're really one
because they go together inseparably.
So when you get this extreme sense of your own existence
as a rather painful fact.
In the middle of everything else.
The everything else feeling and the you feeling
are two poles of one and the same process.
So that the real you is what lies,
as it were, between these poles.
And includes Both of them.
Now this is the fundamental principle of the whole
way in which ancient Chinese thought developed
the philosophy of the Yang and the Yin.
This is one of the oldest ideas in the universe.
I mean, no, that's a rather too big language on
this planet.
And the, the philosophy which I shall have occasion
to speak of a little bit more later, of the book of Changes,
the Yi Jing is based entirely
on this, that the
universe is the interplay
of difference. And the primordial difference is
between up and down, back and
front. Black and white is
and isn't male and female, positive and
negative. So the word yang in Chinese
means or refers
to the south side of a mountain which
is the sunny side. The word yin
refers to the north side of the mountain, which is the shady side.
Did you ever see a south sided mountain only with no north
side or in it
may also yang may refer to the north bank of a river which
gets the sun and yin to the south bank of
the river which gets the shade.
And so you will remember this.
And one half of course is colored dark
as it were two fishes interlocked
and they are chasing each other.
They actually form, you see, more complicated
symbols in which they form a helix, this is
a helix. And the spiral nebulae
are shaped this way in the form of a helix.
And this is the position of man and woman making love.
Fundamentally where I'm trying
to get inside you and you're trying to get inside me, and we're trying to
get into the middle of each other, but there's somehow or other a difference and
we can never quite get there. Just like
if I want to see the back of my head, I can go round and
round and I can chase it, but I never quite catch up with it.
But that's what makes everything work. It is
said in the Vedanta sutras that
the Lord, the supreme knower of all things,
who is the knower in all of us, doesn't know itself.
In the same way that fire doesn't burn itself and a knife
doesn't cut itself,
so nothing to God even you see, would be more
mysterious than God. Do you
know somehow how you surprise yourself, for example, when you feel your
own pulse and you suddenly feel this life going on
in you, which you're not willing.
Or there are all sorts of ways in which you can say you have the
belly rumbles and you didn't intend to have the belly rumbles
and suddenly it happens. Or you had hiccups and
now are you having hiccups or not?
Is this something you're doing,
or is it merely something that's happening to you as if it was raining and
the rain was happening to you?
This is a very debatable question. Consider breathing.
Are you breathing or is it breathing you?
Well, you can feel it either way. You can decide to breathe
and feel that you're breathing in just the same way that you walk when
you want to. On the other hand, when you forget about breathing
altogether, it still goes on. And so it seems to be something that happens
to you. Which is it?
Do you grow your hair, or does your hair just
grow by itself? What enables you to
make a decision when you decide?
Do you first decide to decide, or do you just decide
now? How do you do that? Nobody knows.
You see,
when J tells a story that one
philosopher asked another, how can one get the dao,
which is the power of nature, so as to have it for one's own?
And the other philosopher answers,
your life is not your own. It is the delegated adaptability
of dao. Your offspring are
not your own. They are the outputs
of dao.
You move. You know not how. You are at rest,
you know not why. These are the operations
of dao, so how could you have it for your
own?
That's a funny thing. We can experience ourselves through
and through as something that just happens.
Look at it this way. If you feel your body, your skin,
the solidity of you,
and regard what marvelous eyes you have,
which are the power which generate
light and color out of all these electrical quanta in
the external world, and these
ears, these beautiful shells that you wear on
the side of your head with their little spiral
bones, the cochlea inside, you know all that.
But you feel, don't you don't feel responsible for it.
You don't know how it's made, if it is made.
But it's you. That's what you are.
That extraordinary pattern. Beautiful,
gorgeous, wonderful arabesque
of tubes of bones and cartilage and myriads
of interconnecting electronics and nervous systems
and everything wonderful. See, but the point is,
most people don't own this.
They don't say, this is me. They say, well, it's some kind of
very clever machine which the Lord God made out of his infinite
wisdom and put me in it.
And this is a very limited view because
the. The extraordinary thing is, you see that this
is you, this extraordinary,
marvelous goings on,
see? But you can feel it, all of it, as if
it was just happening to you. But if you want to feel it that way,
then you've got to go the whole way and you've got to feel that your
decisions just happen to you.
And the thing that you call yourself to which things happen is
just something that happens. See, you go,
you don't know how you manage to be an ego, how you happen to be
conscious. That just happened too.
So happenings happen to a happening. So you
can feel yourself completely irresponsible like that. See,
there's nowhere. Or when
you get that way, that's a very interesting road to run.
But you can try the other way. You can extend
it and say, now look here, if, if, if,
if I really am my eyes and
I, although I don't understand them, I mean that is, say I can't describe
it in lines, in words.
This is me. It's an extraordinary
thing, but it is.
Well, I don't understand how it happens.
But then, you see, that's the whole point,
as I made a little while ago, that the very Lord God himself
doesn't understand how he happens. Because if he did,
what would be the point? There'd be no mystery, be no
possibility of surprises. That's why there has
to be Yang and Yin. Yang is bright and it understands
everything. Yin is dark and damned if she'll be understood.
But there are two phases of the same being. So your Yang side
is your conscious attention. All the bright things you know and all the
information you have and all the know how and that you know what to do.
And your Yin side is the other side of the Yang, which enables
the Yang to function. Because you don't know why the Yang side of you functions,
that is the conscious, bright, intelligent side of you. It all depends on something
you don't understand at all. Because if it
didn't, it wouldn't be there, just like you wouldn't be
here unless there was something else.
So they move together.
And therefore, if you will accept the
idea that you are your own eyes
and your own heart and your own ears with
that wonderful little spiral
cochlea inside and all these amazing gadgets
here, you're all that,
but you don't anything about it, but you are it.
Now, therefore, by a little extension of the imagination, you can
very well see that if all those bones and
subtleties inside you feel other than your conscious ego,
but nevertheless are one with it, the same
argument will go for all the other things going on around you.
The sun shining, the stars twinkling, the wind blowing, and the
great ocean restlessly pounding against these cliffs.
That's you too. You don't control it, of course,
because there has to be something about you you don't control or you wouldn't be
you. I see that
all. All that is lesson elementary in
relativity and relativity.
I've talked about it in this way, which is kind of unscholarly
and so on, but I. I wanted to get the message
across, the idea across, because to understand the
principle of relativity is the
absolute foundation of the philosophy of the Dao.
Lao Tzu takes it up in his second chapter when
he says, when all the world understands beauty to be beautiful, there is
already ugliness. When all the world understands
goodness to be good, there is already evil.
Thus, to be and not to be arise
mutually. High and low
are posited mutually, long and short are
compared mutually. And he goes through a whole
list of opposites and show how they create each other.
It's like that wonderful
little parable. The Chinese character for man
looks more or less like an upturned V.
And Lafcadio Hearn, in one of his books, tells a story of a
Japanese girl telling her little sister the
meaning of the character for man by taking two sticks of wood
and balancing them together on the ground, two sticks of
firewood, so that they form the upturned V. And she says to her little sister,
this is the character for man,
because neither stick will stand up
unless it has the other to help it.
And so, you know, we. We must dig
each other.
But the profounder meaning underneath this is
there's no self without other and
no man. And don't forget, get back to the original point.
Every creature in the world feels it's a man. I don't mean a male,
but a human. And that is because it
is in this situation where the
thing it feels as itself, as its separate identity is
supported by the equal and opposite sensation of
other, center,
periphery, here,
there, now, then is,
isn't, or whatever these two
are the yang and the yin, the two poles that hold
each other up. So the
Zen poem says, when misfortune
comes, treat it as a blessing. When fortune
comes, treat it as a disaster.