I wonder, I wonder what you would do if
you had the power to dream at night. Any dream you
wanted to dream.
And you would of course be able to alter your time sense
and slip, say, 75 years of subjective
time into eight hours of sleep.
You would, I suppose, start out by fulfilling
all your wishes.
You could design for yourself what would be the most
ecstatic life. Love affairs,
banquets, dancing girls,
wonderful journeys,
gardens, music beyond belief.
And then after a couple of months of this
sort of thing, at 75 years a night,
you'll be getting a little taste for something different.
And you would move over to an adventurous dimension
where there were certain dangers involved and the thrill of dealing with dangers.
And you could rescue princesses from dragons and
go on dangerous journeys,
make wonderful explosions and blow them up,
eventually get into contest with enemies.
And after you've done that for some time,
you'll think up a new wrinkle to forget that you
were dreaming so that you would think it was
all for real and to be
anxious about it.
And then because be so great when you woke up.
And then you say, well, like children
who dare each other on things, how far out could you get?
What could you take? What dimension of being lost,
of abandonment, of your power? What dimension of that
could you stand? You could ask yourself this, because you know you'd eventually
wake up and
then you would get more and more adventurous and you would make further
and further out gambles as to what you would dream.
And finally you would dream where
you are now.
You would dream the dream of living the life that you are actually living today.
That would be within the infinite multiplicity of
choices you would have of playing that you weren't
God. Because the whole nature
of the Godhead, according to this idea, is to play that
he's not. So in this
idea then everybody is fundamentally the
ultimate reality. Not God in a
politically kingly sense, but God in the sense
of being the self, the deep down, basic whatever
there is. And you're all that,
only you're pretending you're not.
One day you're going to wake up and say,
why, that's me. What you
are, basic, deep,
deep down, far far in,
is simply the fabric and structure
of existence itself. And when you
find that out, you laugh yourself silly.
Some people will use a symbolism of the
relationship of God to the universe, wherein God
is a brilliant light,
only somehow veiled, hiding underneath all these
forms that you see as you look around you.
So far, so good. But the truth is funnier than that.
It is that you are looking right at the brilliant
light. Now that
the experience you are having, which you call ordinary,
everyday consciousness, pretending you're not it.
That experience is exactly the same thing as it.
There's no difference at all.
And when you find that out, you laugh yourself silly.
That's the great discovery.
In other words, when you really start to see things.
And you look at an old paper cup.
And you go into the nature of what it is to see.
What vision is or what smell is or what touches
you realize that that vision of the paper cup is
the brilliant light the cosmos.
Nothing could be brighter. 10,000 suns couldn't
be brighter. Only they
are hidden in the sense that all the points of the infinite
light are so tiny when you see them in the cup.
They don't blow your eyes out. But it
is actually, see, the source of all light is in the eye.
If there were no eyes in this world, the sun would not be light.
You evoke light out of the universe.
In the same way you, by virtue of having a soft skin,
evoke hardness out of wood. Wood is
only hard in relation to a soft skin. It's your eardrum
that evokes noise out of the air.
You, by being this organism, call into
being the whole universe of light and color and hardness and
heaviness and everything, See?
Well, now here's the problem.
If this is the state of affairs which is so.
And if the consciousness state you are in
at this moment. Is the same thing as what we might call the
divine state. If you do anything to make it different,
it shows you don't understand that it's so. So the
moment you start practicing yoga or praying or meditating
or indulging in some sort of spiritual cultivation,
you are getting in your own way.
If you think you have a problem, you see that you're an
ego and that you're in difficulty. The answer that the Zen master
makes to you is, show me your ego. I want to see this thing that
has a problem. See, because when you look
for your own mind. That is to say, your own particularized
center of being. Which is separate from everything else, you won't be able
to find it. The only way you'll know it isn't there is if you look
for it hard enough to find out that it isn't there.
So everybody says, all right, know yourself. Look within.
Find out who you are. Because the harder you look, you won't
be able to find it. And then you'll realize that it isn't there at all.
There isn't a separate you.
Your mind is what there Is everything.
The reason why certain people turn to philosophy,
why I became a philosopher, was that since I was a little boy,
I always felt that existence
as such was weird.
I mean, here we are. Isn't that
odd? Of course
it's odd. What do you mean? What do you mean by odd?
Well, it's what's different from even.
I mean, what's art stands out.
What's even lies flat. But you can't see
the outstanding without the flat background.
Here's the thing standing out that's odd.
Each one of you is odd, strange,
unique, particular, different.
How do we know what we mean by that, except against the background of something
even that is not differentiated like space?
And so you get this philosophical itch.
You begin to scratch your head and think about, why is that so?
Well, after a while, you realize that's a meaningless question. And you
ask, how is it so? Well, that leads you into science
and other investigations. So you want to
know what is it? I mean, this. This happening,
this thing called existence. What is it?
You ask that question long enough, and it suddenly hits you that if you
could answer it, you wouldn't know what terms to put the answer in.
Give me some of the love. Give me some of that.
Give me some of that love. Give me some of it.
Sa.
Change. And everything is changed. Nothing could
be held onto. To the degree that you go with a stream,
you see, you are still. You're flowing
with it. But to the degree you resist the stream.
Then you notice that the current is rushing past you and fighting.
So swim with it, go with it.
And you're there, you're at rest.
And this is, of course, particularly true when it comes to
those moments when life really seems to be going to
take us away. And the stream of change is
going to swallow us completely. The moment of death.
And we think, oh, this is it.
This is the end.
And so at death, we withdraw. Say, no, no, no,
no, not that. Not. Not yet, please.
But actually,
the whole problem is
that it really is no other problem for human beings than
to go
over that waterfall when it comes.
Just as you go over any other waterfall. Just as you
go on from day to day, just as you go to
sleep at night, be absolutely
willing to die. Now, I'm not preaching.
I'm not saying you ought to be willing to die. And that you should
muscle up your courage and somehow put on
a good front when the terrible thing comes. That's not the idea at
all. Point is that you can only die.
Well, if you understand this
system of waves,
if you Understand that
your disappearance as the form in which you
think you are you, your disappearance as this
particular organism is
simply seasonal.
That you are just as much the
dark space beyond death as
you are the lightened called
life. These are
just two sides of you because
you is the total wave.
See, you can't have half a wave.
Nobody ever saw waves which just had crests,
no troughs.
So you can't have half a human being who
is born but doesn't die. Half a thing.
That would be only half a thing.
But the propagation of vibrations, of life is vibration.
It simply goes on and on. But its cycles are long cycles and
short cycles.
Space, you see,
is not just nothing.
If I could magnify my hand to an enormous
degree so that you could see all the molecules in it,
I don't know how far apart they would be, but it seems to me
they would be something like tennis balls in a very,
very large space.
And you'd look, when I move my hand like this,
you say, for God's sake, look at all those tennis balls. They're all going together
crazy. And there are no strings tying them together.
That queer. No, but there's space.
Going with space is a function
of, or it's an inseparable aspect of whatever solids are
in space.
That is the clue, probably to what we mean by gravity.
We don't know. So in
the same way, when those marvelous sandpipers come around here,
the little ones, while they're in the air flying,
they have one mind. They move all together.
When they alight on the mud, they become individuals and they go pecking around for
worms. One click of the fingers and
all those things are zipped into the air. They don't seem to have a
leader because they don't follow. When they turn,
they all turn together and go off in another direction.
Amazing. But they're like the molecules in my hand.
So then you see, here's the principle.
When you don't resist change,
I mean over resist, I don't mean being flabby.
When you don't resist change, you see that the changing
world which disappears like smoke,
is no different from the Nirvana world.
Nirvana, as I said, means breathe out,
let go of the breath. So in the same way, don't resist
change. It's all the same principle.
So the Bodhisattva saves all beings.
Not by preaching sermons to them,
but by showing them that they are delivered.
They are liberated by the very fact of not being able
to stop changing.
You can't hang on to yourself. You don't have
to try not to hang on to yourself.
It can't be done. And that is salvation.
Memento mori. Be mindful of death.
Gurdjieff says in one of his books that
the most important thing for anyone to realize is
that you and all you,
every person you see, will soon be dead.
It sounds so gloomy to us because
we have devised the culture fundamentally
resisting death.
From the first standpoint, the worst is going to happen.
You're all going to die.
And don't just put it off in the back of your mind and say,
I'll consider that later.
It's the most important thing to consider now because
it enables you, it is the mercy of nature because
it's going to enable you to let go and not defend
yourself all the time, waste all the energies in
self defense.
Sa wonder
is, is like in modern philosophy, something you mustn't have. It's like enthusiasm
in 18th century England. But you
see, I don't know what question to ask when I wonder about the
universe. It isn't a question that I'm wondering about.
It's a feeling that I have because
I cannot formulate the question that is my wonder. The moment
my mouth opens to utter it, I suddenly find I'm talking nonsense.
But that should not prevent wonder from being the foundation of philosophy
going into our common sense. The 19th century myth
which succeeded the ceramic myth in Western history. I call
it the myth of the fully automatic model.
Man is a little germ that lives on an unimportant rock
ball that revolves about an insignificant star
on the outer edges of one of the smaller galaxies.
But on the other hand, if you think about that for a few minutes,
I am absolutely amazed to discover myself on this rock
ball rotating around a spherical fire.
It's a very odd situation. And the more I look
at things, I cannot get rid
of the feeling that existence is. Is quite weird.
There is obviously a place in life
for a religious attitude in the sense of awe,
astonishment at existence.
And that is also a basis
of respect for existence.
It has become extremely plausible that
this trip between the maternity ward and
the crematorium is what there is to life.
Here is a tree in the garden, and every
summer it produces apples.
And we call it an apple tree because the
tree apples, that's what it does.
All right. Now, here is a solar system
inside a galaxy. And one of the peculiarities
of this solar system is that at least on the planet Earth, the thing peoples
in just the same way that an apple tree apples.
Now, maybe 2 million years ago,
somebody came from another galaxy in a flying saucer and
had a look at this solar system, and they looked it
over and shrugged their shoulders and said, just a bunch of rocks,
and they went away. Later on,
maybe 2 million years later, they came around and they looked
at it again and they said, excuse me,
we thought it was a bunch of rocks, but it's peopling and
it's alive. After all, it has done something intelligent.
Because, you see, we grow out of this world in
exactly the same way that the apples grow on the apple tree.
If evolution means anything, it means that.
But you see, we. We curiously twist it.
We say, well, first of all, in the beginning there was nothing but gas
and rock. And then intelligence
happened to arise in it, you know, like a sort of
fungus or slime on the top of the whole thing.
But we are thinking in a way, you see, that disconnects the intelligence
from the rocks. Where there are rocks,
watch out, watch out,
because the rocks are going eventually to come alive.
I believe that there is a strong distinction between
faith on the one hand and belief on the other.
That belief is, as a matter of fact, quite contrary
to faith, because belief is really
wishing. It's from the Anglo Saxon root leaf to wish.
And belief, stated, say, in the creed,
is a fervent hope that the universe
will turn out to be thus and so.
And in this sense, therefore, belief precludes the possibility
of faith, because faith is openness to
truth, to reality, whatever it may turn out to be.
I want to know the truth. That is the attitude of faith.
And therefore, to use ideas about the
universe and about God as something to hang
on to in the spirit of Rock
of Ages Cleft for me and
there's something very rigid about a rock, and we are finding
our rock getting rather worn out in an
age where it becomes more and more obvious that our world is a floating
world. It's a world floating in space where
all positions are relative and any point may be regarded as the center.
A world which doesn't float on anything. And therefore, the religious
attitude appropriate to our time is not one of clinging to rocks,
but of learning to swim. And you know
that if you get in the water and you have nothing to hold on to,
and you try to behave as you would on dry land, you will drown.
But if, on the other hand, you trust yourself to the water and let
go, you will float. And this is
exactly the situation of faith.
Imagine the idea that the moment you were born,
you were kicked off the edge of a precipice and
you are falling as you fell.
A great lump of rock came with you, and it's traveling
alongside you, and you're clinging to it for dear
life and thinking,
gee, I gotta hold on to this. See? Well, it doesn't do a
thing for you, and you'll only.
It's only making you anxious, and it's only when you understand
that it doesn't do a thing for you that you let go and relax.
So everybody's in this situation. We're all completely insecure.
We are all headed straight for death as if we had been condemned
by a judge. And yet here we are all clinging
on to things, and we. We have all sorts of alibis for doing
this. We say, well, I have responsibilities for my dependence,
and I've got to cling on. But all you're doing is you're teaching your dependents
to cling the same way as you are and making
them miserable by learning
to go on surviving compulsively.
So the thing is, same way, if you're caught in a torrent
and you try to get out of it by swimming against it, you'll just wear
yourself out and you're still carried along with it. So the sensible thing to do
is to turn around, swim with it,
and if you want to get out of it, swim towards the edge,
but go with it. Same way when you're sailing, always keep the
wind in your sails. If you want to go against the wind, tack,
but use the wind. So it's this way, you know,
we're all in this great stream of change which we call life.
We are the stream. If you imagine you
are separate from it and you're being carried along by it as if you were
a cork, that's a delusion. You're a wave of the stream itself.
So get with it.
This seminar called Inevitable Ecstasy is
about a very sticky problem,
which is to say the problem to which the Buddha primarily
addressed himself, which is that of
agony, suffering.
But before we get into that,
we have to be clear about certain basics.
And these basics have to do not so much with concepts and
ideas as they do with the state
of mind, a state of sensation,
a state of consciousness.
And we need to
understand that, even be in that, before we can really
go very far.
And this is an extraordinarily difficult state of mind to
talk about, even though in its nature it's extremely
simple, because it
is, in a way, like we were when we were babies,
when we hadn't been told anything and didn't know anything other than
what we felt and we had no names for it.
Now, of course, as we grow older,
we learn to differentiate one thing from
another, one event from another, and above all,
ourselves from everything else well
and good, provided you don't
lose the foundations. Just as mountains
are differentiated, but they're all based on the earth,
so the multiple things of this world are differentiated,
but they have, as it were, a basis.
There is no word for that basis, not really,
because words are only for distinction.
And so there can't really be a word, not even an idea
of the non distinction. We can
feel it, but we can't think it, but we
don't feel it like an object. You feel you're alive,
you feel you're conscious, but you don't know what consciousness is,
because consciousness is present in every conceivable kind
of experience. It's like the space
in which we live, which is everywhere.
It's like a fish being in water. And presumably
a fish doesn't know it's in the water because it never goes out.
A bird, presumably, knows nothing of the air,
and we really know nothing of consciousness,
and we pretend space isn't there.
So however,
when you grow up and become
fascinated, which is really the right word, spellbound,
enchanted by all the things that adults wave at
you, you forget the background and
you come to think that all the distinctions which you've been learning are
the supremely important things to be concerned with.
You become hypnotized. And so when we
are told to pay attention to what matters, we get stuck with it.
And that's what in Buddhism is called attachment.
Attachment doesn't mean that
you enjoy your dinner,
you enjoy sleeping or beauty.
Those are responses of our organism
in its environment as natural as feeling hot near
a fire or cold near ice.
So are certain responses of fear or of sorrow.
They are not attachment. Attachment is exactly
translated by the modern slang term hang up.
It's a kind of stickiness, or what in psychology would
be called blocking, when you are in a
state of wobbly hesitation, not knowing how to flow
on. That's attachment. What is meant by the Sanskrit
word klesha.
So we get a hang up on all the various things that we're
told as we grow up by our parents,
our aunts and uncles, our teachers, by our peer group.
And the first thing that everybody wants to tell us
is the difference between ourselves and
the rest of the world and between those actions
which are voluntary and those which are involuntary,
what we do on the one hand and what happens
to us on the other. And this is of
course immensely confusing to a small child because
it's told to do all sorts of things that are really supposed to happen.
Like going to sleep, like having bowel movements,
like loving people,
like not blushing, stopping being anxious,
and all sorts of things like that.
So what happens is this. The child is
told, in sum, that we,
your parents, elders and betters, command you to
do what will please us only if you do it spontaneously.
And no wonder everybody's completely confused.
We go through life with that burden on us.
We therefore develop this curious thing.
We develop a thing which is called an ego.
Now, I've got to be very clear to you what I mean by an ego.
An ego is not the same thing as a
particular living organism.
For my philosophy, the particular living organism which
is inseparable from a particular environment,
that is to say from the universe as centered here and now.
There's something real. It isn't a thing, I call
it a feature of the universe.
But what we call our ego is
something abstract,
which is to say it has the same order and kind of reality
as an hour or an inch
or a pound or a line of longitude.
It is for purposes of discussion, it is for convenience.
In other words, it is a social convention that we
have what is called an ego. But the fallacy
that all of us make is that we treat it as if it were a
physical organ. As if it were
real in that sense. When in fact
it is composed on the one hand of our
image of ourselves.
That is our idea of ourselves. As when we say
to somebody, you must improve your image.
Now, this image of ourselves is obviously not ourselves
any more than an idea of a tree is a
tree. Any more than
you can get wet in the word water or.
And to go on with our image of ourselves is extremely inaccurate
and incomplete. Would that some God the gifted gears
to see ourselves as others see us. We don't.
So my image of me is not at all your image of me.
And my image of me is extremely incomplete in that it
does not include any information
to speak of about the functioning of my nervous system,
my circulation, my metabolism, my subtle relationships
with the entire surrounding human and non human universe.
So the image I have of myself is a caricature.
It is arrived at through
mainly my interaction with other people who tell me
who I am in various ways, either directly or indirectly.
And I play about with what their picture
is of me. And they play something back to me.
So that we set up this conception. And this started
very, very early in life.
And I was told, you see, and you were told
that we must have a consistent Image,
you must be you. You have to find your identity.
In terms of image, this is an awful red herring.
A lot of the current quest for identity among younger
people is a search for an
acceptable image. What role can
I play? Who am I in the sense of what am I going to do
in life? And so on. Now, while that has a certain importance,
if it's not backed up by deeper matters, it's extraordinarily misleading.
So therefore, on the one hand, there is this image which is intellectual,
emotional, imaginative and
so forth. Now, we would
say, I don't feel that I
am only an image.
I feel there's something more real than that. Because I
feel. I mean, I have a sense of there being a
particular sort of.
How do we say, a center of something,
some sort of sensitive core inside
the skin. And that
corresponds to the word I.
Let's take a look at this.
Because the thing that we feel as being myself
is certainly not the whole body,
because a lot of the body can be seen as
an object. In other words, if you
stand, stretch yourself out, lie on the floor and turn your head and look
at yourself, you know, you can see your feet and your legs and
all this up to here, and finally it all vanishes. Only there's a sort of
a vague nose in front.
And you assume you have a head because everybody else does, and you've
looked in a mirror and that told you you had a head, but you could
never see it, just like you can't see your back.
So you tend to put your ego on the side of the
unseen part of the body, the part
you can't get at, because that seems to be where it all comes from.
And you feel it.
But what is it that we feel? Because if I see clearly
and my eyes are in functioning order, the eyes certainly
are not conscious of themselves, themselves. There are no spots
in front of them, no defects, in other words, in the lens or in the
retina or in the optic nerves that give hallucinations.
So also, therefore, if my ego, my consciousness is working properly,
I ought not to be aware of it as something sort
of there being a nuisance, in a way,
in the middle of things. Because your ego is awfully hard to take care of.
Well, what is it then that we feel? Well, I think I've discovered what it
is.
It's a chronic habitual sense of muscular strain which
we were taught in the whole process of doing spontaneous
things to order.
When you're taking off in a jet plane and
the thing has gone rather further down the Runway than you think it should have
without getting up in the air, you start pulling
at your seat belt, get this thing off the
ground. Perfectly useless.
So in the same way, when our community
tells us, look carefully,
now, listen, pay attention, we start
using muscular strains around our eyes, ears,
jaws, hands,
to try to use our muscles to make our nerves work,
which is of course futile.
And in fact, it gets in the way of the functioning of the nerves.
Try to concentrate.
And then when we try to control our emotions,
we hold our breath, pull our stomachs in, or tighten
our rectal muscles to hold
ourselves together. Now pull yourself together immediately.
What are you to do? What does a child understand by that? He does
it muscularly, pulls himself together. It's just useless.
So everybody chronically pulls themselves together so
that. It's so funny. If you get a person to just lie on the floor
and relax, there's the floor under you as firm as can be
holding you up. Nevertheless, you will detect that the person is making
all sorts of tensions lest he should suddenly
turn into a nasty jello on the floor.
So that chronic tension, which in Sanskrit is called samkocha,
which means contraction, is the root of
what we call the feeling of the ego. So that, in other words,
this feeling of tightness is the physical
referent for the psychological image
of ourselves. So that we get the ego as
the marriage of an illusion to a futility.
Even though the idea of an I with a name,
with a being is naturally useful for social
communication, provided we know what we're doing and
take it for what it is.
But we are so hung up on this concept
that it confuses us even in
the proposition that it might be possible for us to feel otherwise.
Because we ask the question, if we hear about people who have
transcended the ego, well, we ask, how do
you do that? Well, I say,
what do you mean, you? How do you do that?
Because the you you're talking about doesn't exist,
so you can't do anything about it any
more than you can cut a cheese with a line of longitude.
Now, that sounds very discouraging, doesn't it?
But let's suppose now you are babies again and
you don't know anything.
Now, don't be frightened, because anything you know, you can get back
later. But for the time being,
here is our
awareness.
And let's suppose you have no information about this at all and no words
for it,
and that my talking to you is just a noise.
Now, don't try to do anything about this.
Don't make any effort,
because naturally, by force of habit.
Certain tensions remain inside you and certain ideas
and words drift all the time through your mind.
Just like wind blows or clouds move across
the sky, don't bother with them at all,
don't try to get rid of them. Just be
aware of what's going on in your head like
it was clouds in the sky or
the crackling of the fire.
There's no problem to this.
All you have to do really is look and listen
without naming. And if
you are naming, never mind, just listen
to that.
Now, that you can't force anything here,
that you can't willfully
stop thinking and stop naming,
is only telling you that
the separate you doesn't exist.
It isn't a mark of defeat, it isn't
a sign of your lack of practice in meditation.
That it runs on all by itself simply means that the individual
separate you is a figment of your imagination.
So you are aware at this point of
a happening.
Remember, you don't know anything about the difference between
you and it. You haven't been told that
you've no words for the difference between inside and outside,
between here and there.
And nobody has taught you that what you see out in front of you
is either near or
far from your eyes.
Watch a baby put out a finger to touch the moon.
You don't know about just
therefore here it is,
we'll just call it this.
And if you will feel it,
the going on which includes
absolutely everything you feel.
And it's a happening.
It doesn't happen to you because where is
that you, what you call you is part of the happening
or an aspect of it has no parts. It's not like a
machine.
And it's a little scary because you'd
say, well, who's in control around here?
Why should there be anyone?
That's a very weird notion we have that processes
require something outside them to control them.
It never occurred to us that processes could be self controlling.
Even though we say to someone, control yourself. We can
always, in order to think about self control, we split
a person in two so
that there's a you separate from the self that's supposed to be controlled.
Well, how can that achieve anything? How can
a noun start a verb? Yet it's a fundamental superstition
that that can be done.
So you have this process which is quite spontaneous
going on. We call it life. It's controlling itself.
It's aware of itself. It's aware of itself
through you. You are an aperture through which the universe looks at
itself. And because of its
the universe looking at itself through you there's always an
aspect of itself that it can't see.
So it is like that snake you see that is pursuing its tail
because the snake can't see its head like you can't.
So therefore,
we always find, as we investigate the universe,
make the microscope bigger and bigger and bigger,
and we will find ever more minute things,
make the telescope bigger and bigger and bigger, and the universe
expands because it's running away from itself.
It won't do that if you don't chase it.
An ego is not the same thing as
a particular living organism.
For my philosophy, the particular living organism which
is inseparable from a particular environment,
that is to say from the universe, as centered here, here and now,
there's something real. It isn't a thing.
I call it a feature of the universe.
But what we call our ego is
something abstract, which is to say it
has the same order and kind of reality as
an hour or an inch or
a pound or a line of longitude.
It is for purposes of discussion, it is for convenience.
In other words, it is a social convention that we have what
is called an ego.
But the fallacy that all of us make is
that we treat it as if it were a physical organization,
as if it were real in that sense,
when in fact it is composed on the one hand of
our image of ourselves, that is our
idea of ourselves. As when we say to somebody, you must
improve your image.
Now, this image of ourselves is obviously not ourselves
anymore than an idea of a tree is a tree
any more than you can get wet in the word water.
And to go on with our image of ourselves is extremely
inaccurate and incomplete. So my image
of me is not at all your image of me.
And my image of me is extremely incomplete in that it does not include
any information to speak of about the functioning
of my nervous system, my circulation, my metabolism,
my subtle relationships with the entire surrounding human
and non human universe.
So the image I have of myself as a caricature,
it is arrived at through mainly
my interaction with other people who tell me who I am in
various ways, either directly or indirectly. And I play
about with what their picture is of me, and they play
something back to me. So that we set up this conception and
this started very, very early in life.
And I was told, you see, and you were told that
we must have a consistent image. You must
be you. You have to find your identity
in terms of image. This is an awful red herring.
A lot of the current quest for identity among younger people
is a search for an acceptable image.
What role can I play who am I in the sense of
what am I going to do in life? And so on. Now, while that has
a certain importance,
if it's not backed up by deeper matters, it's extraordinarily misleading.
So therefore, on the one hand, there is this image which is intellectual,
emotional, imaginative and
so forth.
Now we would say, I don't feel that
I am only an image.
I feel there's something more real than that. Because I
feel. I mean, I have a sense of there being a
particular sort of a
center of something, some sort of sensitive core
inside the skin. And that corresponds
to the word I. Let's take a look
at this.
Because the thing that we feel as being myself is
certainly not the whole body,
because a lot of the body can be seen as an object.
In other words, if you stand, stretch yourself out,
lie on the floor and turn your head and look at yourself, you know,
you can see your feet and your legs and all this up to
here. And finally it all vanishes. Only there's a sort of a vague nose
in front. And you assume
you have a head because everybody else does, and you've looked in a mirror
and that told you you had a head, but you could never see it,
just like you can't see your back.
So you tend to put your ego on the side of the
unseen part of the body, the part
you can't get at, because that seems to be where it all comes from.
And you feel it. But what is it that we feel?
Because if I see clearly and my eyes are in functioning order,
the eyes certainly are not conscious of themselves.
There are no spots in front of them, no defects, in other words, in the
lens or in the retina or in the optic nerves that give hallucinations.
So also, therefore, if my ego, my consciousness, is working
properly, I ought not to be aware of it as something sort
of there being a nuisance,
in a way, in the middle of things. Because your ego is awfully hard to
take care of. Well, what is it then that we feel?
Well, I think I've discovered what it is.
It's a chronic habitual sense of muscular strain,
which we were taught in the whole process of
doing spontaneous things to order.
When you're taking off in a jet plane and
the thing has gone rather further down the Runway than you think it should have,
without getting up in the air, you start
pulling at your seat belt,
get this thing off the ground, perfectly useless.
So in the same way, when our community tells
us, look carefully,
now, listen, pay attention, we start
using muscular strains around our eyes, ears,
jaws, hands,
to try to use our muscles to make our nerves work,
which is, of course, futile.
And in fact, it gets in the way of the functioning of the nerves.
And then when we try to control our emotions,
we hold our breath, pull our stomachs in or tighten our rectal
muscles to hold ourselves together. Now,
pull yourself together.
What are you to do? What does a child understand by that? He does
it muscularly. Pulls himself together, Mr. Eustace.
So everybody chronically pulls themselves together.
It's so funny, if you get a person to just lie on the floor and
relax,
there's the floor under you as firm as can be holding you up.
Nevertheless, you will detect that the person is making all sorts of tensions
lest he should suddenly turn into
a nasty jello on the floor.
So that chronic tension, which in Sanskrit is called samkocha,
which means contraction,
is the root of what we call the feeling of the ego.
So that, in other words, this feeling of tightness
is the physical referent for
the psychological image of ourselves.
So that we get the ego as the marriage of an illusion to a futility.
Even though the idea of an I with a name,
with a being is naturally useful for
social communication, provided we know what we're doing
and take it for what it is.
But we are so hung up on this concept
that it confuses us even in
the proposition that it might be possible for us to feel other bud.