All right everybody, happy Tuesday.
At least I'm very happy today because we've been trending all day on X,
given the interview that I gave with Rabbi Barclay yesterday.
A lot of you guys have so many comments regarding that back and forth.
And one of the questions that I have is why so
many people think I'm going to get killed?
Yeah, it's a recurring theme.
People are like be careful Candace, double up on your security.
Don't do this, don't do that.
They're going to kill you.
You're going to get Michael Jackson.
Where is all of that rhetoric coming from?
Today I want to unpack it and I want to formally state my history when it comes
to my engagement with the political movement in America.
Reveal to you guys some things that I've never revealed before.
Really want to crack open this dialogue.
All that and more today coming up on Candace Owens.
All right guys, a tremendous, tremendous response.
Honestly, thank you.
I think people of all races and religions were just shocked by the conversation that
I had with Rabbi Barclay yesterday.
It wasn't really much of a conversation.
Obviously, he spoke a lot more than I did.
But I was happy for that.
I was grateful for that because I wanted people to hear his perspectives.
I know this is going to sound weird, but I kind of like Rabbi Barclay because I think
he's honest.
I think he honestly, as I tweeted yesterday, views himself as better and more important
or at least his race as more important than other races, more significant the history
of his race as more significant.
And even in terms of someone being a supremacist, if you are honestly a supremacist, at least
I can appreciate that because you're not hiding who you are.
And that's why I meant it when I said that he will always be welcomed back onto this
show.
I think it takes courage to have conversations.
And I think that what he did yesterday was actually quite courageous.
A couple of moments that you guys were shocked by, just like me, was I guess just the lack
of definition when it comes to anti-Semitism.
It mutates.
He told us that over and over again.
It is a definition.
It is a hate that mutates, which essentially, at least the way I took it, and I think most
of you took it means that it can just be whatever they say that it is, including the term hag.
I think I actually learned the word hag from watching the movie Hocus Pocus when I was
a kid.
It actually was one of my favorite movies.
And they used the word hag, and I used it to describe someone that is engaging in which
like behavior, trying to cast a spell on audiences to convince them that can is owned as an anti-Semite
when I could not be further from that sort of a category.
I am just, I have no hatred towards Jewish people in my soul.
I just don't.
I had many experiences with Jewish people growing up.
I've already recounted those.
We're not going to do that today.
But yes, Rabbi Barclay says that the scholars agree.
He kept talking down to me.
It's the scholars.
It's the intelligentsia.
They're so much smarter than us, and they understand the definition just changes.
I think a lot of you guys were also surprised by the double down, right, in the face of
overwhelming evidence.
I just thought there was no way, once we pulled the clips of me saying the exact opposite of
what he claimed that I said.
I thought there was no way that he was going to double down it, but he did.
He particularly doubled down on the Hitler is okay, Candace thing, right?
Candace said Hitler is okay.
He repeated that over and over again in that hit piece.
And then I show that I did not in any way say Hitler was okay because what crazy person
would ever jump on a stage and say that.
Here's one comment from YouTube.
He wrote, when she played her Hitler quote and he still stood by what he wrote, I lost
respect for this guy.
Yeah.
A lot of comments looked like that.
And I think especially because so many people had never actually heard what I said in its
entirety.
You've seen the libels.
You've seen the smears.
They've been printed for years.
I am still having to clarify.
For years I have been clarifying what I said.
And many of you guys have never heard it because you've just seen article after article hit
after hit people trying to convince the masses that I said something that I simply never
said.
And in watching that clip, I think people were shocked.
But yes, this is the truth.
And factually speaking, as a political pundit, whatever it is that you want to call me as
a podcaster, I have been smeared and libeled for years.
And I feel a power building in that people are getting tired of this.
We are being tired of being propagandized.
And that is why for me, I feel in my soul at the time is now.
And people are asking why is Canada speaking out right now?
Well, the truth is, is I'm simply tired of being lied on.
I'm a human, right?
Eventually you get to a point where you say I'm just not going to allow people to lie
on my name anymore.
Especially again, as I said, when it's been happening for years.
And really all I've ever done since I've had a platform is just tried to show you guys
the truth.
I don't want to tell you what to think.
I can only share with you what my experiences are and hope that it helps you develop your
own ideas.
So let's recap, because I'm going to share some things I've never shared before.
Obviously, you guys know that I hit the scene in 2017.
And I had a laser sharp focus on the black community.
My career began when I started making YouTube videos, really challenging the BLM narrative.
I was having my own awakening in real time about the lies that the media was printing
about black people, really lies that were meant in my viewpoint to keep black people
down, to encourage black people to live a life of criminality, to encourage black people
to loot and to riot their own neighborhoods in the name of some perceived social justice.
I pretty immediately got hired at Turning Point USA.
I hit the ground running with Charlie Kirk.
Charlie Kirk is unapologetically pro-Israel.
Everybody knows this.
I was beside him throughout most of his pro-Israel commentary.
And I bet if people dug it up on the internet, you would hear me saying pro-Israel talking
points.
And I say talking points because when I got into it, I didn't really care again about
Israel because I was an American.
And I just want to talk about black America.
But certainly, I was nodding my head no matter what Charlie Kirk said, because I was just
grateful to have a platform to talk about the things that were important to me.
And I had a wonderful experience with Charlie Kirk.
And I learned a lot under him and with Turning Point USA.
In 2018, Charlie Kirk and I traveled to the United Kingdom.
And it is there that I gave a notorious speech in November of 2018 where that clip was derived
from.
I'm going to show you that clip again in its context.
We were talking about things that were happening in the United States.
And somebody raised their hand and asked about the word nationalism, why we're also afraid
to say I'm a nationalist.
I am focused on my own nation.
And in trying to answer their question, I basically said because the word nationalism
has been wrongly attributed to Adolf Hitler, at least in America.
And that's why people are afraid to embrace the word.
Here are my words again.
I agree.
I actually don't have any problems at all with the word nationalism.
I think that the definition gets poisoned by a leader that actually wants globalism.
Globalism is what I don't want.
So whenever we say nationalism, the first thing people think about, at least in America,
is Hitler.
He was a national socialist.
But if Hitler just wanted to make Germany great and have things run well, okay, fine.
The problem is that he had dreams outside of Germany.
He wanted to globalize.
He wanted everybody to be German, everybody to be speaking German, everybody to look a
different way.
That's not to me, that's not nationalism.
So in thinking about how we could go bad down the line, I don't really have an issue with
nationalism.
I really don't.
I think that it's okay.
It's important to retain your country's identity and to make sure that what's happening
here, which I think is incredibly worse in terms of just the decrease in the birth rate
that we're seeing in the UK, is what you kind of want to avoid.
So I don't have anything problem.
I have no problems with nationalism.
It's globalism that I try to avoid.
Where you have it, I have no issues with nationalism.
There's no person that can watch that clip and somehow believe that I was saying it's
totally okay to holocaust the Jews.
I didn't even mention the word holocaust.
I didn't mention the word Jews.
Truly was answering a question about whether or not we should embrace the word nationalism,
but that didn't matter.
Now, again, I want to be clear that that clip that you're watching, that was recorded in
2018 at a live event in the UK.
And there were journalists at that event.
I was interviewed by journalists at that event.
About 200 people were in attendance amongst them.
Many Jewish people were in attendance.
Nobody cared.
Nobody thought it was problematic what I said on stage.
Fast forward to 2019 and out of nowhere, a journalist writing for Media Matters decided
to make that clip go viral online.
The journalist's name who made that clip go viral on Twitter was Jonathan Whitehouse.
Again, he writes for Media Matters and suddenly I woke up months after having given a speech
to every person calling for me to be canceled because I supported Adolf Hitler.
That's not a joke.
I'm showing you some headlines.
This Media Matters turning point USA's Candace Owens quote, if Hitler just wanted to make
Germany great and have things run well, okay, fine.
I have no problem with nationalism.
Wow, that's kind of making it seem very different from what I was actually saying.
Behind them Buzzfeed news, Candace Owens, if Hitler just wanted to make Germany great
and have things run well, okay, fine.
Again, no context giving stop quotations.
You can imagine the firestorm that was caused.
And Mediaite Candace Owens, Hitler's nationalism was actually fine.
It was his globalism that was a problem.
You can already see what they were trying to do.
And again, the firestorm that I endured, I will tell you something personal.
I was so stressed out by that event that I stressed myself into an autoimmune response.
My body was breaking down because I didn't understand what was happening.
I had never in my entire life been accused of anti-Semitism and suddenly I was fighting
for my career.
I was temporarily blacklisted from Fox News for having said this sentence, which suddenly
again was pulled out of obscurity.
And I quite literally was facing a threat that everything was going to be over because
how dare I say that?
I have absolutely no right to say that.
And then you had Jewish organizations that issued very strong statements against them,
among them the Simon Wiesenthal Center.
Here is a tweet from them when this was going viral back in February 18, sorry, back on
February 8, 2019, they wrote, scope and depth of Candace Owens's lack of knowledge of basic
history is appalling and frightening.
Hitler's program to make Germany great was based on race and anti-Semitism.
Also of course, the ADL instantly jumped on this.
They tweeted, they retweeted first and foremost John Whitehouse, so they helped to make this
video go viral.
And then they wrote this in response, Candace Owens bizarrely claims, Hitler went wrong
only when he meddled in other countries.
Hitler's murderous crimes against Jews and others were horrific, regardless of whether
they occurred across Europe or in Germany alone.
Hitler wasn't a globalist, but a genocidal dictator.
So you see what they're doing here.
They're just engaging in the libel and the slander.
They're trying to color people's opinions before they've actually heard or understood
the context of what I was saying.
And let me tell you guys something.
It worked.
It actually worked.
That is the power of the media.
I felt like it was a hit job.
Like someone just said, we've got to get her, pour through every second of footage of Candace
Owens speaking.
We're going to pull something out of context and this girl is going to be gone because
what else could this be?
Of course, if I was on stage saying I love Hitler, it would have gotten viral back in
November.
The Jewish people that attended my speech would have been outraged immediately.
Why was this suddenly popping up in February of 2019?
I'll never have an answer on that, but something that I never shared and I want to share today
was what happened thereafter.
A friend of mine who I am not going to name encouraged me to visit the Simon Wiesenthal
Center.
That's a human rights organization.
There was this very strange meeting that occurred.
I want to be clear that I didn't understand the meeting because the individuals were speaking
in Hebrew.
My understanding going into it was that once I spoke to this individual, things would be
clarified and then I could just go on living and my reputation would pretty much be restored.
And by golly, that's kind of what happened.
So again, it was an extremely old man.
I think he runs the place.
I don't know.
I can't remember his name, so I'm not going to make one up.
But I had to sit in the meeting and explain that I didn't think Hitler was a great person,
listen to two people speak Hebrew, and my reputation was restored.
Or at least I was allowed to go on pursuing what I wanted to pursue, which was just talking
about black Americans and the fracturing of the black and white relationship.
It's a very odd thing when I reflect on that.
But I want to be clear that the threats, the threats that can't just be over at any moment
for you, don't you get out of line again by saying something that you never actually
said, but don't make us have to threaten you again.
That I still always felt over me because it was just a very scary thing to go through.
We spend way too much time on our phones, which is bad enough as it is.
Perhaps even worse is that your phone carrier can track everything you're doing on your
phone, which is a gross invasion of privacy.
Many companies have even admitted to it.
They say it so they can, quote, unquote, better understand your interests.
But really, what they want is to sell your activity to advertisers, stuff like the sites
you visited and what you've been up to online.
More they can get on you of a larger their paycheck, which is why I use ExpressVPN.
It takes the top of a button and your network data is encrypted and rerouted through ExpressVPN's
secure servers for ultimate privacy.
ExpressVPN shields your web browsing and protects all of your network data so you can
stay private even when you're using your favorite apps.
Whether you're an iPhone, Android, or tablet user, ExpressVPN works on all of your devices.
The best part is that one subscription can be used on up to five devices at the same time.
Visit expressdpn.com slash canvas to get the same VPN that I use.
Use my link to get three extra months free at expresvpn.com slash canvas.
But let's fast forward now to 2022 to a situation that the entire world was made aware of, obviously.
When Ye, the artist formerly known as Kanye West, tweeted this.
He tweeted, I'm a bit sleepy tonight, but when I wake up, I'm going, death con three on Jewish people.
The funny thing is I actually can't be anti-Semitic because black people are actually Jew.
Also, you guys have toyed with me and tried to blackball anyone who ever opposes your agenda.
It's good to look at his tweet now without it being interpreted in the media, especially at Lawson.
You guys have toyed with me and tried to blackball anyone who ever opposes your agenda.
Now at that time, obviously, the reason why people were looking for me to make a statement
is that this tweet came very close to the time that I had taken the notorious picture with Kanye West.
We both wore white lives matter t-shirts at his fashion show in Paris.
Again, me teaming up with Kanye because I have a laser focus on the black community.
I had a laser focus on wanting to destroy black lives matter as an organization because I knew that they were lying to the black community.
Again, my entire relationship and what I did publicly with Kanye was based on black America.
Again, because this tweet came closely thereafter, people were looking at me to comment.
The truth is that I was aware behind the scenes.
Kanye gave me conversations.
I read them in their entirety of very specific Jewish people who I would say were definitively making threats against him.
And so I had more knowledge than the public had when he shared this tweet.
Now, what happened thereafter was I tried to caution the public the very next day following his tweet.
So he had done nothing else yet.
He had done no interviews.
It was just the tweet that existed in the public sphere.
And I was trying to essentially say to people, hold your horses because I think that once he explains what's happening behind the scenes,
you will realize that he's not talking about all Jewish people in the entire world.
He is feeling passionately about certain people that he works with.
And here is what I said in an attempt to get people to hold their horses.
Take a listen.
That was the tweets.
And people subsequently demanded that the tweet be taken down for anti-Semitism.
Now, if you are an honest person, you did not think this tweet was anti-Semitic.
You did not think that he wrote this tweet because he hates or wants to genocide Jewish people.
This does not represent the beginning of the Holocaust.
That's if you're an honest person, you'll admit that.
You will admit that.
Right?
If you're an honest person, when you read this tweet, you had no idea what the hell he was talking about.
I had no idea when I read this tweet what the hell he was talking about.
This tweet inspired questions, not answers.
First and foremost, what is death con three?
Did he mean death con three, which would be a military defense position, not an offense
for those of you that are offended, a military defense position?
Is he tweeting this because he's reading the Newsweek headline, calling him an anti-Semitic?
Is he angry because he can't believe that he's not free to talk about people in his
life who happen to be Jewish without being accused of anti-Semitism?
Is he saying, I'm not going to shut up and I'm going to keep tweeting and I'm going to
keep calling these people out, referring to his friends that he feels slighted by?
Is he talking about Jared Kushner and Josh Kushner?
If you're a liar, you'll say, I know I was scared, Candace.
I actually thought that Kanye West was going to launch a military strike in Israel because
that's the reaction, like when I woke up and I looked at the headlines, a reaction was
like Kanye West had gotten together a military strike and it was going to go forward in the
morning time in Israel.
That was the reaction that was met with this tweet.
So that's what I said.
And now that we're looking at it and examining it in the retrospect, you can see that I'm
trying to suggest to people that there are specific people and he is having a reaction.
And I will admit, if I fumbled the ball here and I can understand why people were upset
about it, they read that as no, she's fully defending him and he actually does want to
go death con three on all Jewish people everywhere.
People were very upset that I had said that.
But I want to be clear that I had actually read the messages that were being sent to
him.
One of them, he ended up sharing publicly, this was a text message from Harley-Pastronik
to Kanye.
And this was something again that I had read before he had sent that tweet.
Text message reads, I'm going to help you one of a couple of ways.
First, you and I sit down and have a loving and open conversation, but you don't use cuss
words and everything that is discussed is based in fact and not some crazy stuff that
dumb friend of yours told you or you saw on a tweet.
Second option, I have you institutionalized again, where they medicate the crap out of
you and you go back to Zomie Land forever.
The play date with the kids just won't be the same.
Is that a normal tweet?
I will ask you guys a normal text message, pardon, or somebody in your life and Harley-Pastronik,
yes, he is Jewish, to send to you.
He's supposed to be a trainer.
What do you mean I'll have you institutionalized again?
What does that mean?
Your play dates with the kid, you're threatening somebody's relationship with their kids, right?
Now when you do something like that, it can drive somebody crazy.
And again, I will own it if it read to people at that time that when I was saying that,
I was defending his right to impose upon every single Jewish person in the world, I apologize.
And I'm hoping that this clarifies for you what I knew, the information that I had, and
my understanding that he was responding to threats that he was actually getting from
specific people.
And I was hopeful that he would talk about that in a larger capacity, but then quite
surprised when even when he did share that tweet, there was a minimal media response
to it.
It was sort of like, oh well, Harley-Pastronik is allowed to say that.
And shame on you, Candace, for not recognizing it, but I want to be clear, that is the extent
what you just saw of my commentary on that situation that led to a huge reaction, calls
for me to resign, calls for me to get fired for defending Kanye West.
I want to be honest here and tell you that I was also made to endure a very severe financial
consequence behind the scenes because of those words that you heard right there.
And one day I will talk more about that.
You have my word.
Let's fast forward instead to 2023.
I'm scrolling through Twitter and a journalist, and again, this is just a few weeks after
October 7th.
And a journalist named Yashar Ali is, I think, being pretty measured in his responses.
I think he's pro-Israel based on how he tweets and what he tweets about.
But on this day, he was focused on something that Brian Mast, a congressman, had said on
the floor.
Yashar Ali tweeted, this is absolutely sick stuff from Rep.
Brian Mast.
And if there's any decency left in Congress, a resolution will be passed to condemn his
remarks and he'll be removed from the Foreign Affairs Committee.
I'm not naive enough to think he'd resign.
So I saw this tweet and then I clicked to see what Brian Mast said and I was equally
as disgusted.
Here is what Brian Mast said.
As a whole, I would encourage the other side to not so lightly throw around the idea of
innocent Palestinian civilians, as is frequently said.
I don't think we would so lightly throw around the term innocent Nazi civilians during World
War II.
I hope that enrages you because what he's basically saying is there's no such thing
as an innocent Palestinian life.
And basically, I believe, was laying the groundwork for genocide.
That's genocidal language to say about any group of people.
If I say there's no such thing as an innocent Iraqi, it doesn't matter who you're talking
about, that is genocidal language.
And so I retweeted this and I said, yeah, this was disgusting, utterly dehumanizing.
Of course there are innocent civilians on either side of every conflict and we should
not forget that.
This is shameful, inhumane rhetoric.
I shortly followed up that retweet with a blanket statement, no government anywhere
has a right to commit a genocide ever.
There was no justification for a genocide.
I can't believe this even needs to be said or is even considered the least bit controversial
to state.
Of course, what Brian Mast said was wrong.
When I tweeted that second tweet, people thought that I was talking about Israel or some people
thought I was talking about Israel.
They were so far in the trenches.
They thought when I was making a statement that Israel is committing a genocide.
But in reality, I was saying that people like Brian Mast need to cool it with their language.
I get something bad has happened, but you can't say stuff like this ever.
And so what happened was people who were formerly friends of mine, like Dave Rubin, began reading
into it, began doing shows, just pretending, straight up pretending that I made a statement
about the Israeli government when in fact I hadn't.
I just showed you the proof that I had not.
I liked your Shars tweet.
I retweeted it.
I was obviously speaking about Brian Mast, but it didn't matter because what I learned
and what I think a lot of people are learning and especially on the heels of my discussion
with Rabbi Barclay is that even if what you said was something else, how some people feel
should be prioritized.
So even though I was talking about Brian Mast and I was proven right in talking about Brian
Mast, I was still at fault.
I needed to understand that I was still wrong because of how other people felt that the
timing of my tweet wasn't right.
It wasn't the right time to say that genocide was always wrong.
There's a time and a place for that and that was not it.
And I got even weirder because people started just spinning conspiracy theories.
They started saying that I was coordinating with Tucker Carlson to intentionally get fired
from the Daily Wire.
I'm not kidding.
People were beginning to say, and Dave Ruhman was among these people, that it was so obvious,
so obvious.
Gosh, why else would someone say genocide is always wrong, right?
That I was trying to get hired by Tucker Carlson.
There must have been some coordination between us.
At 40 weeks pregnant, this was my big bad plan.
This was psychopathic.
None of this was true.
There wasn't an ounce of truth to that statement whatsoever.
In fact, I refer to this as aya non.
It's like Israel and non.
It was a conspiracy theory born of absolutely nothing, but the onslaught continued.
People attacking my character saying horrific things about me simply because I didn't like
what Brian Masth has said.
And of course, most notoriously, everybody remembers that a clip started circulating
of Ben Shapiro here at Daily Wire making ad hominid attacks on me, which I chose not
to respond to at that time.
I didn't think it was appropriate.
But that, of course, just fed more people that were attacking me.
Grand Canyon University is a private Christian university in beautiful Phoenix, Arizona.
GCU believes that our creator has endowed us with certain inalienable rights to life,
liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.
They believe in equal opportunities and that the American dream starts with purpose.
And they equip you to serve others in ways that promote human flourishing, creating a
ripple effect of transformation for generations to come.
So whether you're pursuing a bachelor's, master's, or doctoral degree, Grand Canyon
University's online, on-campus, and hybrid learning environments are designed to help
you achieve your goals.
GCU has over 330 academic programs as of September, 2023.
GCU will meet you where you are and provide a path to help you fulfill your unique academic,
personal, and professional ambitions.
Find your purpose today at Grand Canyon University, private, Christian, affordable.
Visit gcu.edu.
That's gcu.edu.
So what is the actual point of that?
The attacks have not stopped.
You've seen this.
You saw that.
In my conversation with Rabbi, he is now starting to share with everybody that I'm enraged.
You have Rabbi Shmueli.
She's deranged.
She just hates you so much.
Smear after smear after libel after libel after libel and it will not stop.
Two years of consistent threats and harassment from Rabbi Shmueli and his hag daughter, and
they have not let up.
They began, by the way, they jumped into the game on the basis of that clip that I just
showed you.
I'm not ashamed to show you guys what I said.
Because nothing was anti-Semitic.
I was just trying to tell people that more was happening behind the scenes.
That's it.
Not make any claims or yelling or saying all Jewish people are this or that.
And yet, people are saying definitively that I am a Jew hater.
I'm a Jew-hating bigot.
That's what Rabbi Barclay said.
What is the point of this?
I want you guys to actually ask yourself this.
When people say they're going to Michael Jackson, you, what are they actually referring to?
Well, I have a suspicion that what they mean is that all of these attacks are meant to
drive me crazy, right?
To drive someone crazy, to make threats to their life, to smear their reputation, to
libel them, to make them somebody who can't even be hired or work within a certain industry
because they have been so forceful in their lies and in their smears.
Basically, then to drive that person to a point of anger so that they might tweet something
that's angry, that they might tweet something that appears to be irrational to the public
so that they can turn around and they can say, told you so.
I told you, Kenneth, this was crazy.
I told you she was deranged.
I told you she was an anti-Semite, but what's really happening is that you have specific
people that are in the Jewish community that won't stop attacking me.
They won't stop attacking me.
I think most people after years of enduring this would in fact be driven crazy.
People actually just yesterday after listening to the full hour, hour and a half discussion
between Remy and Rabbi Barclay said, Kenneth, I don't know how you do it.
This would drive me crazy.
Yeah.
Add years of that.
Years of that.
Headline after, headline smear after smear and ask what sort of person would still remain
this calm.
I want to be clear.
What is happening is a form of psychological terrorism.
What they're doing to me is a form of psychological terrorism.
They want me to snap so that I can then prove their point.
Actually, my options are two.
Either we're going to keep smearing you until you snap or you can simply comply.
What is the thing that they want me to comply with?
I'm not sure.
I think I've been pretty rational and I've been pretty level headed.
I don't understand why they have been engaging in this sort of smearing.
This is why I'm terming this merchants of smear because what they're doing here is they're
constantly threatening people behind the scenes, publicly threatening people by smearing their
reputations and they never, ever, ever take a break.
This business just keeps going on and on and on and on.
The point is again to make me submit.
Another example of that.
This is rather shocking.
I'm kidding.
Yesterday, a journalist, and I'm putting this into quotation marks, despite all of the debunking
that I did in that long article, in that long interview with Rabbi Barclay, already was
jumping on the next smear.
His name is Isaac Schor.
He writes for, you guessed it, Mediate as well as the New York Post.
He is now publicly calling to have me fired.
He's written a lot of articles, by the way.
He talks to a lot of people behind the scenes telling them not to run any pieces on Candace
Owens.
Don't talk about Candace Owens.
This guy's like, you know, doing a real hit job here.
And like a total rational journalist, he tweeted, how long will the Daily Wire stand by Candace
Owens?
No one is asking the Daily Wire to stop Owens from peddling hatred and conspiracy theories.
They're just wondering why it's choosing to subsidize such behavior.
Yeah, totally a rational thing for a journalist to tweet.
He accompanied that with an article by the same title, How Long Would the Daily Wire
Stand by Candace Owens?
Because as you've seen, I've showed you the whole history.
Aren't you convinced yet?
They've written so many articles.
Psychological terrorists, they told you a thousand times in anti-Semites, so it must
be true.
And why would anyone hire and stand by a raging anti-Semite?
They've said it so many times, guys.
And he wasn't done.
He wrote a second headline yesterday published on Mediate.
I don't know, just enraged at the fact that I had to sit down and spoke rationally to
Rabbi Barclay.
I don't know what's driving this.
But here's the headline, Candace Owens Endorses Wild Anti-Semitic Conspiracy Theory About
Jews Being Drunk on Christian Blood.
That is the headline, you guys.
You've been listening to this show.
Have you ever heard me endorse a conspiracy theory about Jews being drunk on Christian
blood?
How sick and how sinister is this getting?
How utterly insane this is all getting?
It's starting to feel like there's some sort of a bounty on my head and the person that
can convince the public of something that is so ridiculous that I can't come back from
is just going to receive a ton of money.
And Isaac Shore is really competing for that because do you want to know where he got that
conspiracy theory from?
A tweet that I had liked of someone defending me when Rabbi Shmueli was smearing me.
He dug up an old tweet of mine that was from February, tried to present it as if it was
something new and something that was about him before our back and forth ever even broke
out.
So I liked the tweet because it clarified the right date of the tweet, saying that Rabbi
Shmueli, this tweet is obviously from February 20th.
What are you drunk on Christian blood?
Didn't even pay attention to the last part of the tweet.
I was just obviously liked that this person was calling out this BS smearing tactic.
Little did I know that Isaac Shore and a team of journalists are now monitoring every single
like of mine on Twitter to see if they can convince the public that I am advocating for
insanity.
This is how desperate they have become.
So I'll ask the question, what are we actually witnessing here?
Do you believe Isaac Shore is a victim?
Did you believe that he is a person who genuinely in his heart thinks that I think Jews are
running around drinking Christian blood by that headline?
Do you think that Rabbi Barclay is a victim?
Do you honestly believe his interpretation that I was the one who owed the apology to
him and the Jewish community on the basis that I just won't let them keep trying to
smear me out of existence, specific people in the Jewish community?
God forbid, did she defend herself against Rabbi Shmueli?
Do you believe Rabbi Shmueli is a victim?
When you listen to these individuals speak and the things that they are publicizing,
does that register to you as true victimhood?
Because what it registers to me as is power, real power hiding behind a veneer of victimhood,
the kind of power that can take somebody out and end their entire career if that person
says something that they don't like.
And in this case, it's not that I'm saying things that they don't like, it's that I'm
refusing to allow my voice to be controlled.
I want to be clear to you guys.
I'm going to be honest with you because everybody's noticing it.
Every single political commentator in America, every single one of them knows this.
That if you do not step out and say things that are radically pro-Israel or if you are
too quiet on certain narratives and they want you to be radically pro-Israel, you can lose
everything.
That's truth.
That is a fact.
I'm not feeling like I need to hide from that anymore because or be afraid to say it rather,
as a better way to say it, because I've endured this for years.
I'm just at the end of my rope.
I have given so much rope here and I am just done with it.
Every person that you are a fan of, they know this.
Every person that you line up to go here speak, they know this.
Again, it's not even on the basis of what you say.
It can sometimes be on the basis of what you don't say.
That an entire mob will assemble.
You'll write piece after piece after piece until you subjugate.
If you don't subjugate, the bounty grows larger.
Yes, there was a large bounty on my head for the crime of refusing to suddenly hate Muslims
and to condone Muslims getting bombed following October 7th.
Everybody can see that.
I have said nothing controversial because genuinely I was sad when a bunch of innocent
Israelis were murdered and killed in horrific acts and genuinely I am sad when a bunch of
innocent Palestinians, and yes, they do exist, Brian Mast, are now being made to endure bombing
and all sorts of other horrific things that we are all seeing on Twitter.
That is my crime.
Everybody can see that.
It's ridiculous to pretend that it's anything else.
There's no language that I have to use.
There's nothing insane that I have said other than I would like to treat all races the same.
I refuse to be a supremacist.
I refuse to condone supremacy.
That is my crime.
So what I want to do here for all of you guys that are worried and that is going to happen
to me is to just provide this full accounting of everything that I have ever done and everything
that I have ever said that has been deemed controversial from this mafia, right, this
mafia of journalists that will not let up and leave me alone.
Because that's what it is.
What is it?
What else could it possibly be?
You're acting like a mafia.
You are threatening me.
You are taking my words out of context.
You are telling people to fire me on the basis that I just won't be radical, on the basis
that I won't hate on command.
It's not about love, it's about hate.
You want me to hate on command.
I want to be clear that what these journalists are engaging in is evil.
It is absolute evil to do this to any person.
I'm not going to be driven crazy by it.
In fact, I'm going to be driven to more clarity by it.
I'm going to grow stronger from this.
I'm going to be a person that is more encouraged to speak out on what is happening to me.
I want the public to see what is happening to me because I think they know my heart and
they know that what I'm actually doing is refusing hatred.
Balance of nature fruits and veggies is the most convenient way to get whole food ingredients
daily.
Balance of nature uses an advanced cold vacuum process that encapsulates fruits and vegetables
into whole food supplements without sacrificing their natural antioxidants.
These capsules are void of additives, fillers, extracts, synthetics, pesticides, or added
sugar.
The only thing that's in balance of nature's fruits and veggies capsules are fruits and
veggies.
Imagine trying to eat 31 different fruits and vegetables every day.
That's impossible.
With balance of nature, getting your daily fruits and vegetables is easier than ever.
Go to balanceofnature.com and use promo code CANDIS to get 35% off your first set of fruits
and veggies and an additional $10 off every additional set that you buy.
That's balanceofnature.com promo code CANDIS.
I saw this video, by the way, further to that point of Anna Kasparian.
Her and I have basically been on the opposite sides of everything throughout our entire
career.
She has said horrible things about me, but so what?
I thought this video was interesting and I'm going to show you what she said regarding
A-PAC.
A-PAC is evil.
A-PAC is evil, evil.
My fellow Americans, are you okay with that?
Are you okay with a lobbying group representing the best interests of a foreign government
telling you, you need to bust your ass every day, work your job that you likely hate, and
have a portion of your earnings taken from you by our federal government and funneled
to the Israeli government so they can commit atrocities in the Gaza Strip?
Are you okay with that?
Because I'm not okay with that and nothing gets under my skin more, okay?
And hearing these pieces of crap, say things that make it clear that they feel entitled
to our money, entitled, entitled.
That gets under my skin more than you guys understand, okay?
That's an impassioned response and what she's referring to there are some leaked documents
from an A-PAC meeting.
A-PAC, of course, alongside Big Pharma, is one of the biggest lobbying organizations in
the United States.
We are congressmen and I'm certain that that includes journalists because we have a budget
like A-PAC.
Why wouldn't you be lobbying journalists as well to essentially always fight to have
pro-Israel narratives?
And again, I want to be clear.
I am not anti-Israel.
This is what is so wild about all of this.
I'm just not anti-Palestinian.
And so I hear what she is saying and I believe that what is happening right now in this country
politically is an evil.
It is wrong.
It is completely ridiculous to have a bunch of people that are fearful to speak and say
rational things, rational things that they know to be true because they know they can
lose everything.
Because they know that a bunch of journalists will pop up like a game of whack-a-mole and
try to spin things that you have said to make them much more nefarious than what you actually
intended when you say them because they know that these journalists have power.
Because they know that these journalists will not stop the onslaught.
And eventually people are going to cave.
And I can't tell you guys how wrong this is.
It is so wrong that every fiber of my being now wants to expose this.
I want to invite each and every journalist that is going to continue to engage with me
in this fight onto my show.
So I, as a chore, take this as a public invite for you to come down to sit with me and to
explain to everybody why you really believed that I think Jews drink Christian blood.
You wrote that article because you really believed it.
You're actually a good guy.
I'm sure you are.
I'm going to sit here quietly.
I'm going to allow you to explain yourself why you have written so many articles about
me and why you believe that I have to be fired because you actually believe, as you've written
in past articles, that people like me and Tucker Carlson were anti-Semites.
Further to that note, further to me believing that the solution to all of this is simply
daylight, daylight being the best of disinfectants.
I have publicly offered to Rabbi Barclay who wants me to watch the IDF footage.
That not only will I watch the footage, but I am challenging him to use his contacts to
also get me a trip to Israel and Gaza.
Allow me to be a reporter on the ground.
People feel like they're being propagandized about the matter one way or the other.
So why not send somebody who I think I've earned the trust of the American public?
I'm not someone that will ever be bought and paid for.
I'm not someone that will ever say things that I know to be untrue.
Why not allow me to go?
I'll talk to IDF, show us how to talk to Netanyahu, but I also want to speak to people that are
impacted by this in Gaza.
I want to see what's going on in Gaza.
Why not allow someone like me to go there and I've offered that I will bring other journalists
that I think are middle of the line, not one way or the other.
Simply reporting on the matters and similarly having to endure a bunch of threats and a bunch
of smears.
But like my friend who's just a commentator, Dave Smith, a Jewish person who is now being
told that he's a self-hating Jew because he won't get in line and I don't know, deliver
the APAC talking points.
People have a right to know what is going on, especially when it is so significant that
you're willing to take out people for not saying the right thing.
So my offer stands, anybody who wants to write an article or smear me or libel me, you are
invited to this show.
Hopefully they'll take up my offer.
Hopefully in a few weeks I will be out to Israel and I will be out to Gaza and I will
be able to report to you guys what it is that I actually see, but I also want to say this
because it's so important.
I am team God.
I'm team God.
I do not fear the media.
I do not fear journalists.
I do not fear APAC.
I don't fear big pharma.
What I actually fear is God.
I think that one day we are all going to have to account for the things that we have done
and the things that we have said and I want to make sure that I am not a person that is
parroting lies.
The fear of losing your job, encouraging some people to spit out lies, I don't think that
works in the end.
I think you've got to check your priorities.
And so with that said, I want to thank everybody who has been on this journey with me, people
that have supported me.
I especially want to thank all of the Jewish people that have been in the comments saying
how outraged they are.
And I know that it is especially difficult for you guys right now because you are being
smeared.
I mean, I'm not going to go away.
I'm going to use my God-given voice to talk about the things that are important for me.
I'm just asking to be left alone or at least just report the truth.
Ladies and gentlemen, unfortunately, that is all the time that we have for today.
But don't worry because we will see you tomorrow for a brand new episode.